<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">mSphere</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">mSphere</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2989</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">msphere</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mSphere</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>mSphere</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2379-5042</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology (ASM)</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4899885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4899885.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4899885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4899885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27303751</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00117-16</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mSphere00117-16</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecological and Evolutionary Science</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>IncM Plasmid R1215 Is the Source of Chromosomally Located Regions Containing Multiple Antibiotic Resistance Genes in the Globally Disseminated <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> GC1 and GC2 Clones</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> One-Step Multiple Resistance</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short-authors">Blackwell et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names initials="GA">Grace A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3614-7261</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidian</surname><given-names initials="M">Mohammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2062-3312</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names initials="RM">Ruth M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">School of Molecular Bioscience, The University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blokesch</surname><given-names initials="M">Melanie</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><aff>Swiss Federal Institute of Technology Lausanne</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to Ruth M. Hall, <email>ruth.hall@sydney.edu.au</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="present-address"><label>*</label><p>Present address: Grace A. Blackwell, Mohammad Hamidian, and Ruth M. Hall, School of Life and Environmental Sciences, The University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation</bold> Blackwell GA, Hamidian M, Hall RM. 2016. IncM plasmid R1215 is the source of chromosomally located regions containing multiple antibiotic resistance genes in the globally disseminated <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> GC1 and GC2 clones. mSphere 1(3):e00117-16. doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00117-16">10.1128/mSphere.00117-16</ext-link>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">270338</issue-id><elocation-id>e00117-16</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-21 20:25:10.853"><day>21</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 Blackwell et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Blackwell et al.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="mSphere.00117-16.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="sph003162102001.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p>Two lineages of extensively antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> currently plaguing modern medicine each acquired resistance to all of the original antibiotics (ampicillin, tetracycline, kanamycin, and sulfonamides) by the end of the 1970s and then became resistant to antibiotics from newer families after they were introduced in the 1980s. Here, we show that, in both of the dominant globally disseminated <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clones, a related set of antibiotic resistance genes was acquired together from the same resistance region that had already evolved in an IncM plasmid. In both cases, the action of IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> was important in this process, but homologous recombination was also involved. The findings highlight the fact that complex regions carrying several resistance genes can evolve in one location or organism and all or part of the evolved region can then move to other locations and other organisms, conferring resistance to several antibiotics in a single step.</p></abstract><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Clear similarities between antibiotic resistance islands in the chromosomes of extensively antibiotic-resistant isolates from the two dominant, globally distributed <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> clones, GC1 and GC2, suggest a common origin. A close relative of the likely progenitor of both of these regions was found in R1215, a conjugative IncM plasmid from a <italic toggle="yes">Serratia marcescens</italic> strain isolated prior to 1980. The 37.8-kb resistance region in R1215 lies within the <italic toggle="yes">mucB</italic> gene and includes <italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aphA1b</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>TEM</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">catA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A), genes that confer resistance to gentamicin, streptomycin and spectinomycin, kanamycin and neomycin, ampicillin, chloramphenicol, sulfamethoxazole, and tetracycline, respectively. The backbone of this region is derived from Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> and is interrupted by a hybrid Tn<italic toggle="yes">2670</italic> (Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic>)-Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic>-type transposon, Tn<italic toggle="yes">6020</italic>, and an incomplete Tn<italic toggle="yes">1</italic>. After minor rearrangements, this R1215 resistance island can generate AbGRI2-0*, the predicted earliest form of the IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-bounded AbGRI2-type resistance island of GC2 isolates, and to the multiple antibiotic resistance region (MARR) of AbaR0, the precursor of this region in AbaR-type resistance islands in the GC1 group. A 29.9-kb circle excised by IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> has been inserted into the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> chromosome to generate AbGRI2-0*. To create the MARR of AbaR0, a different circular form, again generated by IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> from an R1215 resistance region variant, has been opened at a different point by recombination with a copy of the <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic> gene already present in the AbaR precursor. Recent IncM plasmids related to R1215 have a variant resistance island containing a <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>SHV</sub> gene in the same location.</p><p><bold>IMPORTANCE</bold> Two lineages of extensively antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> currently plaguing modern medicine each acquired resistance to all of the original antibiotics (ampicillin, tetracycline, kanamycin, and sulfonamides) by the end of the 1970s and then became resistant to antibiotics from newer families after they were introduced in the 1980s. Here, we show that, in both of the dominant globally disseminated <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clones, a related set of antibiotic resistance genes was acquired together from the same resistance region that had already evolved in an IncM plasmid. In both cases, the action of IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> was important in this process, but homologous recombination was also involved. The findings highlight the fact that complex regions carrying several resistance genes can evolve in one location or organism and all or part of the evolved region can then move to other locations and other organisms, conferring resistance to several antibiotics in a single step.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS:</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>genomic resistance islands</kwd><kwd>IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic></kwd><kwd>IncM plasmid</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded in part by School of Molecular Bioscience, University of Sydney. The efforts of Grace A. Blackwell and Mohammad Hamidian were supported by Australian Postgraduate Awards.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="31"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="5602"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May/June 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="h0.0"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Gram-negative bacteria share a relatively small number of genes that confer resistance to the original antibiotics (such as ampicillin, tetracycline, kanamycin, and sulfonamides). These genes have all been shown to be included within mobile elements that facilitate their spread, namely, compound or class I transposons, class II transposons, or class 1 integrons and their associated gene cassettes. In early resistant isolates, the transposons were generally intact. However, over time more complex resistance regions have emerged as various mobile elements have acted on one another. These regions include several resistance genes either in transposons located within other transposons, such as Tn<italic toggle="yes">2670</italic> (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) or Tn<italic toggle="yes">4</italic> (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). They are frequently found in plasmids that carry horizontal transfer functions, allowing them to spread into multiple strains and species. For example, Tn<italic toggle="yes">2670</italic>, which includes Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic>, and Tn<italic toggle="yes">10</italic> were first found in the FIIA plasmid NR1 (or R100) in the late 1950s (reviewed in reference <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic> was found in the IncP plasmid R1033 in 1979 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), and Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> was found in pRSD1 in 1979 (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). As further events took place, resistance genes were both added and lost, and rearrangements also occurred, these regions evolved to become increasingly complex arrangements of a series of fragments, each derived from an original transposon. Indeed, as many complete plasmid sequences have become available, evidence has emerged that much of the evolution of large resistance regions occurs within the boundaries of a transposon that is located in a specific position. For example, the class 1 integron in SGI1 genomic islands found in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Proteus</italic> chromosomes has many internal configurations (reviewed in reference <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), many A/C plasmids carry a form of the ARI-A resistance island (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), which has a fixed location but varied gene content (reviewed in reference <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), and evolution of a resistance region <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> has also been reported for IncHI1 plasmids (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) and IncL/M plasmids (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The final arrangements can include characteristic specific junctions, such as the exact location of a transposon or insertion sequence (IS), or the junction between regions derived from different mobile elements, which allow larger complex regions with a shared history to be identified.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is an important nosocomial pathogen whose treatment is increasingly problematic due to high levels of antibiotic resistance. Both globally disseminated clones, global clones 1 and 2 (GC1 and GC2), contain several antibiotic resistance genes in chromosomally located resistance islands that are made up of transposons and fragments of transposons. GC1 isolates carry a single region designated AbaR (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">–</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), whereas two resistance islands are found in most GC2 isolates (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">–</xref><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The multiple antibiotic resistance region (MARR) in the center of AbaR islands in GC1 isolates and AbGRI2, found in recent GC2 isolates, have been found to share some features (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Recently, we determined the structure of AbGRI2 of the earlier GC2 reference, RUH134/A320, which was isolated in 1982, and we predicted the ancestral arrangement, AbGRI2-0* (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), which is shown in the top line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>. Comparison of AbGRI2-0* to the MARR of AbaR0, the ancestral AbaR island (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), revealed large regions of identical sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), suggesting a common origin. However, both resistance islands contain sequence that is not present in the other (highlighted in yellow in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), indicating that the source should include both of these segments.</p><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 1 </label><caption><p>Relationship between AbGRI2-0* and the MARR of AbaR0. Thick blue lines depict adjacent chromosomal sequence portions. The thick black solid and dashed lines indicate sequences within the resistance island of AbGRI2-0* and the MARR of AbaR0. Arrows below diagrams indicate the extent and orientation of some of the genes and open reading frames, with antibiotic resistance genes shown in color IS are boxes and the internal arrow depict the orientation of the <italic toggle="yes">tnp</italic> transposase gene. The boxes highlighted in pink are IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>, and an asterisk indicates that the IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> is 3 nucleotides different from the standard sequence. White and gray boxes represent IS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic> and IS<italic toggle="yes">6100</italic>, respectively, and IS<italic toggle="yes">6100</italic>Δ is drawn above the main line. Inverted repeats are shown as vertical lines. The lines above indicate regions of identical sequence, while sequences within the yellow boxes are unique to each island. The corresponding locus tag of the gene interrupted by AbGRI2-0* from the genome of A1 (GenBank accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP010781">CP010781</ext-link>) is provided. The thick maroon lines represent the backbone transposons of AbaR0.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sph0031621020001.jpg"/></fig><p>Here, an IncM plasmid, R1215, recovered from a <italic toggle="yes">Serratia marcesens</italic> strain that was isolated in or prior to 1980 and stored as NCTC 50331 in the National Collection of Type Cultures was found to contain resistance genes present in AbGRI2 and AbaR-type resistance regions, and the plasmid sequence was determined. The R1215 resistance island was compared to both the AbaR MARR and AbGRI2.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="h1"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s1.1"><title>Structure of R1215.</title><p>A group of 16 <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strains containing plasmids of known incompatibility type obtained from the United Kingdom National Collection of Type Cultures (NCTC) for use as references for PCR-based replicon typing was screened for resistance phenotype and, using PCR, for resistance and other genes as described elsewhere (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). We noticed that R1215, which confers resistance to ampicillin, chloramphenicol, gentamicin, kanamycin, streptomycin, sulfonamide, and tetracycline, contained all of the genes found in the AbaR islands of multiply antibiotic-resistant isolates belonging to GC1 of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Specifically, R1215 contained a class 1 integron with the <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic> gene in the 3′-conserved segment (3′-CS), the gene cassette array <italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>-orfP-orfP-orfQ-<italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic> (conferring resistance to gentamicin and spectinomycin), and a <italic toggle="yes">merA</italic> gene identical to that found in Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic>. It also included the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>TEM</sub> ampicillin resistance gene, the <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(A) tetracycline resistance determinant, <italic toggle="yes">catA1</italic>, which confers resistance to chloramphenicol, and the <italic toggle="yes">aphA1b</italic> kanamycin and neomycin resistance gene. Using primers designed to amplify the MARR of AbaR (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), some of the characteristic junctions were found to be present in R1215.</p><p>As it was a possible source of the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> resistance islands, the plasmid was purified and sequenced. The sequence reads assembled into three contigs, which were linked by PCR, with the final structure confirmed by restriction digestion. R1215 is a 95,855-bp plasmid (GenBank accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KU315015">KU315015</ext-link>) that belongs to the IncM1 incompatibility group, as recently defined by Carattoli and coworkers (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The antibiotic resistance genes were clustered together in a 37,808-bp region that interrupts the <italic toggle="yes">mucB</italic> gene and is surrounded by a 5-bp duplication of the target site (5′-AAATA-3′). The plasmid backbone obtained by removing the resistance region was found to be 99.9% identical to the backbone of several IncM plasmids for which sequences are available in GenBank (the closest relatives are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref> and described in more detail below). Like these plasmids, R1215 includes a set of genes required for conjugative transfer. R1215 was shown to conjugate by transferring it into an <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> recipient. All resistances associated with the donor strain were transferred, and the <italic toggle="yes">repM</italic> replicon was shown to be present in the transconjugants.</p><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 1 </label><caption><p>IncM1 plasmids related to R1215</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmidsize (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBankID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yrisolated</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Backbonesize (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI size(bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistancegenespresent</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R1215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95,856</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KU315015">KU315015</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. marcescens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;1980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58,043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,808</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">aphA1b</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>TEM</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">catA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A), <italic toggle="yes">merA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pACM1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89,977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KJ541681">KJ541681</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">K. oxytoca</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58,130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,842</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>SHV-5</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">dfrA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.1"><sup>a</sup></xref>, <italic toggle="yes">aacA4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">merA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pIGT15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74,839</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KP294351">KP294351</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47,849<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,985</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>SHV-5</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">aacA4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">merA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pARM26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86,948</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KP294350">KP294350</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncultured</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58,128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,815</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>SHV-5</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">aacA4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">merA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p202c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79,502</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KM406490">KM406490</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albania</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1985</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,483<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>SHV-5</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">aacA4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">merA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab1.1" fn-type="other"><label>a</label><p>pACM1 contains two copies of the <italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic> gene.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab1.2" fn-type="other"><label>b</label><p>Missing 10.28 kb in the backbone, including <italic toggle="yes">radC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">rmoA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">klcA</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab1.3" fn-type="other"><label>c</label><p>There is a 4.35-kb deletion in the backbone left of the RI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s1.2"><title>Structure of the resistance region.</title><p>The resistance region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>) is bounded by remnants of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and the <italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A) tetracycline resistance determinant is present at the right-hand end. A transposon with a hybrid Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic>-Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic> backbone is found close to IRRI of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic>, and at the <italic toggle="yes">tnp</italic> end of this transposon the sequence extends into the <italic toggle="yes">catA1</italic>-IS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic> configuration found next to Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic> in Tn<italic toggle="yes">2670</italic>. However, the outer end of IS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic> has been truncated by 32 bp due to the insertion of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1</italic>, carrying the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>TEM</sub> gene, and at the other end the Tn<italic toggle="yes">1</italic> has itself been truncated by IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> and lacks the final 129 bp at the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>TEM</sub> end. The IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> forms one end of Tn<italic toggle="yes">6020</italic>, an IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-bounded transposon, which includes the <italic toggle="yes">aphA1b</italic> gene that was originally found in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The final fragment is composed of one end of a transposon related to Tn<italic toggle="yes">1000</italic> and a small internal fragment of Tn<italic toggle="yes">5393</italic>c, followed by IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>; again, this configuration was first seen in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The length and identity of the various segments are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>.</p><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 2 </label><caption><p>Resistance island in R1215. Thick green lines indicate adjacent plasmid backbone, and black lines represent sequence of the resistance island. The extent and orientation of some of the genes and open reading frames are indicated by the arrows below the line, and antibiotic resistance genes are shown in color. The origin of different DNA segments is shown above. Insertion sequences are shown as boxes with arrows above indicating the orientation of the <italic toggle="yes">tnp</italic> transposase gene and numbers inside indicating the identity of the IS. IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>* differs by 3 nucleotides from the standard sequence of IS<italic toggle="yes">26.</italic> Inverted repeats are shown as vertical lines. The <italic toggle="yes">attI1</italic> site of the class 1 integron is shown as a tall open box, and each narrow box represents a cassette with a vertical bar that indicates the <italic toggle="yes">attC</italic> site. The 5-bp target site duplication flanking the island is underlined.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sph0031621020002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 2 </label><caption><p>Modules in the resistance region in R1215</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Regionno.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Length(bp)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Progenitor<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Region orgene(s)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Identity(%)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length(bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBankaccession no.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.2"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portionpresent<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.3"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,707</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AB366441.1">AB366441.1</ext-link><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.4"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9422–11128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ΔorfI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">820</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">820</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AY123253">AY123253</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,883<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">1000</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/X60200">X60200</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2883</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">685</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">5393c</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,470</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF313472">AF313472</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2968–3652</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic toggle="yes">tnpR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">6020</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/FJ172370">FJ172370</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–3069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">aphA1b</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,820</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,949</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HM804085">HM804085</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130–4949</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>TEM</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">tnpR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">2670</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,760</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AP000342">AP000342</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38–6301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ΔIS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">catA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tnpR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tnpM</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">731</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">768</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AP000342">AP000342</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38–768</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ΔIS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,672</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF071413">AF071413</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–4039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tnpR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tnpM</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,371</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CS<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.6"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,371</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/U12338">U12338</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CS<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.6"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,908</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cassettes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,908</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF453999">AF453999</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2908</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">aacC1</italic>-orfP-orfP-orfQ-<italic toggle="yes">aadA1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,731</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/U12338">U12338</ext-link></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8285–16318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3′-CS<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.6"><sup>f</sup></xref>-IS<italic toggle="yes">6100</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">mer1696</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,568</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/X61367">X61367</ext-link><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.4"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–5568</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">tetR</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">tetA</italic>(A)-pecM-Δ<italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab2.1" fn-type="other"><label>a</label><p>The analysis begins with the first base of the resistance region in R1215 (GenBank accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KU315015">KU315015</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.2" fn-type="other"><label>b</label><p>The accession number used was either that for the earliest complete sequence or for the complete and annotated sequence.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.3" fn-type="other"><label>c</label><p>Numbering for an IS includes the transposase gene from left to right; for class II Tn, the <italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic> gene is on the left.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.4" fn-type="other"><label>d</label><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/X61367">X61367</ext-link> is the original complete GenBank entry for Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic>, but this sequence has several single-base differences and a short deletion which are also not present in other published sequences of this region and might be errors.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.5" fn-type="other"><label>e</label><p>Of the region’s length, 209 bp were 99.6% identical to a Tn<italic toggle="yes">1000</italic>-like element found in GenBank sequence accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AY598759">AY598759</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.6" fn-type="other"><label>f</label><p>5′-CS and 3′-CS are the 5′-conserved segment and 3′-conserved segment of a class 1 integron.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Not only does the R1215 resistance region carry the same cassette array as AbaR0 (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), but also all of the boundaries between the DNA segments derived from different sources are identical to those in AbaR and AbGRI2 islands (indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref> in reference <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Furthermore, the two segments that are present only in either AbaR or in AbGRI2 islands (highlighted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>) are both present in R1215. These features are consistent with the resistance region of R1215 being the source or closely related to the source of the antibiotic resistance genes in both of the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> resistance islands.</p></sec><sec id="s1.3"><title>From R1215 to AbGRI2-0*.</title><p>To simplify the description of the pathway to AbaR0 and AbGRI2-0*, we invoked precursors RI-a and RI-b for the R1215 resistance region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). In both precursors, the region between the outer copies of IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> is inverted relative to the R1215 RI, and this could have occurred via recombination between two inversely oriented copies of IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>. In RI-a, the IS<italic toggle="yes">6100</italic> at the right end of the class 1 integron is followed by a partial copy of the same IS. This configuration is seen in In4 of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic>, but the duplication can be lost by homologous recombination (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). An alignment of RI-a with AbGRI2-0* is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>. A deletion generated by the IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> on the left (in replicative mode) creates a circular molecule or translocatable unit (TU) (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). This TU was then incorporated into the gene corresponding to ABA1_01225 in A1 (GenBank accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP010781">CP010781</ext-link>) in the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> genome, again likely using the replicative mode to generate the second IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> bounding AbGRI2-0* and the 8-bp target site duplication.</p><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 3 </label><caption><p>Conversion of the resistance island in R1215 to AbGRI2-0* and the MARR of AbaR0. (A) Predicted precursor RI-a and RI-b of the R1215 resistance island. (B) Relationship between RI-a and AbGRI2-0*. (C) Relationship between RI-b and the MARR of AbaR0. Thick solid green, blue, and black lines represent sequences of the plasmid backbone, chromosome, or the resistance island, respectively. The arrows below indicate the extent and orientation of some of the genes and open reading frames. Antibiotic resistance genes are shown in color. Inverted repeats are shown as vertical lines. Insertion sequences are shown as boxes, and pink, white, and gray boxes represent IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>, IS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic>, and IS<italic toggle="yes">6100</italic>, respectively. An asterisk indicates the IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> is 3 nucleotides different from the standard sequence. The arrows within the boxes indicate the orientation of the <italic toggle="yes">tnp</italic> transposase gene. The <italic toggle="yes">attI1</italic> site of the class 1 integron is shown as a tall open box, and each narrow box represents a cassette with a vertical bar that indicates the <italic toggle="yes">attC</italic> site. In panels B and C, gray blocks of shading and dashed and solid lines between the rows indicate regions of identical sequence.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sph0031621020003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.4"><title>From R1215 to AbaR0.</title><p>RI-b contains all of the regions of the MARR of AbaR0 but in a different order, as shown in the alignment in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>. Multiple steps are required for the evolution from RI-b to AbaR0. First, an inversion between regions of high identity in <italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic> of Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic> of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> creates a hybrid <italic toggle="yes">tnpA</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). This hybrid is composed of 1,418 bp of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> and 401 bp of Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic> as present in AbaR0. Second, a different deletion, again generated by the IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> on the left in replicative mode and extending to 446 bp into Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>), would create a TU. Finally, this TU could then be incorporated into the GC1 <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> chromosome, where another <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic> was already present, through homologous recombination between the two copies of the <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 4 </label><caption><p>Evolution of the MARR of AbaR0 from RI-b. (A) RI-b configuration, showing the segment inverted by homologous recombination. (B) IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-mediated TU formation. (C) Incorporation of the TU into the GC1 chromosome by homologous recombination. Thick solid green lines indicate adjacent plasmid backbone portions, and black solid and dashed lines represent sequence of the resistance island. The arrows below indicate the extent and orientation of some of the genes and open reading frames, with antibiotic resistance genes shown in color. Insertion sequences are shown as boxes with arrows inside, indicating the orientation of the <italic toggle="yes">tnp</italic> transposase gene. The boxes highlighted in pink, white, and gray represent IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>, IS<italic toggle="yes">1</italic>, and IS<italic toggle="yes">6100</italic>, respectively, and the asterisks indicate where the IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> is 3 nucleotides different from the standard sequence. Inverted repeats are shown as vertical lines. The <italic toggle="yes">attI1</italic> site of the class 1 integron is shown as a tall open box.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sph0031621020004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.5"><title>R1215 is not stably maintained in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</title><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> containing R1215 was mated with rifampin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 (17978-Rif<sup>r</sup>), using kanamycin, or ampicillin, or kanamycin, ampicillin, spectinomycin, gentamicin, and tetracycline to select for transfer. On two separate occasions, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> resistant to kanamycin (17978-Rif<sup>r</sup>Km<sup>r</sup>) was recovered but was not resistant to the other antibiotics. The <italic toggle="yes">aphA1b</italic> gene was detected by PCR in the 17978-Rif<sup>r</sup> Km<sup>r</sup> colonies, accounting for the phenotype, but the IncM replicon was not detected, indicating that R1215 had entered the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> recipient but could not be maintained in it. In R1215, the <italic toggle="yes">aphA1b</italic> gene is located in Tn<italic toggle="yes">6020</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> 17978-Rif<sup>r</sup>Km<sup>r</sup> was screened to determine if the gene was still located in this transposon. Tn<italic toggle="yes">6020</italic> was present, presumably incorporated into the genome, but the location was not determined.</p></sec><sec id="s1.6"><title>Related IncM1 plasmids carrying the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>SHV-5</sub> gene.</title><p>Some more recent plasmids (listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>) include a resistance region in the same location as in R1215. The structure of the resistance regions is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>. In each case, the right-hand end is identical to that in R1215 except for an additional <italic toggle="yes">aacA4</italic> gene cassette in the integron. The left-hand end from the IR of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> to the first IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> is also present in three of them, but an IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-mediated deletion has removed a short segment in pACM1. The presence of the same Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic>-Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> boundary in this region and in AbaR has been noted (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). In p202c, the left end has been removed together with flanking backbone sequence via an IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-mediated deletion. The <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>SHV-5</sub> gene is in an IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-bounded transposon in each plasmid, though in p202c the internal segment is inverted.</p><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 5 </label><caption><p>Resistance islands found in the <italic toggle="yes">mucB</italic> gene in the M1 backbone. Thick solid green lines indicate adjacent plasmid backbone portions. Solid horizontal lines represent the sequence of the resistance island, with the extent and orientation of some of the genes and open reading frames indicated by the arrows below. Antibiotic resistance genes are shown in color. Insertion sequences are shown as boxes, with arrows above indicating the orientation of the <italic toggle="yes">tnp</italic> transposase gene and numbers inside indicating the identity of the IS. Inverted repeats are shown as vertical lines. The <italic toggle="yes">attI1</italic> site of the class 1 integron is shown as a tall open box, and each narrow box represents a cassette, with a vertical bar indicating the <italic toggle="yes">attC</italic> site. Gray blocks between lines indicate regions of identical sequence, and black triangles indicate the location of deletions, along with their size.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sph0031621020005.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="h2"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The complexity of the organization of the resistance region of R1215 reflects a complex evolutionary history. The first step is likely to have been the insertion of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic> into the <italic toggle="yes">mucB</italic> gene. Then, a series of transposition and deletion events occurred within the boundaries of the Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic>, resulting in the loss of the central part of this transposon. In this process, a series of unique boundaries were generated, and these serve to unambiguously link this resistance region to those of the AbaR and AbGRI2 islands in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. In both cases, an IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> formed a TU via an adjacent deletion event (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). This TU was then incorporated into the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> chromosome. The presence of the region found in the AbaR0 MARR that is not in AbGRI2-0*, and vice versa, indicates that both regions were acquired directly from R1215 or a variant of it, rather than one from the other. However, while we obtained evidence that R1215 could transfer into an <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolate, it does not appear to be stably maintained. Nonetheless, entry would bring the resistance region into the cell and enable the TU formation and transposition or homologous recombination reactions to take place; this occurred in the case of Tn<italic toggle="yes">6020</italic> in the experiments reported here.</p><p>Neither the AbaR0 form of the MARR nor the AbGRI2-0* configuration of AbGRI2 has survived unaltered in all members of the GC1 and GC2 complexes, respectively. It is now well established that variant forms are numerous and their formation tends to involve IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-mediated events, particularly deletions occurring adjacent to one end of the IS (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, to date, a remnant of the relevant region is present in all reported genomes, indicating that the modern day multiply, extensively, and pan-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates from GC1 and GC2 are all the progeny of a single progenitor for each clone.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="h3"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s3.1"><title>Bacterial strains and plasmids.</title><p>Plasmid R1215 was obtained from the United Kingdom National Collection of Type Cultures (NCTC 50331), in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 strain J53-2 as part of a group of 16 strains containing plasmids of known incompatibility groups for use as controls for PCR-based replicon typing. These strains were screened for resistance to common antibiotics and for the presence of antibiotic resistance genes, mercuric ion resistance genes, class 1 and class 2 integrons, and gene cassettes in class 1 and class 2 integrons, as described elsewhere (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Strains containing R1215 were maintained under selection with 100 µg/ml ampicillin and 25 µg/ml kanamycin. R1215 was transferred into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> E294rif<sup>r</sup> as described previously (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), and transconjugants were recovered on plates containing rifampin (100 µg/ml) to select against the donor and for the recipient and kanamycin to select for R1215. Transconjugant colonies were screened for resistance to antibiotics that the donor strain was resistant to, using L-agar containing the following antibiotics and corresponding concentrations: ampicillin at 100 µg/ml, kanamycin at 20 µg/ml, streptomycin at 25 µg/ml, gentamicin at 8 µg/ml, neomycin at 50 µg/ml, chloramphenicol at 25 µg/ml, tetracycline at 10 µg/ml, and Mueller-Hinton agar containing sulfamethoxazole at 100 µg/ml. Transconjugants were purified and stored at −80°C.</p></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title>Plasmid DNA extraction and sequencing.</title><p>R1215 plasmid DNA was isolated from a pure transconjugant culture grown overnight at 37°C by using an alkaline lysis miniprep method optimized for the extraction of large plasmids, as previously described (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The DNA was sequenced at the Australian Genome Research Facility by using a 314 chip on the Ion Torrent PGM platform (Life Technologies). The sequencing reads (191-fold coverage) were assembled <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> into contigs by using Geneious version 6.1.6 (Biomatters).</p></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title>Plasmid assembly.</title><p>The contigs containing backbone sequence overlapped and were assembled with Sequencher 5.1 (Gene Codes). PCR using published primer pairs (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) and RH1581 (5′-GCGGCATATCTGGGTGCTT-3′) in orfI, followed by sequencing of the amplicons, was used to assemble the resistance island. PCR conditions used to detect short amplicons were described previously (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). PCR amplicons were resolved by electrophoresis on 1% (wt/vol) agarose gels with molecular weight standards, stained with ethidium bromide, and visualized using a GelDoc1000 image analysis station (Bio-Rad). Separated PCR products were purified for sequencing by using the QIAquick gel extraction kit (Qiagen Inc., Valencia, CA, USA), following the manufacturer’s protocols. Sequences were assembled using Sequencher, and the Textco (West Lebanon, NH, USA) gene construction kit (version 4.0) was used to draw figures to scale. To confirm the assembly, R1215 plasmid DNA was digested with BsiW1 or BamHI-HF as per the manufacturer’s instructions, and fragments were resolved by electrophoresis on a 0.7% (wt/vol) agarose gel with molecular weight standards, poststained with ethidium bromide, and visualized using a GelDoc100 image analysis station. The observed fragment pattern was compared to digestion patterns predicted from the assembled sequence of R1215 by using the Textco gene construction kit, version 4.0.</p></sec><sec id="s3.4"><title>Nucleotide sequence accession number.</title><p>The sequence of R1215 has been deposited with GenBank under the accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KU315015">KU315015</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We thank Sheree Yau for initial characterization of the R1215 phenotype and genes present.</p><p>The efforts of Grace A. Blackwell and Mohammad Hamidian were supported by Australian Postgraduate Awards. This study was funded by the School of Molecular Bioscience, The University of Sydney.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liebert</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Transposon Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic>, flagship of the floating genome</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>
<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10477306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mmbr.63.3.507-522.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC103744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopecko</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brevet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Involvement of multiple translocating DNA segments and recombinational hotspots in the structural evolution of bacterial plasmids</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(76)80124-6</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">796463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubens</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>WE</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<article-title>Transposable plasmid deoxyribonucleic acid sequence in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> which mediates resistance to gentamicin and four other antimicrobial agents</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">113388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jb.139.3.877-882.1979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC218034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Transposons Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic> and Tn<italic toggle="yes">21</italic> and their integrons In4 and In2 have independent origins</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1263</fpage>–<lpage>1270</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.45.4.1263-1270.2001</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11257044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC90453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<article-title>Characterisation of Tn<italic toggle="yes">1721</italic>, a new transposon containing tetracycline resistance genes capable of amplification</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source>
<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00276215</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">377024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>SGI-type genomic islands and antibiotic resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic></article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1525</fpage>–<lpage>1538</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.10.122</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21073312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>pRMH760, a precursor of A/C plasmids carrying <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>CMY and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>NDM genes</article-title>. <source>Microb Drug Resist</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2014.0012</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24841670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The A to Z of A/C plasmids</article-title>. <source>Plasmid</source>
<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plasmid.2015.04.003</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25910948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Evolution of a multiple antibiotic resistance region in IncHI1 plasmids: reshaping resistance regions in situ</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>2848</fpage>–<lpage>2853</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dks317</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22888274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ginn</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iredell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>pEl1573 carrying <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>IMP-4, from Sydney, Australia, is closely related to other IncL/M plasmids</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>6029</fpage>–<lpage>6032</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01189-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22926566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3486572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goglin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molyneaux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hujer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavender</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campagnari</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hujer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Comparative genome sequence analysis of multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>8053</fpage>–<lpage>8064</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00834-08</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18931120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2593238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>P-E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vallenet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Audic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poirel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mangenot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abergel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nordmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissenbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Comparative genomics of multidrug resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e7</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0020007</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16415984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1326220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>AbaR5, a large multiple antibiotic resistance region found in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>2667</fpage>–<lpage>2671</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01407-08</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19364869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2687260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Evolution of AbaR-type genomic resistance islands in multiply antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1162</fpage>–<lpage>1170</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkq095</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20375036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krizova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkshoorn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nemec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Diversity and evolution of AbaR genomic resistance islands in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains of European clone I</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>3201</fpage>–<lpage>3206</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00221-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21537009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3122396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidian</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dougan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<day>2</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Five decades of genome evolution in the globally distributed, extensively antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> global clone 1</article-title>. <source>Microb Genom</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000052</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5320584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28348844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrugia</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>A novel family of genomic resistance islands, AbGRI2, contributing to aminoglycoside resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates belonging to global clone 2</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dks459</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23169892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seputiene</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Povilonis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suziedeliene</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Novel variants of AbaR resistance islands with a common backbone in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates of European clone II</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1969</fpage>–<lpage>1973</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.05678-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22290980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3318354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Loss and gain of aminoglycoside resistance in GC2 <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in Australia via modification of genomic resistance islands and acquisition of plasmids</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1135</fpage>–<lpage>1147</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkw1176</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27246238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Evolution of AbGRI2-0, the progenitor of the AbGRI2 resistance island in global clone 2 of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1429</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02662-15</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26666934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4775934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wynn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dougan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Identification of a marker for two lineages within the GC1 clone of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkt379</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24080502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3886933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinyon</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anantham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Commensal <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> of healthy humans: a reservoir for antibiotic-resistance determinants</article-title>. <source>J Med Microbiol</source>
<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1331</fpage>–<lpage>1339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.022475-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20671087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carattoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seiffert</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwendener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perreten</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endimiani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Differentiation of IncL and IncM plasmids associated with the spread of clinically relevant antimicrobial resistance</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>e00117-16</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123063</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4416936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25933288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Recchia</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Family of class 1 integrons related to In4 from Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>3014</fpage>–<lpage>3020</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.45.11.3014-3020.2001</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11600350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC90776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Djordjevic</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Transposons related to Tn<italic toggle="yes">1696</italic> in IncHI2 plasmids in multiply antibiotic resistant <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium from Australian animals</article-title>. <source>Microb Drug Resist</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2010.0042</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20701539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-mediated formation of transposons carrying antibiotic resistance genes</article-title>. <source>mSphere</source>
<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e00038-16</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00038-16</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4894685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27303727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Movement of IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic>-associated antibiotic resistance genes occurs via a translocatable unit that includes a single IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> and preferentially inserts adjacent to another IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic></article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>5</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<elocation-id>e00117-16</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01801-14</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4196232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25293759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hitchcock</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tine</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The complete nucleotide sequence of the multi-drug resistance-encoding IncL/M plasmid pACM1</article-title>. <source>Plasmid</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plasmid.2014.08.005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25291385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haft</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harkins</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hujer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bajaksouzian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benard</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>New insights into dissemination and variation of the health care-associated pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> from genomic analysis</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e00117-16</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00963-13</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3903280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>AbaR4 replaces AbaR3 in a carbapenem resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolate belonging to global clone 1 from an Australian hospital</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>2484</fpage>–<lpage>2491</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkr356</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21873287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adamczuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaleski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dziewit</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolinowska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieckarz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wawrzyniak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kieryl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plucienniczak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartosik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Diversity and global distribution of IncL/M plasmids enabling horizontal dissemination of β-lactam resistance genes among the <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic></article-title>. <source>Biomed Res Int</source>
<volume>2015</volume>:<elocation-id>e00117-16</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/414681</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4510254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26236726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>