<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6531439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6531439.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6531439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6531439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31118466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-44242-y</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">44242</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>American Civil War plant medicines inhibit growth, biofilm formation, and quorum sensing by multidrug-resistant bacteria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8078-9408</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Dettweiler</surname><given-names initials="M">Micah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyles</surname><given-names initials="JT">James T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names initials="K">Kate</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname><given-names initials="B">Brandon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddinger</surname><given-names initials="RM">Ryan M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7920-5601</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zurawski</surname><given-names initials="DV">Daniel V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9615-7886</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Quave</surname><given-names initials="CL">Cassandra L.</given-names></name><address><email>cquave@emory.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0941 6502</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.189967.8</institution-id><institution>Center for the Study of Human Health, </institution><institution>Emory University, </institution></institution-wrap>Atlanta, Georgia USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0941 6502</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.189967.8</institution-id><institution>Department of Dermatology, </institution><institution>Emory University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Atlanta, Georgia USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0036 4726</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.420210.5</institution-id><institution>Wound Infections Department, Bacterial Diseases Branch, </institution><institution>Walter Reed Army Institute of Research (WRAIR), </institution></institution-wrap>Silver Spring, Maryland USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0941 6502</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.189967.8</institution-id><institution>Emory Antibiotic Resistance Center, </institution><institution>Emory University, </institution></institution-wrap>Atlanta, Georgia USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0941 6502</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.189967.8</institution-id><institution>Emory University Herbarium, Emory University, </institution></institution-wrap>Atlanta, Georgia USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">327256</issue-id><elocation-id>7692</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>05</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>05</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-03-06 15:25:12.587"><day>06</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2019_Article_44242.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">A shortage of conventional medicine during the American Civil War (1861–1865) spurred Confederate physicians to use preparations of native plants as medicines. In 1863, botanist Francis Porcher compiled a book of medicinal plants native to the southern United States, including plants used in Native American traditional medicine. In this study, we consulted Porcher’s book and collected samples from three species that were indicated for the formulation of antiseptics: <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Aralia spinosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Quercus alba</italic>. Extracts of these species were tested for the ability to inhibit growth in three species of multidrug-resistant pathogenic bacteria associated with wound infections: <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Extracts were also tested for biofilm and quorum sensing inhibition against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus. Q. alba</italic> extracts inhibited growth in all three species of bacteria (IC<sub>50</sub> 64, 32, and 32 µg/mL, respectively), and inhibited biofilm formation (IC<sub>50</sub> 1 µg/mL) in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> extracts inhibited biofilm formation (IC<sub>50</sub> 32 µg/mL) in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> extracts inhibited biofilm formation (IC<sub>50</sub> 2 µg/mL) and quorum sensing (IC<sub>50</sub> 8 µg/mL) in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. These results support that this selection of plants exhibited some antiseptic properties in the prevention and management of wound infections during the conflict.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Antibiotics</kwd><kwd>Secondary metabolism</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100000011</institution-id><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute (HHMI)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>52006923</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Dettweiler</surname><given-names>Micah</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100006955</institution-id><institution>U.S. Department of Health &amp;amp; Human Services | NIH | Office of Extramural Research, National Institutes of Health (OER)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R21 AI136563</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Quave</surname><given-names>Cassandra L.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Antibiotic resistance in pathogenic microbes poses a significant threat to human health<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>; antibiotics are critical not only in treating bacterial diseases but also in enabling surgery and other procedures with high risks of infection. Given the great genetic diversity and capacity for evolution present in bacteria, a rise in antibiotic resistance is an inevitable response to antibiotic use. For example, in 1940, even before penicillin was widely used, penicillin resistance was observed. Any single antibiotic, then, is not a permanent solution but another step in the struggle against infection.</p><p id="Par3">Several factors complicate the relationship between antibiotics and bacteria. For example, the innate immune system plays a role in fighting infections with or without the use of antibiotics. Further, commensal members of the microbiome may compete with pathogenic bacteria or may themselves become pathogenic under certain circumstances. Relevant to this study, bacterial community effects such as biofilms and quorum sensing produce resistance and virulence phenotypes not necessarily observed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Biofilms are extracellular mixtures of polysaccharides and proteins that can physically protect bacterial populations from antibiotics and immune responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Consequently, biofilms are associated with chronic infections, especially in the cases of indwelling medical devices and implants, and there is currently a lack of effective treatments for these conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Quorum sensing is a system by which toxin production or other pathogenic activity is initiated when extracellular communication indicates achievement of a threshold population of bacteria. Inhibition of quorum sensing and biofilm formation, then, can be therapeutic but not bactericidal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. In the absence of new antibiotics, multidrug-resistant infections may be treatable by administering biofilm inhibitors or quorum quenchers to increase the vulnerability of bacteria to the immune system or conventional antibiotics.</p><p id="Par4">The natural product compositions investigated in this study are plant extracts used during the American Civil War (1861–1865), a period of history in which infections were treated without the use of modern antibiotics and before the emergence of germ theory. The accepted definition of antiseptic was “tonic useful to prevent external or internal mortification”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Union General Ulysses S. Grant once famously demanded that onions be sent to him before he would move his army. While soldiers certainly used onions in their cooking, we know now that antimicrobial agents such as ajoene and allicin found in garlic and onions have an impact on quorum sensing and biofilm to disrupt infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. At the time, they were used to treat powder burns.</p><p id="Par5">During the latter half of the war, a Union blockade<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> prevented the Confederacy from importing sufficient amounts of conventional medicines such as quinine, morphine, and chloroform (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Francis Porcher, a botanist, was commissioned to find and catalogue plants native to the southeastern US that could be used as medicines in their place<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Porcher compiled a book of his findings, including 37 plant species to be used as antiseptics, treating gangrene and other infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. From this research, Samuel Moore, the Confederate Surgeon General, published a field guide of native plant medicines to be used by battlefield physicians, including methods of collection, preparation, and administration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Infection was a leading cause of death for soldiers in the Civil War and was often treated with amputation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. It may be hoped that Porcher’s work with medicinal plants saved many lives and limbs.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Cartoon map of the Union blockade proposed by General Winfield Scott during the American Civil War. Created in 1861 by J.B. Elliott and entered in Library of Congress, Geography and Map Division.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e431" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2019_44242_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">Natural products—compounds produced by living organisms—are used directly as medicine by an estimated 4 billion people for whom traditional medicine is a primary healthcare source<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Approximately 25% of modern drugs are derived from natural products used in traditional medicine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Plants in particular produce a large variety of secondary metabolites to interact with their environments, and some of these serve to control local microbes by encouraging or inhibiting bacterial growth and/or function.</p><p id="Par7">Many of the plant species Porcher described as antiseptic have not been tested for antibiotic activity, particularly for adjuvant activity (biofilm and/or anti-virulence properties) or activity against multidrug-resistant bacteria. The aim of this study was to examine the potential efficacy of the plants used to stave off infection during the Civil War. While the majority of drugs on the market today are synthetic, many are still derived from natural products; a review of new drugs from 1981–2014 found that only two new approved novel chemical entities (NCEs), sorafenib and ataluren, were created through <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> combinatorial chemistry<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Searching natural products for NCEs may be a more effective tactic, especially when systems of traditional medicine and historical pharmacopoeias are available to use as heuristics.</p><p id="Par8">One benefit of natural product extracts as antibiotic agents over single-compound drugs is that due to the presence of dozens to thousands of compounds, they can exhibit multiple mechanisms of activity, potentially making it more difficult for resistance to develop. For example, English oak (<italic toggle="yes">Quercus robur</italic> L., Fagaceae) bark was found to exert its quorum quenching activity via two distinct mechanisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">In this study, samples of three species from Porcher’s book were selected for investigation: white oak (<italic toggle="yes">Quercus alba</italic> L., Fagaceae), devil’s walking stick (<italic toggle="yes">Aralia spinosa</italic> L., Araliaceae), and tulip tree (<italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic> L., Magnoliaceae). We hypothesized that, given the historic use of these plants as antiseptics, their extracts may inhibit growth, biofilm production, and/or quorum sensing in pathogenic bacteria that affect the skin and soft tissue structures. Multidrug-resistant bacteria were used in all experiments to examine the potential use of these plant compounds to combat emerging resistance in species commonly found in wound infections today.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Extract yield</title><p id="Par10">Extraction in MeOH yielded six crude extracts, representing <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> bark and galls, <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> leaves, and <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> leaves, root inner bark, and branch bark (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Extract yield was highest (27.1% of dry mass) in extract 620 (<italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> galls). Other crude extracts had yields ranging from 8–11%. Masses of partitions and fractions of crude extracts varied from &lt;0.1% to 4% relative to dry plant matter (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Partitions were labelled B, C, D, and E for solvents hexane, ethyl acetate, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>-butanol, and water, respectively; non-tannin fractions were labelled F1 and tannin fractions were labelled F2. The non-tannin fraction of <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> leaves (616-F1) was more than 10 times as massive as the tannin fraction, suggesting that tannin content is not high in <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> leaves. The tannin and non-tannin fractions of <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> bark were similar in mass.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Preparation of plant materials.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Botanical Name (Voucher #)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plant Part</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drying Procedure</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Grinding Procedure</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extract Number</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Percent Yield</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Aralia spinosa</italic> L. (MD-023)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">leaves</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">drying cabinet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wiley Mill with 2 mm mesh</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">618</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.92</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic> L. (MD-027)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">leaves</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">drying cabinet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wiley Mill with 2 mm mesh</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">616</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.71</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">root inner bark</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cut into 3 × 3 cm pieces, drying cabinet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wiley Mill with 2 mm mesh</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">617</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.39</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">branch inner bark</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cut into 1 × 3 cm pieces, drying cabinet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">coffee grinder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">621</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.65</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Quercus alba</italic> L. (MD-022)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">bark</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cut into 3 × 3 cm pieces, drying cabinet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wiley Mill with 2 mm mesh</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">619</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.78</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">branch galls</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">drying cabinet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">coffee grinder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">620</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.10</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Growth inhibition</title><p id="Par11">All 19 crude extracts, partitions, and fractions were tested for growth inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Reported here are minimum concentrations of extract that achieved 50% inhibition (IC<sub>50</sub>) and 90% inhibition (MIC or IC<sub>90</sub>). Extracts from <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> were shown to be most active in inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> growth (IC<sub>50</sub> 64 μg/mL in each case). <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extracts 619, 619-F2, and 620 displayed inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub> 64, 32, and 32 μg/mL, respectively) and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub> 128, 64, and 32 μg/mL).<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Growth inhibition of multidrug-resistant bacteria by Civil War samples.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sample</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Species</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Strain</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">UAMS1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">NRS385</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">EU27</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">EU32</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AH71</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">616</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">616-F1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">616-F2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">617</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">617B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">617 C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">617D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">617E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">618</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">618B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">618 C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">618D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">618E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">619</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">619-F1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">619-F2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">619 W</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">620</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">620 W</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">621</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Amp</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Van</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gent</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IC<sub>50</sub> and MIC (IC<sub>90</sub>) values are expressed as concentration (μg/mL), with a maximum concentration tested of 256 μg/mL. Dashes indicate that a sample was not tested.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par12">Extracts which displayed strong activity against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (619, 619-F2, and 620) were tested for growth inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic> and additional strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>. All three of these <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extracts inhibited growth in the strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub> 32–256 μg/mL), but not in the additional <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> strains tested (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extracts 619 and 619-F2 were found to inhibit growth of <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub> 256 and 64 μg/mL, respectively).<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Growth inhibition of additional strains by <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> samples 619, 619-F2, and 620.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sample</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>
</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">EU24</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AB5075</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDC0035</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDC0037</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDC0045</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDC0300</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">EU33</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">EU34</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">EU36</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">NRS101</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">619</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">619-F2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">620</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Amp</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Van</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gent</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mem</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IC<sub>50</sub> and MIC values are expressed as concentration (μg/mL), with a maximum concentration tested of 256 μg/mL. Dashes indicated that a sample was not tested.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Biofilm inhibition</title><p id="Par13">Extracts from all species inhibited <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> biofilm formation (IC<sub>50</sub> 1–256 µg/mL). Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows biofilm inhibition across serial dilutions of the most active extracts. <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extract 619-F2 displayed the greatest biofilm inhibition (IC<sub>50</sub> 1 µg/mL). Some extracts, such as <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> extract 616-F1 and <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> extract 618B, displayed little growth inhibition activity against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> but strongly inhibited biofilm formation (IC<sub>50</sub> 32 and 2 µg/mL, respectively). Full biofilm inhibition data is reported in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Biofilm inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> by Civil War samples. Extracts tested at sub-IC<sub>50</sub> concentration. Percent biofilm inhibition calculated as inhibition compared to vehicle control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2721" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2019_44242_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Quorum sensing inhibition</title><p id="Par14">Transcription of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus agr</italic> types I, II, and III was inhibited by several Civil War extracts (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> extract 617 C, <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> extract 618 C, and <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extract 619-F1 exhibited the most activity in these assays, primarily against <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic> III (IC<sub>50</sub> 16, 32, and 16 μg/mL, respectively). No extracts demonstrated inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic> IV transcription. Full quorum sensing inhibition data is reported in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Quorum sensing inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> by Civil War samples. (<bold>A</bold>) Screen of all samples at 64 µg/mL. OD represents <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> growth and FLD represents expression of the <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic> gene. (<bold>B</bold>) Serial dilution of active samples from 0.5 to 64 µg/mL. Only 224C-F2, the control, showed activity against <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic> IV at sub-inhibitory concentrations for growth.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2782" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2019_44242_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cytotoxicity</title><p id="Par15">Of the 19 extracts studied, 13 were recognized to have potential antibiotic activity and were tested with human keratinocytes (HaCaT) to counter test for cytotoxicity. <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> root bark extracts 617 and 617 C displayed high levels of cytotoxicity (IC<sub>50</sub> 16 μg/mL in each case). <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extracts displayed no significant cytotoxicity at test concentrations (2–256 μg/mL). Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> displays cytotoxicity across serial dilutions of samples tested; IC<sub>50</sub> and IC<sub>90</sub> values are reported in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>.<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Cytotoxicity of Civil War samples exhibiting bioactivity in antibacterial models of growth, biofilm inhibition or quorum quenching. Percent keratinocyte survival is relative to vehicle control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2818" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2019_44242_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Chemical analysis</title><p id="Par16"><italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extracts 619-F2 and 620 were selected for chemical analysis because of their strong antibacterial activity both in growth inhibition and in adjuvant assays and because of their lack of toxicity towards human cells. Initial HPLC indicated a wealth of early eluting compounds, so the chromatographic conditions were adjusted for LC-FTMS to achieve greater separation in that region. LC-FTMS revealed that 619-F2 and 620 have few compounds in common (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Negative ESI mass spectrum base peak chromatograms of (<bold>A</bold>) 619-F2 and (<bold>B</bold>) 620. Peaks in common are 6, 41, and 42.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2843" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2019_44242_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">Analysis of LC-FTMS revealed 22 peaks in 619-F2 and 24 peaks in 620 with ≥1% peak area. Of these peaks, 16 and 10 respectively were putatively matched with known <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic> spp. Compounds (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Only three compounds were found in both 619-F2 and 620, 6, 41, and 42 with <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> of 466.0306, 367.2866, and 367.2866 respectively.<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Putative compounds from fraction 619-F2 and extract 620 identified from database searches (7) isomers of procyanidin: procyanidin C<sub>1</sub>, procyanidin C<sub>2</sub>, procyanidin T<sub>2</sub>, procyanidin T<sub>3,</sub> (<bold>8a</bold>) catechin-gallocatechin-4,8-dimer, (<bold>8b</bold>) catechin-gallocatechin-6′,8-dimer, (<bold>8c</bold>) gallocatechin-catechin-6′,8-dimer, (<bold>8d</bold>) potengriffioside A and tiliroside, (<bold>8e</bold>) prodelphinidin C, (<bold>8f</bold>) (2 R,2′R,3 S,3′S,4 R)-[2′-(3,4-dihydroxyphenyl)-3,3′,4,4′-tetrahydro-2-(3,4,5 trihydroxyphenyl)-4,6′-Bi-2H-1-benzopyran]-3,3′,5,5′,7,7′-hexol, (<bold>15a</bold>) isomers of procyanidin B: procyanidin B<sub>1</sub>, procyanidin B<sub>2</sub>, procyanidin B<sub>3</sub>, procyanidin B<sub>4</sub>, procyanidin B<sub>5</sub>, procyanidin B<sub>6</sub>, procyanidin B<sub>7</sub>, procyanidin B<sub>8</sub>, (<bold>15b</bold>) catechol-catechol-6′,8-dimer, (<bold>15c</bold>) echinacin, (<bold>24a</bold>) isomers of procyanidin B 3-O-gallate: procyanidin B<sub>1</sub> 3-O-gallate, procyanidin B<sub>2</sub> 3-O-gallate, procyanidin B<sub>3</sub> 3-O-gallate, (<bold>24b</bold>) procyanidin B<sub>2</sub> 3′-O-gallate, (<bold>28</bold>) epicatechin gallate, (<bold>30</bold>) isocryptomerin (<bold>2</bold>) castalin and vescalin, (<bold>12a</bold>) casuariin, (<bold>12b</bold>) pedunculagin, (<bold>14a</bold>) castacrenin A, (<bold>14b</bold>) castacrenin B, (<bold>14c</bold>) castacrenin C, (<bold>14d</bold>) leiocarposide, (<bold>29</bold>) ellagic acid, (<bold>32a</bold>) 2, 19, 23-trihydroxy-3-[(3, 4, 5-trihydroxybenzoyl) oxy]-β-D-glucopyranosyl ester (2α, 3β, 4α)-urs-12-en-28-oic acid and 2, 19, 23-trihydroxy-3-[(3, 4, 5-trihydroxybenzoyl) oxy]-α-D-glucopyranosyl ester (2α, 3β, 4α)-urs-12-en-28-oic acid, (<bold>32b</bold>) quercotriterpenoside I, (<bold>32c</bold>) quercotriterpenoside II, (<bold>32d</bold>) quercotriterpenoside III, (<bold>32e</bold>) quercotriterpenoside VI, (<bold>40a</bold>) arjugenin, (<bold>40b</bold>) belleric acid, (<bold>40c</bold>) sericic acid, (<bold>40d</bold>) 2α,19,23-trihydroxyursolic acid, (<bold>40e</bold>) 2,3,23,24-tetrahydroxy-(2α,3β)-urs-12-en-28-oic acid.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e3011" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2019_44242_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par18">Extracts of <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> displayed inhibitory activity against bacteria that cause skin and soft tissue infections, substantiating their use as antiseptics during the American Civil War. These medicinal plants may be useful in modern medicine as treatments for antibiotic-resistant bacteria. Of particular interest are 618B and 620 as <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> biofilm inhibitors and 619, 619-F2, and 620 as growth inhibitors of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>.</p><p id="Par19">While a 1947 survey of antibacterial properties of plants found no activity in <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, the positive results in this experiment may be explained by differences in a number of factors. The previous study used H<sub>2</sub>O extracts whereas this experiment used MeOH extracts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>; <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> bark was historically prepared for treatment by dissolving in EtOH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, which produces an extraction profile similar to MeOH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Additionally, given the role of endophytic microorganisms in the synthesis of secondary metabolites, the chemical composition of plant extracts can vary based on differences in the plant microbiome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Other possible sources of variation include collection date and location, assay method, and extract concentration tested. Finally, given the variability in how different laboratories may perform one type of extraction, results can vary between related studies. For example, of two studies that evaluated <italic toggle="yes">Aralia nudicaulis</italic> root (a traditional Native American remedy ingredient) for growth inhibition of mycobacteria, only one reported moderate antibacterial effects while the other reported little activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par20">In his report, Porcher recommended the entire genus <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic> as a source of antiseptics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. This activity is confirmed not only by the results of the experiments reported herein, but also by multiple other studies showing antibiotic effects by <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic> spp. extracts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. A European herbal remedy referred to as <italic toggle="yes">Quercus cortex</italic> (originating from <italic toggle="yes">Q. robur</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Q. petrea</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Q. pubescens</italic> bark) has shown weak antibacterial and quorum sensing inhibition effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Acorn extract from a variety of oaks has shown inhibition of both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par21">However, the activity of various <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic> spp. extracts is far from uniform. For example, the <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> gall extract (620) in this study inhibited growth of drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> whereas a study of <italic toggle="yes">Q. infectoria</italic> galls found no significant inhibition of drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">Antibacterial activity in oak extracts is frequently attributed to tannins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, compounds that typically interfere with biological processes by binding to proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. In <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic>, tannin content is typically highest in galls, with a reported 70% tannin content in <italic toggle="yes">Q. infectoria</italic> galls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. In this experiment, higher activity in 620 (gall crude extract) over 619 (bark crude extract) and 619-F2 (bark tannin fraction) over 619-F1 (bark non-tannin fraction) suggests that <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic>’s growth inhibitory activity is due to tannins. However, quorum sensing inhibition by 619-F1 suggests that additional compounds could contribute to the antibacterial activity of crude oak extract, the medicine used during the Civil War.</p><p id="Par23">LC-FTMS analysis of 619-F2 and 620 confirmed the existence of a variety of tannins in both extracts (Supplementary Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). Of particular interest are ellagitannin isomers, 2, found in 620; as well as related ellagitannins 12a and 12b. Ellagitannins have been reported to have antibiotic activity against antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. While only three MS peaks were found in common between 619-F2 and 620, both extracts are rich in tannins. 619-F2 is enriched in procyanidin condensed tannins and 620 contains many ellagitannins and triterpenes.</p><p id="Par24">Tannins have been shown to inhibit growth in a wide range of bacteria, fungi, and viruses. Suggested mechanisms of action include inactivation of microbial enzymes, inhibition of membrane transport, and sequestering essential metal ions in complexes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Tannins may also act as biofilm inhibitors by binding to matrix proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. However, tannins have also been found to bind with digestive enzymes and nutrients such as proteins and starches, and as such are generally considered as anti-nutritive; a variety of animals have shown gastrointestinal distress and decreased growth when fed on high-tannin diets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Because of this nondiscriminatory binding, external applications of <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> extracts would be preferable to internal or systemic applications; Porcher recommended that powdered oak bark be applied in a wash for gangrene and a poultice for wounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">Leaves of several <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic> species (<italic toggle="yes">Q. cerris</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Q. ilex</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Q. virginiana</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Q. incana</italic>) have also shown antibacterial properties, including biofilm and quorum sensing inhibition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. One future research direction could be to compare the antibacterial properties of <italic toggle="yes">Q. alba</italic> leaves with the activity identified in bark and gall extracts.</p><p id="Par26">While <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> has several reported uses in traditional medicine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, it has not frequently been studied for medicinal properties. The most notable results of this experiment for <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> are significant biofilm inhibition by 618B (leaf hexane partition) and quorum sensing inhibition by 618 C (leaf ethyl acetate partition). The presence of these adjuvant properties rather than simple growth inhibitory activity in <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> leaves may explain the 1947 report of no significant antibiotic activity in <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par27">Other <italic toggle="yes">Aralia</italic> species have exhibited antibacterial activity in roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> and aerial parts (flowers, leaves, and stems)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, including biofilm inhibition by <italic toggle="yes">A. cachemirica</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In his list, Porcher also ascribed antiseptic activity to <italic toggle="yes">A. racemosa</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par28"><italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> has been widely studied and its various parts have exhibited a variety of medicinal effects including antibacterial<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, anti-malarial<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, and anti-cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> activity. The other species of <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">L. chinense</italic>, is used in Chinese traditional medicine and has been shown to have antibacterial effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Additionally, an extract from a hybrid of <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. chinense</italic> has been shown to exhibit inhibition of biofilm production and quorum sensing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> extracts demonstrated activity in the inhibition of growth, biofilm production, and quorum sensing. However, the root bark extract (617), which is generally more bioactive than the leaf extract (616) and branch bark extract (621) in our models, displayed significant mammalian cytotoxicity (IC<sub>50</sub>: 16 µg/mL). It may therefore be ill-suited for medicinal use, or at least dose-limited. A study of <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> for antiplasmodial activity also found high cytotoxicity in active fractions but it has been suggested that, given the use of <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> in traditional medicine, toxicity may not be problematic <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> at therapeutic doses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Porcher recommended root bark as the medicinal part of <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> to be harvested<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>; perhaps preparation techniques or dosage made the potency/toxicity trade-off worthwhile in a wartime context. Interestingly, Porcher also suggested <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> bark as a substitute for <italic toggle="yes">Cinchona</italic> bark in malaria treatment, an application supported by recent research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par30">Perhaps the most notable <italic toggle="yes">L. tulipifera</italic> extract with low toxicity is 616-F1 (leaf non-tannin fraction), which displayed little growth inhibition but significant biofilm and quorum sensing inhibition—an adjuvant effect similar to the <italic toggle="yes">A. spinosa</italic> extracts tested.</p><p id="Par31">Further study should focus on bioassay-guided fractionation, a recursive process of fractionation and bioassay to identify individual active compounds and synergistic relationships. Of the extracts tested, 616-F1, 618B, 618 C, 619-F2, and 620 exhibit the most promise for antibiotic NCEs and are good candidates for this process. Specifically, the HPLC methods developed for 619-F2 and 620 could be used to produce further fractions with adaptation to preparative liquid chromatography.</p><p id="Par32"><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> testing of the antibacterial properties of extracts active <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> is also a logical next step in this research. Given the potential of some of these extracts as adjuvants rather than direct antibiotics, they may be tested as adjuvants with existing, FDA-approved antibiotics for the potentiation of antibacterial activity in wound infections.</p><p id="Par33">Finally, given the activity seen in the extracts tested in this study, it may be worthwhile to investigate the antibacterial properties of other plants recorded as antiseptics in Porcher’s book. In total, 37 plant species were described as having antiseptic applications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. As the global spread of antibiotic-resistant strains of bacteria continues, it is increasingly important to consider all possible sources of new, and perhaps old, treatments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par34">Samples of <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Aralia spinosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Quercus alba</italic> were identified and collected in May 2015 from Lullwater Preserve on the Emory University campus in Atlanta, Georgia. Leaves were gathered manually and a handsaw was used to cut segments of roots and branches for bark collection. Vouchers (Accession numbers 20338-20341) were deposited in the Emory University Herbarium (GEO) in Atlanta and digital copies of the specimens are accessible for viewing online via the SERNEC web portal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Samples were dried and ground into powder by either a Wiley mill equipped with a 2 mm mesh or coffee grinder (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Extraction, partitioning, and fractionation</title><p id="Par35">All ground material (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) was sonicated in MeOH (1 g/10 mL). After 20 minutes the sample was filtered sequentially with Whatman filter paper 8 and 2, and then fresh MeOH was added to the plant material for a second round of sonication. The two filtrates were combined and dried <italic toggle="yes">in vacuo</italic> at ≤40 °C. The resulting residue was suspended in H<sub>2</sub>O, frozen, and lyophilized. The dried extract was collected and 20 mg of each extract was dissolved in DMSO (10 mg/mL) for biological testing.</p><p id="Par36">Extracts 617 and 618 were suspended in H<sub>2</sub>O (1 g/10 mL) and were sequentially partitioned in hexane, ethyl acetate, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>-butanol, yielding 4 partitions. Extracts 616 and 619 were dissolved in 95% ethanol (1 g/2 mL and 1 g/3 mL, respectively), loaded on a Sephadex LH-20 column (25 g, 32 × 2.5 cm), and sequentially eluted with 95% ethanol (300 mL), 70% acetone (300 mL), and 100% acetone (150 mL) to yield three fractions. All partitions and fractions were dried <italic toggle="yes">in vacuo</italic>, resuspended in H<sub>2</sub>O, frozen and lyophilized before being dissolved in DMSO (10 mg/mL) for biological testing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p id="Par37">In this study, six strains of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (UAMS1, UAMS929, NRS385, AH1747, AH1677, AH430, AH1872), one strain of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> (NRS101), three strains of <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (NR-15410, NR-15411, NR-15412), eight strains of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (AB5075, NR-17786, AR-BANK#0035, AR-BANK#0037, AR-BANK#0045, AR-BANK#0300, OIFC143, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="H72721">H72721</ext-link>), and one strain of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (AH071) were used (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). To create liquid cultures for all assays, strains were grown overnight in tryptic soy broth (TSB) with constant shaking (230 rpm). All strains were maintained on Tryptic Soy Agar (TSA) and tested in Cation-Adjusted Mueller-Hinton Broth (CAMHB).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Growth inhibition assays</title><p id="Par38">Assays were carried out under CLSI M100-S23 guidelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. A working culture was created by standardizing liquid culture using a BioTek Cytation3 and inoculating into CAMHB to a concentration of 5.0 × 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/mL. Working culture was added to extracts and controls in 96-well microtiter plates (Grenier-Bio 655-185) such that each well contained a total volume of 0.2 mL. Vehicle controls and antibiotic controls (ampicillin, kanamycin, and vancomycin for <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> spp. assays, gentamicin, tetracycline, and meropenem for other species, 0.5 to 64 µg/mL) were included for each strain. Extracts and vehicle were tested at a concentration range of 2.0 to 256 µg/mL, using 2-fold serial dilution. Plates were incubated at 37 °C, with <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus, S. epidermidis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> for 18 hours and <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> for 22 hours. Optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) was measured using a BioTek Cytation3 plate reader at initial and final time points, to account for extract colour. The IC<sub>50</sub> for growth was defined as the lowest concentration at which an extract displayed ≥50% inhibition and MIC (IC<sub>90</sub>) at ≥90% inhibition.</p><p id="Par39">Extracts active against multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (OIFC143) and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> (NR-15410) were tested for growth inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic> and additional strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Biofilm inhibition assays for <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic></title><p id="Par40">Biofilm inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> was performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Briefly, supplemented TSB with 3% NaCl, 0.5% dextrose, and 2% human plasma was used in 96-well microtiter plates (Falcon 35–1172). Working cultures of UAMS-1 (<italic toggle="yes">wt</italic>) and UAMS-929 (isogenic <italic toggle="yes">ΔsarA</italic> mutant of UAMS-1) were standardized to a concentration of 5 × 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/mL and the final well volume was 0.2 mL. Extracts were assessed at sub-IC<sub>50</sub> concentrations for growth, ranging from 2.0 to 256 µg/mL. The vehicle and positive control, 220D-F2, were assessed from 2.0 to 256 µg/mL. All experiments were incubated statically at 37 °C for 22 hours. Optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) was measured using a BioTek Cytation3 plate reader at initial and final time points, to account for extract colour. Biofilms were rinsed twice with 1X PBS, fixed with 100% EtOH, and stained with crystal violet. The dry stain was eluted with ethanol, diluted in PBS, and quantified at 595 nm using a BioTek Cytation 3 plate reader. The MBIC<sub>50</sub> (minimum biofilm inhibitory concentration) was defined as the lowest concentration at which an extract displayed ≥50% inhibition and MBIC<sub>90</sub> at ≥90% inhibition.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Quorum quenching assays for <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic></title><p id="Par41">Examination of the quorum quenching potential of extracts against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> was conducted as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Briefly, all <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic> fluorescent reporter strains were maintained in chloramphenicol (10 µg/mL) supplemented TSA and TSB. The assay was conducted in tissue culture-treated clear bottom, black-sided 96-well microtiter plates (Costar 3603) with a final well volume of 0.2 mL. Extracts were assessed at sub-MIC<sub>50</sub> concentrations, ranging from 0.5 to 64 µg/mL. Vehicle and positive control, 224C-F2, were also assessed from 0.5 to 64 µg/mL. Plates were incubated at 37 °C in a humidified chamber, shaking at 1200 rpm (Stuart SI505). OD (600 nm) and fluorescence (493 nm excitation, 535 nm emission) readings were taken at initial (0 hr) and final (22 hr) time points.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Cytotoxicity assays</title><p id="Par42">Human immortalized keratinocytes (HaCaT) were maintained and used to examine the cytotoxicity of the active extracts with an LDH cytotoxicity assay (G-Biosciences, St. Louis, MO) as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Briefly, the cell culture was standardized to 4 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/mL using a hemocytometer and 0.2 mL added per well in a tissue culture treated 96-well microtiter plate (Falcon 35–3075). Plates were incubated for 48 hours to allow for seeding, and then cells were exposed to fresh media with treatment. Extracts and vehicle were serially diluted 2-fold (2–256 μg/mL) and were processed 24 hours post-treatment following manufacturer’s protocol for chemical induced cytotoxicity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Chemical analysis</title><p id="Par43">HPLC methods were adapted from Mämmelä<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> and were performed on an Agilent 1260 Infinity system running OpenLab CDS ChemStation (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) with an Agilent Zorbax Eclipse XDB-C18 (250 × 4.6 mm, 5 µm) column with compatible guard column at 35 °C. A gradient elution consisting of mobile phases (A) 1% formic acid in H<sub>2</sub>O and (B) 1.0% formic acid in MeOH at 1.0 mL/min beginning at 95:5 A:B for 9 min, then following a linear gradient to 0:100 A:B at 69 min, which was held for 9 min, before returning to initial conditions to equilibrate the column. Extracts were prepared for HPLC at 10 mg/mL in DI H<sub>2</sub>O with an injection volume of 10 µL.</p><p id="Par44">The liquid chromatography-Fourier transform mass spectrometry (LC-FTMS) analysis was performed using a Shimadzu SIL-ACHT and Dionex 3600 SD HPLC pump with a modification of the previous method. A 10 µL injection at ambient temperature with (A) 1.0% formic acid in H2O and (B) 1% formic acid in MeOH at a flow rate of 1.0 mL/min. Initial conditions were 95:5 (A:B) and held for 9 min, changing to 38:62 (A:B) using a linear gradient at 85 min, and then 100% B at 109 min, which was held for 10 min before returning to initial conditions to equilibrate the column. The data was acquired in MS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> mode scanning from a <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> of 150–1500 on a Thermo Scientific LTQ-FT Ultra MS in negative ESI mode and processed with Thermo Scientific Xcalibur 2.2 software (San Jose, CA). The capillary temperature was 275.0 °C, nitrogen was the sheath gas at a flow of 60, source voltage and current 5.0 kV and 100.0 µA, and the capillary voltage −19.0 V.</p><p id="Par45">Using SciFinder Scholar (Chemical Abstracts Service, Columbus, OH, USA) all reported compounds from the genus <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic> were searched for matches to the LC-FTMS accurate mass data for each peak. The resulting putative compounds for samples 619-F2 and 620 are listed in Supplementary Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec19"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2019_44242_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Data</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-019-44242-y.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. Alexander Horswill for providing the <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic> reporter strains. Thanks to Dr. E. Jane Bradbury for help with plant identification and collection. This work was supported in part by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute Science Education Program award #52006923 to Emory University. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute or Emory University. This work was also supported by a grant from the National Institutes of Health, National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (R01 AT007052, PI: CQ) and National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease (R21 AI136563, PI: CQ). The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily reflect the officinal view of NCCIH, NIAID or NIH. The funding agencies had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. Material has been reviewed by the Walter Reed Army Institute of Research. There is no objection to its presentation and/or publication. The opinions or assertions contained herein are the private views of the author and are not to be construed as official or as reflecting true views of the Department of the Army or the Department of Defense.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>M.D.: Collected the material; C.Q., D.Z. and J.L.: Conceived and designed the experiments; M.D., J.L., B.D., R.D. and K.N.: Performed the experiments; M.D. and C.Q.: Analyzed the data; M.D., J.L. and C.Q.: Prepared the draft; All authors proofread the final draft and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article and its Supplementary Information Files.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par46">The research herein was conducted in absence of any competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Antibiotic Resistance Threats in the United States. (Atlanta, GA, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>William Costerton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance of bacteria in biofilms</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2001</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(01)05321-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11463434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quave</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Castanea sativa</italic> (European Chestnut) leaf extracts rich in ursene and oeanene derivatives block <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> virulence and pathogenesis without detectable resistance</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0136486</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26295163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4546677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoiby</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies for combating bacterial biofilm infections</article-title><source>Int J Oral Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ijos.2014.65</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25504208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4817533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Porcher, F. P. <italic toggle="yes">Resources of the Southern Fields and Forests</italic>. (Evans &amp; Cogswell, 1863).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifi-Rad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plants of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Allium</italic> as antibacterial agents: From tradition to pharmacy</article-title><source>Cell Mol Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27585263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ajoene, a sulfur-rich molecule from garlic, inhibits genes controlled by quorum sensing</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2012</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2314</fpage><lpage>2325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.05919-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22314537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3346669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Office of the Historian United States Department of State. <italic toggle="yes">The Blockade of Confederate Ports, 1861–1865</italic>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://history.state.gov/milestones/1861-1865/blockade">https://history.state.gov/milestones/1861-1865/blockade</ext-link> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipińska</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klewicka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sójka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure, occurrence and biological activity of ellagitannins: a general review</article-title><source>Acta Sci Pol Technol Aliment</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17306/J.AFS.2014.3.7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24887944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Moore, S. P. <italic toggle="yes">Standard Supply Table of the Indigenous Remedies for Field Service</italic>. (Richmond, 1863).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. National Library of Medicine. <italic toggle="yes">Maimed Men- Life and Limb: The Toll of the American Civil War</italic>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/exhibition/lifeandlimb/maimedmen.html">https://www.nlm.nih.gov/exhibition/lifeandlimb/maimedmen.html</ext-link> (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ekor, M. The growing use of herbal medicines: issues relating to adverse reactions and challenges in monitoring safety. <italic toggle="yes">Front Pharmacol</italic><bold>4</bold>, 10.3389/fphar.2013.00177 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2013.00177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3887317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24454289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cragg</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural products as sources of new drugs from 1981 to 2014</article-title><source>J Nat Prod</source><year>2016</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jnatprod.5b01055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26852623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolmacheva</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogozhin</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deryabin</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and quorum sensing regulatory activities of some traditional Eastern-European medicinal plants</article-title><source>Acta Pharm</source><year>2014</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/acph-2014-0019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24914718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survey of Higher Plants for Presence of Antibacterial Substances</article-title><source>Botanical Gazette</source><year>1947</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/335424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Bj</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Skc</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative study on phenolic profiles and antioxidant activities of legumes as affected by extraction solvents</article-title><source>J Food Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>S159</fpage><lpage>S166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2006.00260.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17995858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertweck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spitellert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical Ecology of Endophytic Fungi: Origins of Secondary Metabolites</article-title><source>Chem Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chembiol.2012.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22840767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimycobacterial natural products from endophytes of the medicinal plant <italic toggle="yes">Aralia nudicaulis</italic></article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1641</fpage><lpage>1642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26669092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimycobacterial screening of traditional medicinal plants using the microplate resazurin assay</article-title><source>Can J Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>487</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/W10-035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20657619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karioti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial properties of <italic toggle="yes">Quercus ilex</italic> L. proanthocyanidin dimers and simple phenolics: Evaluation of their synergistic activity with conventional antimicrobials and prediction of their pharmacokinetic profile</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>6412</fpage><lpage>6422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf2011535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21563833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sati</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sati</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sati</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis and antimicrobial activity of volatile constituents from <italic toggle="yes">Quercus leucotrichophora</italic> (Fagaceae) bark</article-title><source>Nat Prod Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786419.2011.564584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21929280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobby</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Quercus cerris</italic> extracts limit <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2012</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2012.10.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23127649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3516361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ul Haq</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qayyum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of antibacterial compounds from <italic toggle="yes">Quercus dilatata</italic> L. through bioassay guided fractionation</article-title><source>Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-0711-11-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22554280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3416653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan Nor Amilah</surname><given-names>WaW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masrah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasmah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noor Izani</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of <italic toggle="yes">Quercus infectoria</italic> gall extracts against multidrug resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Trop Biomed</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25776593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deryabin</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolmacheva</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and anti-quorum sensing molecular composition derived from <italic toggle="yes">Quercus</italic> cortex (Oak bark) extract</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>17093</fpage><lpage>17108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules200917093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26393551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6332234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohebi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> antibacterial activity of acorn herbal extract against some Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria</article-title><source>Roum Arch Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2011</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22568261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chusri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voravuthikunchai</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detailed studies on <italic toggle="yes">Quercus infectoria</italic> Olivier (nutgalls) as an alternative treatment for methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2008.03979.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19120622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tannins and human health: a review</article-title><source>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr</source><year>1998</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408699891274273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9759559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwatsuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial action of several tannins against <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2001</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/48.4.487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11581226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sarwar, R. <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. Evaluation of antioxidant, free radical scavenging, and antimicrobial activity of <italic toggle="yes">Quercus incana</italic> Roxb. <italic toggle="yes">Front Pharmacol</italic><bold>6</bold>, 10.3389/fphar.2015.00277 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2015.00277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4655348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26635607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brussell</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Araliaceae species used for culinary and medicinal purposes in Niigata-ken, Japan</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1663/0013-0001(2004)058[0736:ASUFCA]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>4-epi-Pimaric acid: a phytomolecule as a potent antibacterial and anti-biofilm agent for oral cavity pathogens</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-011-1287-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21594714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palazzo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Setzer</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal variation and bioactivity in the leaf oil of <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic> growing in Huntsville, Alabama</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19634333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graziose</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antiplasmodial activity of aporphine alkaloids and sesquiterpene lactones from <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic> L</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2010.08.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20826204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3010440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Farnesyl protein transferase and tumor cell growth inhibitory activities of lipiferolide isolated from <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic></article-title><source>Arch Pharm Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>299</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02977609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17424934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doskotch</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Feraly</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antitumor agents II: Tulipinolide, a new germacranolide sesquiterpene, and costunolide. Two cytotoxic substances from <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron tulipifera</italic> L</article-title><source>JPharmSci</source><year>1969</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jps.2600580720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5810209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zeng, C.-z. &amp; Liu, Z.-x. Bacteriostatic activity and stability of extracts from <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron chinense</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Hubei Agric Sci</italic>, 1222–1224 (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The investigation of inhibiting quorum sensing and methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation from <italic toggle="yes">Liriodendron</italic> hybrid</article-title><source>Pak J Pharm Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26004723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">SERNEC. <italic toggle="yes">Southeast Regional Network of Expertise and Collections</italic>, http://sernecportal.org/portal/collections/list.php?collector=Dettweiler&amp;eventdate1=April%202015&amp;eventdate2=July%202015&amp;db=279;&amp;page=1 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cockerill, F. R. <italic toggle="yes">Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing: twenty-third informational supplement; M100 - S23</italic>. (CLSI, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quave</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ellagic acid derivatives from <italic toggle="yes">Rubus ulmifolius</italic> inhibit <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation and improve response to antibiotics</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e28737</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22242149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3252291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mämmelä</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindroos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kangas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vartiainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of oak tannins by liquid chromatography-electrospray ionisation mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J Chromatogr A</source><year>2000</year><volume>891</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9673(00)00624-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10999626</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>