<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi Pharm J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi Pharm J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2116</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">saudipharmj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Pharmaceutical Journal : SPJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1319-0164</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2213-7475</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10981156</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10981156.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10981156</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10981156</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38558886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsps.2024.102041</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1319-0164(24)00091-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102041</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessing the antibacterial potential of 6-gingerol: Combined experimental and computational approaches</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elfaky</surname><given-names initials="MA">Mahmoud A.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okairy</surname><given-names initials="HM">Hassan M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names initials="HM">Hossam M.</given-names></name><email>hmafifi@kau.edu.sa</email><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koshak</surname><given-names initials="AE">Abdulrahman E.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names initials="GA">Gamal A.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names initials="SRM">Sabrin R.M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alzain</surname><given-names initials="AA">Abdulrahim A.</given-names></name><xref rid="af025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au040"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegazy</surname><given-names initials="WAH">Wael A.H.</given-names></name><xref rid="af030" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="af035" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au045"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khafagy</surname><given-names initials="ES">El-Sayed</given-names></name><xref rid="af040" ref-type="aff">h</xref><xref rid="af045" ref-type="aff">i</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au050"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seleem</surname><given-names initials="NM">Noura M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Department of Natural Products and Alternative Medicine, Faculty of Pharmacy, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Centre for Artificial Intelligence in Precision Medicines, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="af015"><label>c</label>Preparatory Year Program, Department of Chemistry, Batterjee Medical College, Jeddah 21442, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="af020"><label>d</label>Department of Pharmacognosy, Faculty of Pharmacy, Assiut University, Assiut 71526, Egypt</aff><aff id="af025"><label>e</label>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Gezira, Wad Madani 21111, Sudan</aff><aff id="af030"><label>f</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Pharmacy, Zagazig University, Zagazig 44519, Egypt</aff><aff id="af035"><label>g</label>Pharmacy Program, Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Oman College of Health Sciences, Muscat 113, Oman</aff><aff id="af040"><label>h</label>Department of Pharmaceutics, College of Pharmacy, Prince Sattam Bin Abdulaziz University, Al-Kharj 11942, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="af045"><label>i</label>Department of Pharmaceutics and Industrial Pharmacy, Faculty of Pharmacy, Suez Canal University, Ismailia 41522, Egypt</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Natural Products and Alternative Medicine, Faculty of Pharmacy, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia. <email>hmafifi@kau.edu.sa</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">458442</issue-id><elocation-id>102041</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-02 12:25:23.027"><day>02</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab005"><p>The rise of antibiotic resistance in bacteria is becoming a global concern, particularly due to the dwindling supply of new antibiotics. This situation mandates the discovery of new antimicrobial candidates. Plant-derived natural compounds have historically played a crucial role in the development of antibiotics, serving as a rich source of substances possessing antimicrobial properties. Numerous studies have supported the reputation of 6-gingerol, a prominent compound found in the ginger family, for its antibacterial properties. In this study, the antibacterial activities of 6-gingerol were evaluated against Gram-negative bacteria, <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, with a particular focus on the clinically significant Gram-negative <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and Gram-positive bacteria <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. Furthermore, the anti-virulence activities were assessed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic>. The current findings showed that 6-gingerol’s antibacterial activity is due to its significant effect on the disruption of the bacterial cell membrane and efflux pumps, as it significantly decreased the efflux and disrupted the cell membrane of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. Furthermore, 6-gingerol significantly decreased the biofilm formation and production of virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> in concentrations below MICs. The anti-virulence properties of 6-gingerol could be attributed to its capacity to disrupt bacterial virulence-regulating systems; quorum sensing (QS). 6-Gingerol was found to interact with QS receptors and downregulate the genes responsible for QS. In addition, molecular docking, and molecular dynamics (MD) simulation results indicated that 6-gingerol showed a comparable binding affinity to the co-crystalized ligands of different <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> QS targets as well as stable interactions during 100 ns MD simulations. These findings suggest that 6-gingerol holds promise as an anti-virulence agent that can be combined with antibiotics for the treatment of severe infections.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kg005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Antibacterial</kwd><kwd>6-Gingerol</kwd><kwd>Quorum sensing</kwd><kwd>Molecular docking</kwd><kwd>Molecular dynamics</kwd><kwd>Industrial development</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0005">The emergence of widespread bacterial resistance to antibiotics and the simultaneous decrease in the supply of effective antibiotics are interconnected issues that pose a serious threat to global healthcare. Bacterial resistance results in the emergence of superbugs impervious to existing antibiotics. Consequently, many infections become increasingly difficult and, in some cases, nearly impossible to treat (<xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Hoiby et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Carattoli, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al., 2019</xref>). Traditional antibiotics employ a range of mechanisms to combat bacterial infections, which are diverse in their targets and modes of action (<xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Li and Nikaido, 2004</xref>, <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Blair et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Girlich et al., 2020</xref>). However, the effectiveness of traditional antibiotics can diminish over time due to bacterial resistance developed through processes like horizontal gene transfer and the development of mutations (<xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Hoiby et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">Partridge et al., 2018</xref>). The dwindling supply of new antibiotics compounds this problem and mandates the discovery of new antibacterial and the development of new, efficient strategies to conquer bacterial resistance (<xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">Tacconelli et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Foletto et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Alandiyjany et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="p0010">Gram-positive and -negative bacteria employ diverse communities to control the virulence factors production during the different stages of infection, however, the quorum sensing (QS) systems play the principal roles in controlling bacterial virulence (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Juhas et al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Li and Tian, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Jiang and Li, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Elfaky et al., 2022</xref>, <xref rid="b0365" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2022</xref>). For instance, biofilm formation and production of diverse virulence factors are orchestrated in the population mainly by QS systems in both Gram-positive and -negative bacteria (<xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Parsek et al., 1999</xref>, <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">Rutherford and Bassler, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">Papenfort and Bassler, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Hegazy and Abbas, 2017</xref>). QS systems function in an inducer-receptor manner. They rely on the production and detection of signaling molecules, often referred to as autoinducers, to facilitate communication and coordination among the bacterial cells in a population. When a threshold concentration of these signaling molecules is reached, it triggers specific responses and behaviors in the bacterial community. This mechanism enables bacteria to collectively adapt and coordinate actions like virulence factor production, based on their population density (<xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Parsek et al., 1999</xref>, <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">Solano et al., 2014</xref>). Therefore, disrupting QS could potentially lead to a significant reduction in bacterial virulence. This supposition, where interference with QS is considered a promising approach to reducing bacterial virulence, can facilitate the immune system's efforts to eradicate the bacteria (<xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Rasmussen and Givskov, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Jiang and Li, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">Remy et al., 2018</xref>). Anti-QS agents have been proposed as potential antibiotics or adjuvants to antibiotics, aiding in the management of bacterial infections (<xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Almalki et al., 2022a</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Cavalu et al., 2022</xref>, <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Lila et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Natural compounds from plant sources have played a significant role in the history of antibiotics, serving as a source of compounds with antimicrobial properties (<xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Nascimento et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Ghosh et al., 2008</xref>). Numerous studies have confirmed the antibacterial properties of 6-gingerol, a prominent compound found in members of the ginger family such as ginger and grains of paradise (<xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Ilic et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Beristain-Bauza et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">Teles et al., 2019</xref>). 6-Gingerol has been extensively studied for its potential therapeutic effects, including anti-inflammatory (<xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Dugasani et al., 2010</xref>), antioxidant (<xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Masuda et al., 2004</xref>), and anti-nausea properties (<xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Mohd Yusof, 2016</xref>). Previous studies showed that 6-gingerol exhibited significant inhibition of biofilm formation in a fluconazole resistant strain of <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic>. It demonstrated the ability to decrease the virulence of the fungus (<xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2018</xref>). The antibiofilm activities of 6-gingerol have been studied, and its ability to disrupt quorum sensing (QS) mechanisms has been identified as the underlying cause of this attribute in multiple research findings (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Girhepunje et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">Parmar et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Shukla et al., 2021</xref>). In addition, 6-gingerol exhibited the capability to disrupt the quorum sensing (QS) mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, thereby reducing biofouling in reverse osmosis water treatment systems (<xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Ham et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">To the best of our knowledge, there are no detailed studies regarding the antibacterial and anti-virulence activities of 6-gingerol. The current study was aimed to evaluate 6-gingerol antibacterial activity, exploring the possible modes of its antibacterial actions against Gram-positive and -negative bacterial models: <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, respectively. Further, its anti-virulence and anti-QS activities including effect on production of virulence factors, biofilm formation, expression of QS-encoding genes and affinity to QS receptors have been studied in detail against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, and other Gram-negative bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumonia</italic>. Detailed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> investigations have been performed to explore the 6-gingerol’s antibacterial and anti-virulence activities.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Extraction of 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0025">Pure 6-Gingerol was isolated from <italic toggle="yes">A. melegueta</italic> seeds and identified by <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR as previously reported (<xref rid="s0235" ref-type="sec">Supporting data</xref>
<xref rid="s0235" ref-type="sec">Figs. S1–S4</xref>) (<xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Abdou et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Abdallah et al., 2022</xref>). NMR data were recorded on Bruker Avance DRX 850 MHz spectrometers (Bruker BioSpin/Billerica/MA/USA). The seeds were purchased from a local herbal shop in Cairo, Egypt, in 2021 and a specimen of the identified seeds (AM-1023) was retained at the Natural Products Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, King Abdulaziz University.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Chemicals and bacterial strains</title><p id="p0030">All the chemicals used were of pharmaceutical quality and obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). The media used were purchased from Oxoid (Hampshire, UK). The antibacterial activities were evaluated using Gram-negative bacterial model strains: <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC 27853), <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (ATCC 17978), and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (ATCC 700603), and Gram-positive <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 6538).</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Growth conditions and determination of minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) and growth effect at sub-MIC</title><p id="p0035">The bacterial stock cultures were maintained on Muller-Hinton (MH) agar plates, and a broth microdilution assay was performed to determine the MICs according to the guidelines of the Clinical Laboratory and Standards Institute (<xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Khayat et al., 2022</xref>). A loopful of fresh overnight bacterial culture was suspended in 5 mL normal saline and the turbidities were adjusted to the equivalent of 0.5 McFarland standard. The effect of the extracted 6-gingerol at sub-MIC (1/5 MIC) was evaluated on the growth of bacteria, as previously mentioned (<xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Hegazy et al., 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Evaluation of 6-gingerol anti-efflux pump activity</title><p id="p0040">To explore the gingerol effect on the efflux pump activity of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, a real-time quantification of an energy-dependent assay was conducted as previously described (<xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">Reens et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Abu Lila et al., 2023</xref>). Briefly, pellets collected from fresh overnight cultures in Luria-Bertani (LB) were washed with phosphate buffer saline (PBS) and 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and resuspended in PBS to optical densities OD<sub>600</sub> 0.5. Bacterial suspensions were mixed with 10 μM fluorescence Nile Red dye (Cas No.7385–67-3, Sigma-Aldrich/St. Louis/MO/USA) for 2 hrs at 37 °C. The bacterial pellets were collected by centrifugation and resuspended in 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>/PBS provided with 6-gingerol at MIC in 96-microtiter plates. Dye hydrolysis was estimated at 560/640 nm of excitation/emission. Glucose (2 mM) was added to the wells as an efflux pump activator and the efflux was estimated for 10 min. Glucose-treated Nile Red-stained bacterial cells and 6-gingerol-untreated Nile Red-stained cells were involved as controls. The increase of fluorescence inside the bacterial cells indicated the efflux pump inhibition. The experiment was conducted in triplicate and the relative fluorescence was normalized to the fluorescence intensity before glucose addition.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Evaluation of 6-gingerol effect on cell membrane</title><p id="p0045">The effect on bacterial membrane was assessed using carboxyfluorescein diacetate succinimidyl ester (CFDA-SE) dye as described previously (<xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Mattio et al., 2019</xref>). Briefly, the optical densities of overnight cultures were adjusted to (OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.5). The bacterial suspension was supplemented with 4 μM cFDA-SE (Cas No. 50347–59-4, Cayman Chemical/MI/USA), which is a precursor molecule of carboxyfluorescein diacetate succinimidyl ester (cFSE). Then, the bacterial suspensions were provided with 6-gingerol at MIC. For negative control, the cFSE-labeled cell suspension was likewise subjected to an equivalent volume of DMSO, which was used for dissolving 6-gingerol. The cell membrane active antibiotic kanamycin (125 µg/mL) was used as a positive control. After incubation for 30 min, 1 mL of the samples was centrifuged, and the supernatants were transferred to a 96-microtiter plate to quantify the fluorescence of cFSE at 490/520 nm of excitation/emission.</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.6</label><title>Evaluation of 6-gingerol effect on β-lactamase enzyme</title><p id="p0050">The 6-gingerol β-lactamase inhibition activity was assessed using a coulometric β-lactamase activity assay kit (product No. ab197008, Abcam/Md/USA). Fresh <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> cultures were prepared and adjusted to OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.5 and mixed or not with 6-gingerol at MIC. After overnight culturing, bacterial cells were collected to be resuspended in BL assay Buffer. The samples were sonicated for 5 min, kept on ice for 5 min, and centrifuged to remove insolubles, and collect the supernatants. The procedure of β-lactamase and calculations were performed according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.7</label><title>Biofilm formation assay</title><p id="p0055">Bacterial biofilm formation with and without the 6-gingerol at sub-MIC (1/5 MIC) was evaluated, as reported earlier (<xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Khayat et al., 2023</xref>). Briefly, overnight cultures were cultivated, diluted with 5 mL normal saline (0.85 % NaCl) and turbidity was adjusted to 1–5 x 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL; 200 μL of the prepared bacterial cultures were transferred into sterile 96-well microtiter plates and incubated at 37 °C for 24hrs. The planktonic bacteria were then removed, each well was rinsed twice by pipetting 1 mL sterile distilled water, and the plates were allowed to dry for 15 min at 37 °C in the incubator. 200 µL of 1 % crystal violet (CV) (prepared in 100 % ethanol) was added and incubated at 25 °C for another 15 min. CV was poured and plates were rinsed thrice by adding 1 mL of sterile distilled water. The plates were then allowed to dry at room temperature for 20 min. CV was solubilized by adding 200 µL of 30 % glacial acetic acid and the optical densities were measured at OD590 by a microplate reader. All assays were performed in triplicate. Sub-MIC of ciprofloxacin and dimethyl sulfoxide (1 % v/v) were used as positive and negative controls, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>2.8</label><title>Evolution of 6-gingerol effect on bacterial motility</title><p id="p0060">As previously described, LB agar plates containing 6-gingerol at sub-MIC (1/5 MIC) concentration were prepared and inoculated at the center with 5 µL of optically adjusted fresh overnight <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">Thabit et al., 2022</xref>). Controls were prepared by central inoculation with untreated <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. Swarming motility zones were measured in mm.</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><label>2.9</label><title>Evaluation of 6-gingerol effect on protease production</title><p id="p0065">Protease production was assessed in the presence and absence of 6-gingerol at 1/5 MIC, following the previously described method (<xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Saqr et al., 2021</xref>). In summary, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> overnight cultures with an optical density at 600 nm (OD600) of 0.4 were cultivated in LB broth with or without 6-gingerol at 1/4 × concentration. After overnight incubation at 37 °C, the supernatants were collected and combined with a mixture of 2 % casein in PBS (0.05 M) and NaOH (0.1 M) at pH 7.0, in a 1:1 ratio. The mixture was then incubated at 37 °C for 15 min. The reaction was halted by adding 2 mL of 0.4 M trichloroacetic acid for 25 min. Following centrifugation, the optical densities of the supernatants were measured at 660 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>2.10</label><title>Evaluation of 6-gingerol effect on hemolysins production</title><p id="p0070">The supernatants were collected from <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> overnight cultures as described above, and hemolysin assay was performed with and without 6-gingerol at 1/5 MIC as previously shown (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Almalki et al., 2022b</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Cavalu et al., 2022</xref>). Briefly, the supernatant was mixed with 2 % erythrocyte suspensions sterile saline in the ratio of 1:1, and kept for 2 hrs at 37 °C. After centrifugation, the optical densities of the released hemoglobin were measured at 540 nm. Negative and positive controls were prepared using intact and fully lysed erythrocytes, respectively, achieved by the addition of 0.1 % sodium dodecyl sulfate.</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>2.11</label><title>Evaluation of 6-gingerol effect on the production of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and S. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> pigments</title><p id="p0075">The effect of the 6-gingerol at 1/5 MIC on pyocyanin (<xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Cavalu et al., 2022</xref>) and staphyloxanthin (<xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Almalki et al., 2022c</xref>) biosynthesis was detected as formerly described.</p></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>2.12</label><title>Effect of 6-gingerol on the expression of QS-encoding genes</title><p id="p0080">RNA was extracted from <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> fresh overnight cultures, both treated and untreated with 6-gingerol at 1/5 MIC, using an RNA extraction and purification kit from Life Technologies (Carlsbad, CA, USA). The collected RNA samples were quantified using a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (Wilmington, DE, USA) and stored at −80 °C (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Askoura et al., 2022</xref>). The expression levels were normalized to the housekeeping gene <italic toggle="yes">ropD</italic>, and the expressions were determined using the comparative threshold cycle (ΔΔCt) method, with the primers previously reported in other studies (<xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Saqr et al., 2021</xref>). cDNA was synthesized using a reverse transcriptase kit from Applied Biosystems (Waltham, MA, USA), and the resulting cDNA was amplified using the Syber Green I PCR Master Kit from Fermentas (Waltham, MA, USA), using the Step One instrument from Applied Biosystems (Waltham, MA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s0075"><label>2.13</label><title>In silico study</title><sec id="s0080"><label>2.13.1</label><title>Molecular docking</title><p id="p0085">In this research, the structures of various targets related to <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, including QscR (PDB ID: 3SZT), LasR (PDB ID: 2UV0), PqsR (PDB ID: 4JVD), RhlR (PDB ID: 7R3H), MexB (PDB ID: 3W9J), and AmpC (PDB ID: 4WZ4), were acquired from the Protein Data Bank. The preparation of these structures was carried out using the Protein Preparation Wizard in Maestro. The determination of binding sites around the bound ligands was conducted using the Receptor Grid Generation tool in Maestro. 6-Gingerol was prepared using the LigPrep tool in Maestro. Gingerol and the bound references were docked into the active sites of the targets using the extra precision mode of the Glide tool.</p></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>2.13.2</label><title>Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations</title><p id="p0090">In our study, we used the Desmond tool, which is part of the Schrodinger software suite, to perform molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. These simulations examined how 6-gingerol and a reference bound ligand (N-3-oxo-dodecanoyl-L-Homoserine Lactone) interacted with the QscR protein.</p><p id="p0095">During the simulation process, we employed TIP3P as a solvent model in an orthorhombic box, that extended outward by 10 Ã… in all directions. To describe the behavior of molecules accurately, we used the OPLS4 force field. Our simulation conditions were set to match those found at 1 atmosphere of pressure and a temperature of 300 Kelvin, within the NTP ensemble class.</p><p id="p0100">In total, our simulation ran for 100 ns (ns), and we collected data at regular intervals of 100 picoseconds, resulting in 1000 recorded frames. To analyze the trajectories during the simulation, we used the simulation interaction diagram of Maestro. Additionally, we delved into various aspects of the MD simulation, such as measuring the root mean square deviation (RMSD) of the protein, the root means square fluctuation (RMSF) of both the protein and the bound ligand, and the interactions between the protein and ligand.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0090"><label>2.14</label><title>In-vivo evaluation</title><p id="p0105">To evaluate the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> anti-virulence activity of 6-gingerol at 1/5 MIC, a mouse protection assay was used, as described in previous studies (<xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Aldawsari et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Saqr et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">Thabit et al., 2022</xref>). Fresh cultures of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> were prepared and allowed to grow in the presence or absence of gingerol at sub-MIC concentration. The optical densities of the cultures were adjusted to an OD600 of 0.4. Three-week-old Mus musculus mice were divided into six groups of five mice each. The first and second groups served as negative controls and were not inoculated; nor did they receive intra-peritoneal (Ip) injections of sterile PBS. The third and fourth groups were Ip injected with DMSO-treated <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, serving as positive controls. The fifth and sixth groups were Ip injected with <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa,</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> treated with gingerol at sub-MIC concentration. The survival of the mice was monitored over five consecutive days to observe any fatalities.</p></sec><sec id="s0095"><label>2.15</label><title>Microdilution checkerboard assay</title><p id="p0110">The interaction between gingerol and the tested antibiotics against <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> was evaluated using a checkerboard assay (<xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Elfaky et al., 2023</xref>). Briefly, serial dilutions of gingerol were vertically placed in a microtiter plate, while dilutions of tested antibiotics were horizontally placed to attain the checkerboard pattern. Bacterial cells were diluted to 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL and added to each well. After overnight incubation at 37 °C, 5 µL was drawn from each well and plated to determine viable cells (<xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2015</xref>). The fractional inhibitory concentration index (FICI) was calculated (<xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Khayyat et al., 2021</xref>). Antibiotic potentiation were evaluated to check their efficacy in the presence of gingerol, and the MICs of antibiotics were determined in the presence of gingerol (<xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0100"><label>2.16</label><title>Statistics</title><p id="p0115">All tests were conducted in triplicate, and the results reported as mean ± standard error of mean. Unless otherwise mentioned, all results were analyzed using Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, where <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0105"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0110"><label>3.1</label><title>Isolation and characterization of 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0120">6-Gingerol (<xref rid="s0235" ref-type="sec">Fig. S1</xref>) was isolated as a yellow oil with molecular weight 294 (<xref rid="s0235" ref-type="sec">Fig. S2</xref>). <sup>1</sup>H NMR spectra showed three aromatic protons at δ<sub>H</sub> 6.68 (d, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 1.7 Hz, H-2′), 6.82 (d, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 8.5 Hz, H5′), and 6.66 (dd, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 1.7, 8.5 Hz, H-6′), indicating the presence of 1,3,4-trisubstituted phenyl ring. In addition, the spectra displayed an oxymethine proton at δ<sub>H</sub> 4.03 correlated in HSQC with carbon at δ<sub>C</sub> 67.6. The positioning of the hydroxyl group at C-5 was confirmed through a strong correlation between H-5 at δ<sub>H</sub> 4.03 and carbons at δ<sub>C</sub> 211.5 of the carbonyl group. Moreover, the spectra displayed the characteristic peak of terminal methyl at 0.88 (t, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 7.6 Hz, H-10), in addition to seven methylene groups at δ<sub>H</sub> 2.83 (t, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 7.7 Hz, H-1), 2.73 (t, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 7.7 Hz, H-2), 2.46 (dd, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 2.5, 17.0 Hz, H-4a), 2.55 (dd, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 9.0, 17.0 Hz, H-4b), and 1.18–1.20 (m, H-6–9) (<xref rid="s0235" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref>). The structure identity of this compound was confirmed by comparing the obtained data with the published data (<xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Abdou et al., 2021</xref>) (<xref rid="s0235" ref-type="sec">Figs. S3 and S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0115"><label>3.2</label><title>Antibacterial activity of 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0125">The lowest concentration of 6-gingerol that inhibited the growth of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, was 0.4 mg/mL, while it inhibited the growth of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> at 0.2 mg/mL.</p><sec id="s0120"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Anti-efflux activity of 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0130">The influence on bacterial efflux was assayed by real-time quantification of an energy-dependent efflux of Nile Red dye (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). 6-Gingerol at MIC reduced the <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> efflux, as the fluorescence of dye was significantly increased (indicating its accumulation into cells due to anti-efflux activity) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). On the other hand, 6-gingerol had no significant effect on the <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> efflux.<fig id="f0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Inhibition of energy-dependent efflux pumps. The efflux of Nile Red was assayed in the presence of 6-gingerol at MIC in comparison to untreated Nile Red stained and glucose treated-Nile Red-stained <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. 6-Gingerol significantly enhanced the efflux of tested bacterial stains (* <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00005" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0125"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Cell membrane damage activity of 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0135">The fluorescent dye CFDA-SE is commonly employed to evaluate the damage effects on the cell membrane. This dye can enter cells and hydrolyzed to yield carboxyfluorescein derivative (cFSE) that remains trapped inside the cells; its leakage indicates the cell membrane damage. The current results showed a significant increase in the intensity of the fluorescence, indicating the ability of 6-gingerol to damage the cell membranes of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="f0010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>6-Gingerol increased the leakage of cFSE due to membrane damages. The leakage of fluorescent dye was increased significantly as compared to untreated <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> controls (*** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Kanamycin-treated bacterial cell suspensions were used as positive controls.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00010" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0130"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Effect of 6-gingerol on the production of β-lactamase</title><p id="p0140">The effect of 6-gingerol on the production of β-lactamases was quantified calorimetrically. Though 6-gingerol showed a significant effect on the production of β-lactamase in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus,</italic> there was no significant effect on its production in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="f0015" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>6-Gingerol effect on the production of β-lactamase. The β-lactamase activity was assayed in the <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> cultures treated or not with 6-gingerol at MIC. However, 6-gingerol showed significant reducing effect on the production of β-lactamase in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (* <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), it had no significant influence in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00015" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0135"><label>3.3</label><title>Anti-virulence activity of 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0145">To ensure that the anti-virulence activities were solely attributed to 6-gingerol, excluding its effect on bacterial growth, the bacterial viable counts were performed in the presence of sub-MIC (1/5 MIC) of 6-gingerol, compared to untreated bacteria. The sub-MIC of 6-gingerol did not show any notable impact on bacterial growth, nor did it significantly affect bacterial counts in the presence or absence of 6-gingerol at sub-MIC levels (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Consequently, all the subsequent experiments were performed using 6-gingerol at sub-MIC.<fig id="f0020" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The effect of 6-gingerol at sub-MIC on the growth of (<bold>A</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, (<bold>B</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, (<bold>C</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, and (<bold>D</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. There were no significant differences between the viable counts of the treated and untreated tested strains. (ns: * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00020" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><sec id="s0140"><label>3.3.1</label><title>Anti-biofilm activity</title><p id="p0150">The crystal violet method was employed to evaluate the impact of sub-MIC concentrations of 6-gingerol on biofilm formation. The absorbances of crystal violet staining, which indicated the presence of adhered biofilm-forming bacteria, were measured. It was observed that 6-gingerol significantly reduced the absorbance, suggesting the inhibition of biofilm formation. The results revealed that 6-gingerol exhibited a notable ability to decrease biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><bold>A</bold>).<fig id="f0025" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The anti-virulence activity of 6-gingerol at sub-MIC. (<bold>A</bold>) Antibiofilm activity: 6-gingerol at sub-MIC significantly diminished the production of biofilm in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. (B) Effect on bacterial motility: 6-gingerol significantly reduced the <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> swarming motility. (C) Effect on the production of virulent enzymes: gingerol significantly decreased the production of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> protease and hemolysins. (D) Effect on production of virulent factors: 6-gingerol significantly diminished the production of the <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> virulent pigment pyocyanin and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> virulent pigment staphyloxanthin. The data are presented as a percent change from untreated controls. (*** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00025" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0145"><label>3.3.2</label><title>Effect on <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> motility</title><p id="p0155">The extent of the swarming zones formed by <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> was measured on MH agar plates with or without the addition of sub-MIC concentrations of 6-gingerol. The presence of 6-gingerol significantly reduced the motility of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><bold>B</bold>).</p></sec><sec id="s0150"><label>3.3.3</label><title>Effect on production of virulent enzymes</title><p id="p0160"><italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is characterized by its wide arsenal of virulence factors, including protease and hemolysins that play a role in the spread and establishment of infections. 6-Gingerol decreased the production of protease and hemolysins in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><bold>C</bold>).</p></sec><sec id="s0155"><label>3.3.4</label><title>Effect on the production of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> virulent pigments</title><p id="p0165">The staphyloxanthin and pyocyanin pigments produced by <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, respectively play key roles in the pathogenesis of the host. Accordingly, the release of these two virulent pigments was assayed in the presence of 6-gingerol at sub-MIC, compared to untreated controls. It was found that 6-Gingerol significantly reduced the production of these virulent pigments (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><bold>D</bold>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0160"><label>3.4</label><title>Anti-QS activity of 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0170">QS systems orchestrate the production of bacterial biofilm and other bacterial virulence factors as enzymes and virulent pigments.</p><sec id="s0165"><label>3.4.1</label><title>Assessing the expression of QS-encoding genes in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic></title><p id="p0175">To assess the anti-quorum sensing (QS) activity of 6-gingerol, Rt-PCR was conducted to quantify the impact of 6-gingerol on the expression of genes involved in QS (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). The results demonstrated that 6-gingerol exhibited a significant capability to downregulate the expression of all tested QS-encoding genes.<fig id="f0030" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Effect of 6-gingerol on the expression of QS genes in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. 6-Gingerol significantly downregulated the expression of QS receptors and autoinducer encoding genes. (** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00030" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0170"><label>3.4.2</label><title>Virtual evaluation of 6-gingerol affinity to QS targets</title><sec id="s0175"><label>3.4.2.1</label><title>Molecular docking</title><p id="p0180">This docking study aimed to evaluate how well 6-gingerol binds to different targets associated with <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. The docking scores of 6-gingerol were compared to those of co-crystalized reference compounds to investigate its potential antibacterial mechanism against <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>).<fig id="f0035" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>2D and 3D interactions of 6-gingerol in complex with various targets related to <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. (<bold>A</bold>) QscR, (<bold>B</bold>) LasR, (<bold>C</bold>) PqsR, and (<bold>D</bold>) RhlR.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00035" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7a.jpg"/><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00835" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7b.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0185">The results indicated that 6-gingerol displayed varying levels of binding affinity to the different <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> QS targets. A more negative docking score indicated a stronger binding affinity to the proteins (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For QscR, gingerol achieved a docking score of −10.158 kcal/mol, slightly outperforming the reference compound (-9.878 kcal/mol), suggesting competitive binding. Gingerol showed slightly weaker binding to LasR compared to the reference compound, with docking scores of −9.709 kcal/mol and −10.097 kcal/mol, respectively.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>XP docking scores of 6-gingerol and the bound references with various targets related to <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa.</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Name</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">PubChem ID</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Docking Scores (kcal/mol)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">QscR<break/>(PDB ID: 3SZT)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">LasR<break/>(PDB ID: 2UV0)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PqsR<break/>(PDB ID: 4JVD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">RhlR<break/>(PDB ID: 7R3H)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6-Gingerol</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">442,793</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.158</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−9.709</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.498</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−8.436</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Co-crystalized reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−9.878</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.097</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.698</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.062</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0190">In the case of PqsR, 6-gingerol exhibited a docking score of −6.498 kcal/mol, similar to the reference compound (-6.698 kcal/mol), indicating a comparable binding affinity. For RhlR, 6-gingerol obtained a docking score of −8.436 kcal/mol, whereas the reference compound scored −6.062 kcal/mol, indicating competitive binding.</p><p id="p0195">We examined the interactions between 6-gingerol and the targets. 6-Gingerol formed hydrogen bonds with specific amino acid residues in the binding pockets of the proteins, such as SER38, TYR58, and GLY40 in QscR, TYR56 and LEU125 in LasR, GLN194, LEU197, and ILE208 in PqsR, and TYR64 in RhlR. Additionally, 6-gingerol engaged in hydrophobic interactions with all the targets, which further supported stable binding modes.</p></sec><sec id="s0180"><label>3.4.2.2</label><title>Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations</title><p id="p0200">The selection of QscR as the target for the MD studies was based on the docking scores of 6-gingerol compared to the other protein targets. Further, the docking study showed the formation of multiple hydrogen bonds between gingerol and the QscR protein.</p><p id="p0205">MD simulations were performed for 100 ns, and within the initial 45 ns, fluctuations were observed in both 6-gingerol and the reference compound while they were bound to QscR (<xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). Throughout the entire simulation, the 6-gingerol-QscR complex exhibited a stable interaction, with RMSD values consistently below 4 Å until the end of the simulation. On the other hand, the reference-QscR complex maintained RMSD values around 5 Å throughout the 100 ns simulation.<fig id="f0040" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>The protein–ligand RMSD plot of 6-gingerol and the reference complexed with QscR (PDB ID: 3SZT). A: 6-gingerol, B: bound ligand (N-3-oxo-dodecanoyl-L-Homoserine Lactone).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00040" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr8.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0210">The RMSF values, which indicated protein fluctuations, were similar for both the 6-gingerol-QscR and reference-QscR complexes, with an average value of 1.085 Å and a standard deviation of 0.4771. This indicated that the protein remained stable during the simulations (<xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>).<fig id="f0045" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>The protein RMSF plot of 6-gingerol and the reference complexed with QscR (PDB ID: 3SZT). A: 6-gingerol, B: bound ligand (N-3-oxo-dodecanoyl-L-Homoserine Lactone).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00045" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr9.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0215">Further analysis of the RMSF values for 6-gingerol and the reference compound when bound to QscR revealed average values of 1.706 Å (with a standard deviation of 0.5636) and 1.465 Å (with a standard deviation of 0.2945), respectively. These findings suggested that both compounds exhibited similar fluctuation patterns during their interaction with QscR (<xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>).<fig id="f0050" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>The ligand RMSF plot of 6-gingerol and the reference complexed with QscR (PDB ID: 3SZT). A: gingerol, B: bound ligand (N-3-oxo-dodecanoyl-L-Homoserine Lactone).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00050" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr10.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0220">In the 6-gingerol-QscR complex, hydrogen bonds were observed with amino acids like ASN98 (40 %), TYR66 (10 %), ARG65, TRP62, and SER38. Additionally, water bridges were formed with TYR66 (20 %), ASP75, ASN98, PHE101, LYS63, SER56, PHE39, and SER38. In contrast, the reference-QscR complex primarily formed hydrogen bonds with SER38 (79 %) and SER129 (60 %) (<xref rid="f0055" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>).<fig id="f0055" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Protein-ligand contact histogram of 6-gingerol, and the reference complexed with QscR (PDB ID: 3SZT). A: 6-gingerol, B: bound ligand (N-3-oxo-dodecanoyl-L-Homoserine Lactone).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00055" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr11.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s0185"><label>3.5</label><title>Evaluation of 6-gingerol synergistic effect with antibiotics</title><p id="p0225">To evaluate the synergistic effect of 6-gingerol in combination with different antibiotics, cefepime, cefaperazone, and ciprofloxacin were chosen to be tested. The MICs of tested antibiotics against both <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> were determined in combination with 6-gingerol at sub-MIC (1/5 MIC) (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The current results showed FICs ≤ 0.5, indicating synergistic effects.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Interaction between 6-gingerol and antibiotics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Antibiotic</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC<sub>gen</sub></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">FIC</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC<sub>gen</sub></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">FIC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.125</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cefepime</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cefoperazone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.125</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Imipenem</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Piperacillin/tazobactam</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>FIC: Fractional inhibitory concentration = MIC<sub>gen</sub> drug in combination/MIC drug alone. The result of the combination may be antagonistic (FIC &gt; 4), indifferent (FIC &gt; 0.5 to 4), or synergistic (FIC ≤ 0.5). MICs and MIC<sub>gen</sub> are in µg/mL.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0190"><label>3.6</label><title>In vivo anti-virulence activity of the 6-gingerol</title><p id="p0230">An <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> protection assay was performed to evaluate the anti-virulence activities of 6-gingerol at sub-MIC against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. The deaths in each mice group were documented over five successive days and the results were plotted using the Kaplan–Meier method and the log-rank test was used to determine any trends statistically (<xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Khayat et al., 2022</xref>). In the negative control groups, no deaths were observed. In the mice group injected with <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, three out of the five mice died, while only one died of the five in the group injected with <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> treated with 6-gingerol (<xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref><bold>A</bold>). In the mice group injected with untreated <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, four out of five mice died, while one death was observed in the mice group injected with treated <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref><bold>B</bold>). These results showed a significant diminishing effect of 6-gingerol on the capacity of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> to induce <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> pathogenesis, log-rank test for trend <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0346 and 0.0032, respectively.<fig id="f0060" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>In vivo protection assay. Mice groups were injected with (A) <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> or (B) <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> treated or not with 6-gingerol at sub-MIC. Interestingly, 6-gingerol significantly decreased the <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> capacities to induce pathogenesis to the injected mice and protected the mice, log-rank test for trend <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0346 and 0.0032, respectively. *: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00060" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr12.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0195"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0235">Despite the significant success of antibiotics in controlling bacterial infections since their initial discovery, the development of resistance in bacteria is an inherent and evolutionary process. Bacteria possess the capability to adapt and evolve resistance mechanisms in response to the selective pressure imposed by antibiotics. This phenomenon causes a global and substantial concern. In light of this situation, the discovery of new antimicrobials is not merely a choice but a necessity. Many antimicrobial compounds have their origins in plants, highlighting the importance of exploring natural sources for potential solutions to combat antibiotic resistance and bacterial infections (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Agha et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Aldawsari et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Khayat et al., 2023</xref>). Grains of paradise has been reported to possess antibacterial properties, with its prominent active compound, 6-gingerol, believed to be a potentially effective antibacterial candidate.</p><p id="p0240">The antibacterial activity of the 6-gingerol has been documented in several studies as reviewed (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Girhepunje et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">Yahyazadeh et al., 2021</xref>). Particular attention has been paid to highly alkylated gingerols, specifically 10-gingerol and 12-gingerol, which have demonstrated significant effectiveness in inhibiting the growth of oral pathogens (<xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2008</xref>). Further, it has been observed that 6-gingerol showed promising potential adjuvant in combination with the first-line anti-TB drug isoniazid, suggesting 6-gingerol's possible role in enhancing the efficacy of tuberculosis treatment (<xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Bhaskar et al., 2020</xref>). In the present study, 6-gingerol showed antibacterial activity against Gram-negative <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> and Gram-positive <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> with MICs lower than 0.4 mg/mL. Typically, the antibacterial activities of antibiotics are attributed to their capability to target essential bacterial components or processes (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Blair et al., 2015</xref>). One of the most important bacterial targets is the bacterial cell membrane. The current findings showed the significant damaging effect of 6-gingerol on cell membrane viability in both <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. Further, the docking study suggested that 6-gingerol exhibited mild binding affinity to MexB efflux protein in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Li and Nikaido, 2004</xref>) in compliance with the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> findings, as 6-gingerol significantly diminished <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> efflux. Notably, 6-gingerol did not influence the production of β-lactamases.</p><p id="p0245">Mitigating bacterial virulence without affecting bacterial growth may reduce the selective pressure that leads to the development of resistance (<xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">Rutherford and Bassler, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Askoura et al., 2021</xref>). This approach can potentially help minimize the risk of bacteria evolving resistance mechanisms (<xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Rasmussen and Givskov, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Khayat et al., 2022</xref>). Considering the pivotal role of QS in regulating the production of virulence factors in both Gram-positive and -negative bacteria, targeting QS mechanisms holds the promise of reducing bacterial virulence effectively (<xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">Thabit et al., 2022</xref>, <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Khayat et al., 2023</xref>). Quorum sensing (QS) systems operate through an inducer-receptor mechanism (<xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Parsek et al., 1999</xref>). Due to its structural resemblance to QS signal molecules such as N-oxododecanoyl-l-homoserine lactone (OdDHL) and N-butyryl-l-homoserine lactone (BHL), 6-gingerol is capable of competing with these QS signal molecules for binding to their specific receptors. This enables 6-gingerol to effectively reduce bacterial virulence (<xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Ham et al., 2021</xref>). Further, the synthesized 6-gingerol and its derivatives, including those found naturally in ginger root, showed considerable ability to bind to the LasR QS receptor, and the abundant Lux-type QS in Gram-negative bacteria (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2017</xref>). Numerous studies have reported the anti-quorum sensing (QS) activities of 6-gingerol, which have been shown to significantly reduce the virulence of QS-controlled bacteria. These activities are achieved by impacting bacterial motility and biofilm formation, as well as the production of virulence enzymes, pigments, and other factors (<xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0250"><italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is an opportunistic Gram-negative bacterium known for its extensive repertoire of virulence factors (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Bottomley et al., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Filloux, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">El-Mowafy et al., 2014</xref>). These virulence factors are regulated mainly in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> through sensing the autoinducers by Lux-type QS receptors LasR and RhLR, and QscR which responds to the LasI autoinducers, besides PqsR (<xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Nalca et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">Venturi, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">Lintz et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">Thabit et al., 2022</xref>). In the current study, the anti-QS activities of 6-gingerol have been assessed through a detailed docking study into several QS targets in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. The docking study found 6-gingerol exhibiting promising binding affinity to various targets associated with the four <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> QS receptors. It demonstrated competitive binding compared to co-crystalized reference compounds in most cases. The formation of key interactions, including hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic interactions, further supported the potential anti-QS activity of 6-gingerol. Molecular dynamic studies revealed dynamic interactions in the 6-gingerol-QscR complex, with both compounds exhibiting fluctuations and stable binding to the protein. The interaction patterns observed in the 6-gingerol-QscR complex differed somewhat from those in the reference-QscR complex. These findings contribute to our understanding of 6-gingerol’s potential as an anti-virulence agent when it binds to QscR<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Interestingly, 6-gingerol decreased the expression of the QS-encoding genes in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> which supports the <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> findings.</p><p id="p0255">Confirming the results of virtual studies and the downregulating effect of 6-gingerol on the QS genes, 6-gingerol demonstrated a significant diminishing effect on the production of QS-controlled virulence factors. To exclude any effect of 6-gingerol on bacterial growth, the anti-virulence activities were assessed at sub-MIC concentrations. Impressively, 6-gingerol significantly diminished the biofilm formation in all the tested bacterial stains, and bacterial motility. Further, 6-gingerol reduced the production of essential virulence factors such as protease, hemolysins, and pyocyanin in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and satphyloxanthin in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. These <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> results were emphasized by <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> investigation which addressed the significant decrease in the <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> capacities to induce pathogenesis in mice when treated with 6-gingerol at sub-MICs, conferring protection to injected mice. Further, 6-gingerol synergistically decreased the MICs of the antibiotics tested against <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. Considering the above results, 6-gingerol is a promising anti-virulence and anti-QS candidate that could serve as an adjuvant to antibiotics in the treatment of aggressive Gram-negative and -positive infections.</p></sec><sec id="s0200"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0260">In a nutshell, 6-gingerol is one of the prominent active constituents of ginger family that acquires considerable antibacterial potency against Gram-negative and -positive bacteria mainly due to its ability to disrupt bacterial cell membranes, besides its effect on hindering the efflux pumps. 6-Gingerol significantly disrupted the <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> cell membranes and reduced their efflux. Moreover, it did not show any significant effect on the production of β-lactamases. Importantly, 6-gingerol’s anti-QS activities were more significant and in much lower concentrations (sub-MIC). It significantly diminished the <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> biofilm formation and decreased the production of virulence factors. These anti-virulence activities could be due to the interference of 6-gingerol with QS systems, as it downregulated the QS-encoding genes. Furthermore, the virtual docking and molecular dynamics studies revealed the potential affinity of 6-gingerol to bind and hinder QS receptors. These findings highlight 6-gingerol’s role as a potential anti-virulence agent to be used in combination with traditional antibiotics in the treatment of serious Gram-positive and -negative infections.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0205"><label>6</label><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0265">Data will be made available on request.</p></sec><sec id="s0210"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="p0270">The current study was performed as per the Helsinki Declaration, and all animal procedures used were approved by Zagazig University's Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (ZU-IACUC), Egypt, vide approval number (ZU-IACUC/3/F/264/2023).</p></sec><sec id="s0215"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0275">The Deanship of Scientific Research (DSR) at King Abdulaziz University (KAU), Jeddah, Saudi Arabia has funded this project, under grant no. (RG-41-166-43).</p></sec><sec id="s0225"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0285"><bold>Mahmoud A. Elfaky:</bold> Investigation, Methodology. <bold>Hassan M. Okairy:</bold> Investigation, Methodology. <bold>Hossam M. Abdallah:</bold> Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Writing – original draft. <bold>Abdulrahman E. Koshak:</bold> Investigation, Methodology. <bold>Gamal A. Mohamed:</bold> Supervision, Validation, Writing – original draft. <bold>Sabrin R.M. Ibrahim:</bold> Supervision, Validation, Writing – original draft. <bold>Abdulrahim A. Alzain:</bold> Methodology, Validation, Writing – original draft. <bold>Wael A.H. Hegazy:</bold> Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Writing – original draft. <bold>El-Sayed Khafagy:</bold> Investigation, Methodology. <bold>Noura M. Seleem:</bold> Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0290">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Halawany</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darwish</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bio-guided isolation of SARS-CoV-2 main protease inhibitors from medicinal plants: in vitro assay and molecular dynamics</article-title><source>Plants</source><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1914</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35893619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/plants11151914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9332707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdou</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Dine</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Tanbouly</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimization for ultrasonic-assisted Extraction of <italic toggle="yes">Aframomum melegueta</italic> phenolics using response surface methodology</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Chem.</source><volume>64</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>3153</fpage><lpage>3160</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abu Lila</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alharby</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alanazi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical resistant strains of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococci</italic> and their correlation to reduced susceptibility to biocides: phenotypic and genotypic analysis of macrolides, lincosamides, and streptogramins</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><volume>12</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>461</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36978327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics12030461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10044631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abo-Dya</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Benzotriazole-mediated synthesis and antibacterial activity of novel N-acylcephalexins</article-title><source>Sci. Pharm.</source><volume>84</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/scipharm84030484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28117314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5064239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alandiyjany</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelaziz</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelfattah-Hassan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel in vivo assessment of antimicrobial efficacy of ciprofloxacin loaded mesoporous silica nanoparticles against <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella typhimurium</italic> infection</article-title><source>Pharmaceuticals</source><volume>15</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>357</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35337154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ph15030357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8953957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldawsari</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khafagy</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saqr</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tackling virulence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa by the natural furanone sotolon</article-title><source>Antibiotics (Basel)</source><volume>10</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics10070871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8300740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34356792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almalki</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhady</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repurposing α-adrenoreceptor blockers as promising anti-virulence agents in gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35203781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics11020178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8868568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almalki</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhady</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computational and biological evaluation of β-adrenoreceptor blockers as promising bacterial anti-virulence agents</article-title><source>Pharmaceuticals</source><volume>15</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>110</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35215223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ph15020110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8877484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almalki</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taher</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, antimicrobial, anti-virulence and anticancer evaluation of new 5(4H)-oxazolone-based sulfonamides</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>27</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>671</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35163939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules27030671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8838850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Askoura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almalki</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lila</surname><given-names>A.S.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alteration of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> virulence and host pathogenesis through Targeting sdiA by using the CRISPR-Cas9 system</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><volume>9</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>2564</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34946165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/microorganisms9122564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8707642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Askoura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Sadoun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elevated levels of IL-33, IL-17 and IL-25 indicate the progression from chronicity to Hepatocellular Carcinoma in hepatitis C virus patients</article-title><source>Pathogens</source><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>57</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35056005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/pathogens11010057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8781674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beristain-Bauza</surname><given-names>S.D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández-Carranza</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cid-Pérez</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of ginger (Zingiber officinale) and its application in food products</article-title><source>Food Rev. Int.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaskar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>[6]-gingerol exhibits potent anti-mycobacterial and immunomodulatory activity against tuberculosis</article-title><source>Int. Immunopharmacol.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">106809</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2020.106809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32693356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylay</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25435309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bottomley</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muraglia</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazzo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular insights into quorum sensing in the human pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa from the structure of the virulence regulator LasR bound to its autoinducer</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>282</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>13592</fpage><lpage>13600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M700556200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17363368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carattoli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasmids and the spread of resistance</article-title><source>Int. J. Med. Microbiol.</source><volume>303</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmm.2013.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23499304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbaramawi</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eissa</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the anti-biofilm and anti-quorum sensing activities of the β-adrenoreceptor antagonist atenolol against gram-negative bacterial pathogens</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><volume>23</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>13088</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36361877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms232113088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9656717</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC13159964"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>S.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure–activity relationships of 6-and 8-gingerol analogs as anti-biofilm agents</article-title><source>J. Med. Chem.</source><volume>60</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>9821</fpage><lpage>9837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29135250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.7b01426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Horizontal gene transfer contributes to virulence and antibiotic resistance of Vibrio harveyi 345 based on complete genome sequence analysis</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>20</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>761</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-6137-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31640552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6805501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dugasani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pichika</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadarajah</surname><given-names>V.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of [6]-gingerol,[8]-gingerol,[10]-gingerol and [6]-shogaol</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>127</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jep.2009.10.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elfaky</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thabit</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eljaaly</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Controlling of bacterial virulence: evaluation of anti-virulence activities of prazosin against Salmonella enterica</article-title><source>Antibiotics (Basel)</source><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11111585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9686722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36358239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elfaky</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbaramawi</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eissa</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drug repositioning: doxazosin attenuates the virulence factors and biofilm formation in gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>107</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>3763</fpage><lpage>3778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37079062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00253-023-12522-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Mowafy</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaaban</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El Galil</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sodium ascorbate as a quorum sensing inhibitor of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source><volume>117</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1388</fpage><lpage>1399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.12631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25175797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Filloux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein secretion systems in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: an essay on diversity, evolution, and function</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>155</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2011.00155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21811488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3140646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foletto</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Rosa</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serafin</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repositioning of non-antibiotic drugs as an alternative to microbial resistance: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents.</source><volume>58</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">106380</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2021.106380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34166776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of some medicinal plant extracts</article-title><source>J. Nat. Med.</source><volume>62</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18404337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11418-007-0216-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girhepunje</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumore</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taksande</surname><given-names>S.U.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gingerol: a review</article-title><source>Ind. J. Med. Res. Pharm. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girlich</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnin</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dortet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetics of acquired antibiotic resistance genes in Proteus spp</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>256</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32153540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7046756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>S.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of membrane biofouling by 6-gingerol analogs: quorum sensing inhibition</article-title><source>Fuel</source><volume>250</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>S.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combined treatment of 6-gingerol analog and tobramycin for inhibiting <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> infections</article-title><source>Microbiol. Spectrum.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>e00192</fpage><lpage>00121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/Spectrum.00192-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8549756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34704784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegazy</surname><given-names>W.A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the role of SsaV ‘<italic toggle="yes">salmonella</italic> pathogenicity island-2 dependent type III secretion system components on the virulence behavior of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> enterica serovar <italic toggle="yes">typhimurium</italic></article-title><source>Afr. J. Biotechnol.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJB2016.15852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegazy</surname><given-names>W.A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alotaibi</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terazosin interferes with quorum sensing and type three secretion system and diminishes the bacterial espionage to mitigate the <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella typhimurium</italic> pathogenesis</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>465</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35453216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics11040465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9025009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoiby</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjarnsholt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Givskov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance of bacterial biofilms</article-title><source>Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</source><volume>35</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2009.12.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20149602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilic</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulev</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of grains of paradise (Aframomum melegueta schum) extract</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food. Chem.</source><volume>62</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>10452</fpage><lpage>10457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25293633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/jf5026086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4212708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing inhibitors: a patent review</article-title><source>Expert Opin. Ther. Pat.</source><volume>23</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/13543776.2013.779674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23506025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juhas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberl</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tummler</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing: the power of cooperation in the world of Pseudomonas</article-title><source>Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00769.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15816912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khayat</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-quorum sensing activities of gliptins against <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><volume>10</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1169</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35625906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines10051169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9138634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khayat</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbaramawi</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazeih</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diminishing the pathogenesis of the food-borne pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Serratia marcescens</italic> by low doses of sodium citrate</article-title><source>Biology</source><volume>12</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>504</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37106705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biology12040504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10135860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khayyat</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>M.F.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Not only antimicrobial: metronidazole mitigates the virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic> isolated from macerated diabetic foot ulcer</article-title><source>Appl. Sci.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>6847</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0200"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>6-gingerol reduces <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> biofilm formation and virulence via quorum sensing inhibition</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>8656</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25728862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep08656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4345325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0205"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chhibber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Zingerone silences quorum sensing and attenuates virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><volume>102</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2015.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25704369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.-G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiofilm and antivirulence activities of 6-gingerol and 6-shogaol against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> due to hyphal inhibition</article-title><source>Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>299</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30211127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fcimb.2018.00299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6121036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikaido</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efflux-mediated drug resistance in bacteria</article-title><source>Drugs</source><volume>64</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003495-200464020-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14717618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0220"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing and bacterial social interactions in biofilms</article-title><source>Sensors (Basel)</source><volume>12</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2519</fpage><lpage>2538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s120302519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22736963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3376616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lila</surname><given-names>A.S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajab</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biofilm lifestyle in recurrent Urinary Tract infections</article-title><source>Life</source><volume>13</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>148</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36676100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/life13010148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9865985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0230"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintz</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oinuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wysoczynski</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of QscR, a Pseudomonas aeruginosa quorum sensing signal receptor</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>108</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>15763</fpage><lpage>15768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1112398108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21911405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3179110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0235"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An enantioselective synthesis of (+)-(S)-[n]-gingerols via the l-proline-catalyzed aldol reaction</article-title><source>Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>3909</fpage><lpage>3911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19362472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bmcl.2009.03.081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0240"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuzaki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hisamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant properties of gingerol related compounds from ginger</article-title><source>Biofactors</source><volume>21</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15630214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/biof.552210157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0245"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattio</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallavalle</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of resveratrol-derived monomers and dimers against foodborne pathogens</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>19525</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31862939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-019-55975-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6925292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0250"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd Yusof</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gingerol and its role in chronic diseases</article-title><source>Drug Discov. Mother Nat.</source><year>2016</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-3-319-41342-6_8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27771925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0255"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nalca</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bredenbruch</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quorum-sensing antagonistic activities of azithromycin in Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1: a global approach</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1680</fpage><lpage>1688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.50.5.1680-1688.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16641435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1472232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0260"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of plant extracts and phytochemicals on antibiotic-resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbiol.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>256</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0265"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Papenfort</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing signal-response systems in gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2016.89</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27510864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5056591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0270"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of [10]-gingerol and [12]-gingerol isolated from ginger rhizome against periodontal bacteria</article-title><source>Phytotherapy Research: an International Journal Devoted to Pharmacological and Toxicological Evaluation of Natural Product Derivatives.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1446</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ptr.2473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18814211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0275"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The rise of gingerol as anti-QS molecule: darkest episode in the LuxR-mediated bioluminescence saga</article-title><source>Bioorg. Chem.</source><volume>99</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103823</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bioorg.2020.103823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32283347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0280"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsek</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Val</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanzelka</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acyl homoserine-lactone quorum-sensing signal generation</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S a.</source><volume>96</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>4360</fpage><lpage>4365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.8.4360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10200267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC16337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0285"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mobile genetic elements associated with antimicrobial resistance</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00088-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6148190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30068738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0290"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Givskov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum-sensing inhibitors as anti-pathogenic drugs</article-title><source>Int. J. Med. Microbiol.</source><volume>296</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmm.2006.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16503194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0295"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reens</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C.-C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A cell-based infection assay identifies efflux pump modulators that reduce bacterial intracellular load</article-title><source>PLoS Path.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>e1007115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6007937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29879224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0300"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Remy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mion</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plener</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interference in bacterial quorum sensing: a Biopharmaceutical perspective</article-title><source>Front. Pharmacol.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.00203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29563876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5845960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0305"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial quorum sensing: its role in virulence and possibilities for its control</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a012427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3543102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23125205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0310"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saqr</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldawsari</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khafagy</surname><given-names>E.-S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel use of allopurinol as a quorum-sensing inhibitor in Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><volume>10</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1385</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34827323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics10111385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8615079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0315"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breaking bad: better call gingerol for improving antibiotic susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> by inhibiting multiple quorum sensing pathways</article-title><source>Microbiol. Res.</source><volume>252</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">126863</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.micres.2021.126863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34530246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0320"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fungicidal action of geraniol against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> is potentiated by abrogated CaCdr1p drug efflux and fluconazole synergism</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>13</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>e0203079</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30157240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0203079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6114893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0325"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Echeverz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biofilm dispersion and quorum sensing</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2014.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24657330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0330"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synergistic activity of magnolol with azoles and its possible antifungal mechanism against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source><volume>118</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>826</fpage><lpage>838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.12737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25641229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0335"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro activities of retigeric acid B alone and in combination with azole antifungal agents against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source><volume>53</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aac.00940-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2663064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0340"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tacconelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrara</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savoldi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Discovery, research, and development of new antibiotics: the WHO priority list of antibiotic-resistant bacteria and tuberculosis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29276051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30753-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0345"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teles</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><part-title>Ginger (Zingiber officinale) antimicrobial potential: a review</part-title><source>Ginger Cultivation and Its Antimicrobial and Pharmacological Potentials</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0350"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thabit</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eljaaly</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zawawi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Muting bacterial communication: evaluation of prazosin anti-quorum sensing activities against gram-negative bacteria <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Proteus mirabilis,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Serratia marcescens</italic></article-title><source>Biology (basel).</source><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology11091349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9495718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36138828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0355"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venturi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of quorum sensing in Pseudomonas</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source><volume>30</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2005.00012.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16472307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0360"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yahyazadeh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baradaran Rahimi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yahyazadeh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Promising effects of gingerol against toxins: a review article</article-title><source>Biofactors</source><volume>47</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34418196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/biof.1779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0365"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y.-X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.-S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Actinomycin D: a novel Pseudomonas aeruginosa quorum sensing inhibitor from the endophyte Streptomyces cyaneochromogenes RC1</article-title><source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>170</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35904625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11274-022-03360-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0235" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0305">The following are the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary data 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ak005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0295">The Deanship of Scientific Research (DSR) at King Abdulaziz University (KAU), Jeddah, Saudi Arabia has funded this project, under grant no. (RG-41-166-43). The authors, therefore, gratefully acknowledge DSR’s technical and financial support.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="s0230" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0300">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsps.2024.102041" id="ir005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsps.2024.102041</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>