<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1257</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jmm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jmm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Medical Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-2615</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1473-5644</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Microbiology Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11920071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11920071.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11920071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11920071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40100248</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.001980</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">001980</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Antimicrobial Resistance</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Antimicrobial Resistance</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Antimicrobials</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Biofilms</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Hospital Infection</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Mrsa</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fractional inhibitory concentration of bio-actives from agricultural waste disassembles biofilms and quenches virulence of nosocomial pathogens</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names initials="S">Srividhya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>srividhya172@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatachalam</surname><given-names initials="P">Ponnusami</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>vponnu@chem.sastra.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanmugam</surname><given-names initials="SR">Saravanan Ramiah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref rid="pa1" ref-type="author-notes">†</xref><email>saravanan.ramiahshanmugam@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paramasivam</surname><given-names initials="N">Nithyanand</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><email>pnithyanand@gmail.com</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Biofilm Biology Laboratory</institution>, <institution>School of Chemical and Biotechnology, SASTRA Deemed University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Thanjavur, TN, 613401</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Biomass, Bioenergy and Bioproducts Laboratory</institution>, <institution>School of Chemical and Biotechnology, SASTRA Deemed University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Thanjavur, TN, 613401</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Centre for Bioenergy, School of Chemical and Biotechnology, SASTRA Deemed University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Thanjavur, TN, 613401</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>†</label><p>Department of Biosystems Engineering, Auburn University, Auburn, Alabama, 36849, USA</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Saravanan RamiahShanmugam, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="saravanan.ramiahshanmugam@gmail.com">saravanan.ramiahshanmugam@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">NithyanandParamasivam, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pnithyanand@gmail.com">pnithyanand@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Supplementary material:</bold> Two supplementary figures and two supplementary tables are available with the online version of this article.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>74</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">484019</issue-id><elocation-id>001980</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-20 00:25:16.910"><day>20</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="jmm-74-3-01980.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><title>Graphical abstract</title></abstract><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><bold>Introduction.</bold> The contact surfaces in hospitals serve as reservoirs for pathogens and account for 20–40% of hospital-acquired infections. This resistance is mainly attributed to the biofilm-forming ability of the microbes. These biofilms restrict the entry of the antibiotics to penetrate them, thus giving rise to drug resistance. Hence, there is a renewed interest in formulating an environmentally friendly, non-allergic, quick mode of action, broad-spectrum disinfectant.</p><p><bold>Hypothesis.</bold> We hypothesize that the pure compounds present in the pyrolysis aqueous phase could act as an anti-infective and anti-biofilm agent.</p><p><bold>Aim.</bold> The present work investigates the effectiveness of furfuryl alcohol, 2-methyl-2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol as effective anti-infective agent followed by testing its biofilm eradication potential against the mixed species of multidrug-resistant pathogens such as <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Candida auris</italic>.</p><p><bold>Methodology.</bold> The MIC and fractional inhibitory concentrations (FIC) of the pure compounds were determined using checkerboard assay for two-compound and three-compound combinations. The biofilm eradication concentration was performed on stainless coupons, followed by RNA isolation and quantitative PCR (qPCR) analysis to elucidate virulence gene downregulation.</p><p><bold>Results.</bold> The individual MICs of furfuryl alcohol, 2-methyl-2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol were found to be 8%, 9% and 2% (v/v), respectively. The two-compound combination FIC index of 0.75 showed partial synergy between the compounds, while the three-compound combination showed an additive effect with a FIC index of 0.87. Further, at ½ FIC (biofilm inhibitory concentration), the compounds showed 52% eradication of preformed biofilms on the hospital contact surfaces (stainless steel). The growth and time-to-kill curve showed that the compounds were not lethal to planktonic cells at BIC. Finally, the qPCR analysis showed a reduction in the expression levels of biofilm and adhesion genes, while the Quorum sensing (QS) genes were affected much more, elucidating a possible eradication mechanism.</p><p><bold>Conclusion.</bold> From this study, we have found a new class of compounds that have potential disinfecting ability. With the current knowledge, the future lead would be to effectively use them in disinfectant formulations.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>biofilms</kwd><kwd>checkerboard assay</kwd><kwd>disinfectant</kwd><kwd>fractional inhibitory concentration</kwd><kwd>hospital-acquired infections</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>DST-SERB</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>CRG/2022/003211</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paramasivam</surname><given-names>Nithyanand</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The ever-rising issue of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) has become a global menace, second only to cancer. Several classes of microbial pathogens now exhibit resistance against the antibiotics that were previously used to fight the infections caused by them. The urge for a new class of antimicrobial agents is the need of the hour. Globally, ~4.95 million deaths have been reported due to AMR in the year 2019. In addition to the deaths, it has an impact on the economy of healthcare sectors, and it is projected that by the year 2030, it will result in an annual Gross domestic product (GDP) loss of around U.S. $304 trillion (WHO, 21 November 2023) [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The increase in the usage of antibiotics during the recent Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic has also given rise to AMR. The mortality rates due to secondary infections were higher post-COVID-19. Infections caused by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) are high in hospital settings due to their resistance towards an extended class of antibiotics [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It was also reported by the Center for Disease Control and Prevention that the co-infection of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and MRSA was ~46% in 2020. Apart from bacterial resistance, the World Health Organization (WHO) has also reported <italic toggle="yes">Candida auris</italic> as a critical invasive fungal infection, which urgently requires new antifungal agents for treatment [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The most frequent transmission of hospital-acquired infections (HAIs) is through contact or touch surfaces, accounting for ~20–40% of the total HAI rates. It is reported that <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> can survive up to 44 °C for 20 days on surfaces and can only be inactivated by moist heat at 70 °C applied for a duration of 30 min [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. MRSA can sustain for more than 6 weeks on stainless steel surfaces and can only be inactivated by dry heating at 160–170 °C for a period of 1 h [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> infections are the fourth leading nosocomial infections wherein they survive at wide temperature ranges (0–60 °C) and can tolerate a wide pH range of 2.0–8.5. These abilities to withstand extreme temperature ranges, pH tolerance and surface persistence make them more resistant to a wide spectrum of antibiotics. All these attributes are mainly due to their ability to form biofilms. Biofilms are matrices that are produced by the cells to encase themselves. Due to the formation of these surface biofilms, they resist many antimicrobial agents during disinfection measures [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The disinfection of these surfaces is predominantly performed with ethanol, sodium hypochlorite, UV irradiation, quaternary ammonium salts and some surface cleaning techniques like plasma sterilization. During the pandemic, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has listed 545 products (nitrogen-containing groups – list N) that contain quaternary ammonium salts (QASs), alcohols and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> as active ingredients [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Discharge of the chlorine-based chemicals has posed an environmental risk to aquatic ecosystems and sewage systems, while the QASs show adverse effects on respiratory systems and reproductive health [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Due to the above-mentioned issues with existing chemical disinfectants, there is a renewed interest in the development of environmentally friendly, non-allergic, quick mode of action, broad-spectrum disinfectants [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Pyrolysis is a thermochemical process that breaks down the lignocellulosic biomass into solid (bio-char), liquid (bio-oil aqueous phase) and gas (syngas) fractions [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The oil layer of the liquid fraction is used for the fuel applications following catalytic hydrotreatment [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], whereas the aqueous layer is generally regarded as waste and requires further treatment owing to the high chemical oxygen demand and biological oxygen demand before discharging it into the water bodies. The aqueous phase contains oxygenated compounds, aromatics, with various functional moieties along with nitrogen and phosphorus. Hence, direct discharge of the aqueous phase in the water bodies causes eutrophication [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>In our previous work [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], we have reported that the aqueous phase obtained from the pyrolysis of wheat straw residue had an excellent biofilm eradication property against the pre-formed MRSA biofilms on stainless steel (SS) and polypropylene surfaces which are widely used materials in hospital settings. However, there is a lack of understanding on the inhibitory nature of the major compounds identified from the aqueous phase, i.e. does the inhibition against multidrug-resistant pathogens arise from the individual effect or synergistic effect of these compounds? We envision that addressing this research question would enable us to formulate a disinfectant from agricultural biomass. So, the present work aims to test the individual and combined activity of these pure compounds against mixed-species biofilms of multidrug-resistant pathogens such as <italic toggle="yes"> A. baumannii</italic>, MRSA and <italic toggle="yes">C. auris</italic>. We have selected the three compounds, namely furfuryl alcohol, 2-methyl-2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol, based on their higher relative abundance from the GC-MS analysis of the aqueous phase. Fractional inhibitory concentration (FIC), biofilm eradication and downregulation of biofilm and adhesion genes on hospital contact surface (SS coupons) were evaluated to gain a complete understanding of their eradication mechanism.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Procurements of chemicals</title><p>The pure compounds of furfuryl alcohol, 3-methyl-2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (purity 99.0%). Guaiacol was dissolved in 50% ethanol to a stock concentration of 40% (v/v) and then diluted using 1X PBS, while the other two compounds were dissolved using water. Soybean casein digest (SCD) broth, yeast peptone broth (YPD) and Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) were purchased from HiMedia, India.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Microbial strains and culture conditions</title><p>Clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (AB2) (GenBank accession no. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF443128">MF443128</ext-link>), MRSA (GSA-44) and <italic toggle="yes">C. auris</italic> (GenBank accession ID <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MK108049">MK108049</ext-link>) strains were used in the study. MRSA and <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were cultured in SCD and <italic toggle="yes">C. auris</italic> was cultured in a YPD medium. All three cells were adjusted to a cell density of 10<sup>7</sup> c.f.u. ml<sup>−1</sup> separately, and then 16.6 µl from each cell suspension were added, so that the total volume of cells is 50 µl wherein the final cell density was 3×10<sup>7</sup> c.f.u. ml<sup>−1</sup>. For the co-culturing of bacterial and fungal cells, RPMI medium is used.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Determination of MIC</title><p>The minimum concentration required to inhibit the growth of the test strains was tested using the MIC assay [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Briefly, in a 96-well plate, 100 µl RPMI media, 50 µl of cells and 50 µl of compound on varying dilutions were added and kept for incubation at 37 °C for 24 h. Following incubation, 30 µl of MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide) dye was added and incubated in the dark for 30 min. The results were visualized and recorded.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Determination of FIC of test compounds in two-compound combinations</title><p>A checkerboard assay was performed to check the synergistic activity of the three test compounds in three different combinations. Combination 1 comprised furfuryl alcohol and 3-methyl-2-cyclopentenone, combination 2 comprised 3-methyl-2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol and combination 3 comprised guaiacol and furfuryl alcohol. The compounds were prepared in the range of eight times their respective MIC [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. To a 96-well plate, 100 µl of RPMI media, 50 µl of cells and 50 µl of varying concentrations of the compounds were added according to the above-mentioned combinations. The plates were incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. After incubation, the plates were screened for their fractional inhibitory concentrations by adding 30 µl concentration MTT. Equation 1 gives the FIC index of two compound combinations.</p><p>
<disp-formula>
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" alttext="\mathrm{F}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }\left (\mathrm{o}\mathrm{f}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{t}\mathrm{w}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{c}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{p}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{u}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{d}\mathrm{s}\right)=\frac{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\left (1\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{c}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{b}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\right)}{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }1}+\frac{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\left (2\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{c}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{b}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\right)}{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }2}" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Determination of FIC of test compounds in three-compound combinations</title><p>To determine the FIC of three compounds in combination, the FIC of two combinations is fixed as MIC, and the third compound is varied accordingly [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As mentioned above, 100 µl of RPMI media and 50 µl of cells were added to a 96-well plate. Fifty microlitres of varying concentrations of compounds were added and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. Following the incubation, 30 µl concentration MTT was added and visualized. Equation 2 was used to calculate the FIC index of the three-compound combination.</p><p>
<disp-formula>
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M2" alttext="\mathrm{F}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }\left (\mathrm{o}\mathrm{f}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{t}\mathrm{h}\mathrm{r}\mathrm{e}\mathrm{e}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{c}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{p}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{u}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{d}\mathrm{s}\mathrm{\ }\right)=\frac{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }\left (\left (1,2\right)\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{c}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{b}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\right)}{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }\left (1,2\right)\mathrm{a}\mathrm{l}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{e}}+\frac{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }\left (3\ \mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{c}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{b}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\right)}{\mathrm{M}\mathrm{I}\mathrm{C}\mathrm{\ }\left (3\right)\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{a}\mathrm{l}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{e}}" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p><p>FIC&lt;0.5 is synergy, 0.5&lt;FIC≤0.75 is partially synergy, 0.75&lt;FIC≤1 is additive, FIC&gt;1 is indifferent and FIC&gt;4 is antagonistic.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Determination of biofilm eradication ability at its FIC</title><p>To check for the matured biofilm disrupting ability of the three compounds in combination, a biofilm eradication assay was performed. In a 24-well plate, 1 ml of media with 100 µl cells was incubated for 24 h at 37 °C under static conditions [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. After 24 h, the spent media was removed, and the fresh media was supplemented along with 50 µl of the three compounds at their 1/2<sup>nd</sup>, 1/4<sup>th</sup> and 1/8<sup>th</sup> of FIC and incubated for another 24 h. Following incubation, the spent media was removed, and the biofilms were stained with 0.4% crystal violet (CV). Excess stain was washed with water, wells were solubilized with 70% ethanol and the absorbance was recorded using an ELISA plate reader (Tulip, Lisaquant, TS). The wells without compounds served as controls. The biofilm eradication was calculated using Equation 3.</p><p>
<disp-formula>
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M3" alttext="\mathrm{P}\mathrm{e}\mathrm{r}\mathrm{c}\mathrm{e}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{g}\mathrm{e}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{b}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{f}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{l}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{e}\mathrm{r}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{d}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{c}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{i}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{\ }\left (\mathrm{\% }\right)=\frac{\mathrm{C}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{r}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{l}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{O}\mathrm{D}-\mathrm{S}\mathrm{a}\mathrm{m}\mathrm{p}\mathrm{l}\mathrm{e}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{O}\mathrm{D}}{\mathrm{C}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{n}\mathrm{t}\mathrm{r}\mathrm{o}\mathrm{l}\mathrm{\ }\mathrm{O}\mathrm{D}}\mathrm{*}100" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">*</mml:mi><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Determination of planktonic cell growth by growth curve analysis</title><p>To check if the compounds inhibit cell growth, a growth curve assay was performed. Briefly, 1% (v/v) of the overnight cultures was inoculated into RPMI media. The compounds at concentrations of 1/2 BIC and FIC were added and incubated at 37 °C at 150 r.p.m. The tubes with only cells served as controls. The cell absorbance was recorded for every 2 h at 600 nm [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Determination of viable cell count by time-kill analysis</title><p>To support that the planktonic cells are alive, a time-kill assay was performed. The mixed cell suspensions without treatment, FIC treated and BIC treated were prepared. The samples were collected at 2-h time intervals, serially diluted and spread plated in the SCD and YPD agar plates and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. The countable colonies were recorded, and log c.f.u. was calculated accordingly [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>Visualization of biofilm eradication through light microscopy</title><p>The Minimum Biofilm Eradication concentration (MBEC) assay was performed on a 1×1 cm glass slide. The slides were stained using 0.4% CV and air dried. The CV binds to the Exopolysaccharide (EPS) produced by the biofilms. The control and treated slides were then visualized under the light, and images were captured using Nikon Eclipse Ti 100, Japan digital camera.</p></sec><sec id="s2-10"><title>Visualization of the cell viability using live/dead staining</title><p>The viable but non-culturable cells were visualized using a live/dead staining using SYTO9 and Propidium Iodide (PI) dyes and observed under the fluorescence microscope (Model-Eclipse Ts2, Serial No. 245859) [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-11"><title>Effect of biofilm eradication on contact surface and molecular level downregulation using the qPCR analysis</title><p>To elucidate a mechanistic view of the action of these compounds, the major genes responsible for biofilm formation, quorum sensing and adhesion were studied through the quantitative PCR (qPCR) analysis. On the SS (Grade 316) coupons, the MBEC assay was performed on a 6-well plate. The coupons with only cells served as the control. RNA was isolated from scrapping the biofilms present in the SS coupons using 1X PBS as reported elsewhere [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. First, the biofilm cells were centrifuged followed by (1:1) phenol/chloroform extraction. To the obtained aqueous phase, lysis buffer was added, and the RNA was precipitated using isopropanol. The obtained pellet was washed with ice-cold 70% ethanol and centrifuged at 5000 r.p.m. for 5 min. The RNA pellet was air dried and suspended in 25 µl RNase-free water and stored at −80 °C. The RNA was converted to cDNA using the High-Capacity Reverse Transcription Kit 260 (Applied Biosystem™, USA). The gene expression of the virulence genes as listed in the Table SA4 was quantified using real-time StepOnePlus thermal cycler 262 (AB17500, Applied Biosystems™, USA) using SYBR green PCR mix.</p></sec><sec id="s2-12"><title>Visualization of biofilm eradication on SS surface through scanning electron micrographs</title><p>The biofilm eradication was performed on SS coupons, the Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) samples were prepared as per [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] by fixing with glutaraldehyde and dehydration with ethanol. The samples were gold sputtered and visualized (VEGA, TESCAN).</p></sec><sec id="s2-13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All the studies were carried out in triplicates. The results are expressed as mean±<sc>sd</sc>, and data were analysed using ANOVA. The significant difference between the control group and treated groups was indicated using asterisks (*) and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05. Graphs were plotted using GraphPad Prism version 5.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Individual compounds possess microbicidal activity against mixed microbial pathogens</title><p>The MIC determines the least concentration of the compound needed to kill the cells. The formation of the formazan product by the live cells is visualized by the purple colour. The MTT assay shows a MIC of 8%, 9% and 2% (v/v) for furfuryl alcohol, 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol, respectively, against the mixed microbial community of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, MRSA and <italic toggle="yes"> C. auris</italic> (Fig. SA1 and Table SA3, available in the online Supplementary Material).</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Evaluation of FIC of two compounds against mixed microbial pathogens</title><p>The two-compound combinations were assessed using the checkerboard assay. The use of two compounds in combination can possess an additive, synergistic or antagonistic effect depending on their mode of action. In our case, all the three combinations showed an FIC index of 0.75 inferring they are partially synergistic to each other (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a–c</xref>). The FIC of the combinations was calculated using Equation 1 and is tabulated in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>FICs of two compounds at three different combinations against mixed microbial strains</title><p>FIC 1 (furfuryl alcohol, 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone)=4/8 + 2.25/9=0.75 (partial synergy). FIC 2 (3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone, guaiacol)=4.5/9 + 0.5/2=0.75 (partial synergy). FIC 3 (guaiacol, furfuryl alcohol)=1/2 + 2/8=0.75 (partial synergy).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIC index</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Furfuryl alcohol, 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial synergetic</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3-Methyl,2-cyclopentenone, guaiacol</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial synergetic</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Guaiacol, furfuryl alcohol</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial synergetic</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>The FIC of two-compound combinations. (a) Furfuryl alcohol and 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone, (b) 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol and (c) guaiacol and furfuryl alcohol.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Evaluation of FIC of three compounds against mixed microbial pathogens</title><p>The FIC of all the three compounds was assessed by taking 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone and furfuryl alcohol together against guaiacol (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). The three-combination FIC was calculated using Equation 2. The combination showed an additive effect with a FIC index of 0.87 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>The FIC of three compounds where 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone and furfuryl alcohol were considered as single compounds and guaiacol being the second compound.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>FICs of three compounds against the mixed species</title><p>FIC (furfuryl alcohol + 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone) / guaiacol=2/8 + 1.12/9 + 1/2. FIC index (combined)=0.87.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound combination</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIC index (combined)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Furfuryl alcohol+3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone/guaiacol</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additive</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The additive effect was observed in the three compound FIC, indicating that all three compounds are responsible for the activity and it is not the individual or synergistic effect even though they are present as a mixture.</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>FIC concentration of compounds eradicated mixed species biofilms</title><p>The ability of the three compounds against the eradication of pre-formed biofilms was evaluated at its 1/2<sup>nd</sup>, 1/4<sup>th</sup> and 1/8<sup>th</sup> FIC concentrations. It was shown to eradicate 53% of the mixed species biofilms at 1/2<sup>nd</sup> FIC concentration (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). This concentration was considered as its biofilm inhibitory concentration (BIC) for further studies.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Biofilm eradication ability of the pure compounds at 1/2 FIC, 1/4 FIC and 1/8 FIC.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>BIC concentration was non-lethal against planktonic cells</title><p>The microbicidal activity of the FIC and BIC concentrations was assessed against mixed microbial strains. Cells without treatment served as control. It was observed that the FIC concentration showed a decline in the cell growth, indicating that it was lethal to the microbial cells. On the other hand, the BIC concentration did not show any lethal effect against the cells, as the cells treated with it showed a growth pattern similar to that of the control (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>(a) The growth pattern of mixed species in RPMI medium upon treatment at its BIC and FIC and control. Time-kill pattern on (b) SCD agar and (c) YPD agar showing log c.f.u. reduction at FIC, BIC and control is shown.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>A time-kill curve pattern was obtained by enumerating the colonies and calculating their c.f.u. per millilitre. The time-kill plot shows that the BIC was not lethal to the planktonic cells, while at FIC, the compounds exhibited killing effects. Since the mixed species contain <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, MRSA and <italic toggle="yes">C. auris</italic>, the samples were spotted on SCD agar and YPD agar plates to enumerate bacterial and fungal cells, respectively. The cells were reduced by 4.3 log c.f.u. ml<sup>−1</sup> (in SCD) and 6.3 log c.f.u. ml<sup>−1</sup> (in YPD) at its FIC (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b, c</xref>), whereas the BIC showed a similar growth pattern as the control, which further indicates that BIC does not kill the bacterial and fungal cells. From the growth curve and kill graph, we can correlate and infer that the control and BIC-treated cell absorbance were increasing in the growth curve (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref>) with an increase in log c.f.u. per millilitre from 2 h itself (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b, c</xref>). Meanwhile, there is reduced cell growth in the case of FIC treated with reducing log c.f.u. per millilitre.</p></sec><sec id="s3-6"><title>Biofilm eradication of mixed species visualized using light microscopy</title><p>MBEC assay performed with BIC concentration on glass slides were visualized after CV staining under a light microscope. CV binds to the EPS, and as a result, the intensity of CV aggregation was high in the control sample and lesser in the case of the BIC-treated sample, as shown in Figure SA2.</p></sec><sec id="s3-7"><title>Visualization of viable but non-culturable cells through fluorescence microscopy</title><p>Fluorescence microscopic images show us the metabolically inactive cells that are not culturable. The SYTO9 dye binds to the DNA of live cells and emits green fluorescence, while PI can only enter and bind to the DNA of cells with a compromised membrane, emitting red fluorescence, indicating the presence of dead cells. In the case of control, the cells were metabolically alive emitting green fluorescence, while in case of BIC treated, the cell morphology was changed, but the green intensity tells that the planktonic cells were still alive. The green fluorescent intensity of the BIC-treated sample was less than the control due to a reduction in biofilm cells (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). The treated samples did not show any red fluorescence indicating that the cells were not affected much.</p><fig position="float" id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Fluorescence microscopy image showing live and dead cells staining of mixed species. (a) Control slide and (b) BIC-treated slide showing green (SYTO9), red (PI) and merged fluorescence.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-8"><title>Mixed species biofilm eradication on an SS surface downregulates the virulence genes</title><p>The downregulation of virulence genes was observed in MRSA, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. auris</italic>. The genes used, along with their function and primer sequences, are listed in Tables SA4 and SA5. In the case of MRSA, the EPS adhesion genes (<italic toggle="yes">ica</italic>A, <italic toggle="yes">ica</italic>D) and staphyloxanthin genes (<italic toggle="yes">crt</italic>M and <italic toggle="yes">crt</italic>N) were downregulated to 0.36-fold, while the expression of fibronectin binding protein (<italic toggle="yes">fnb</italic>B) and autoinducer (<italic toggle="yes">ssp</italic>B) genes were decreased to 0.14- and 0.14-fold, respectively. The effect on <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic>AC, which modulates the Quorum sensing (QS) virulence, was greatly affected (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6a</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>The qPCR analysis of virulence gene expression of (a) MRSA, (b) <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and (c) <italic toggle="yes">C. auris</italic> in mixed species biofilms developed on control and treated SS surfaces.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>In <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, genes related to surface motility (<italic toggle="yes">aba</italic>I and <italic toggle="yes">aba</italic>R) were reduced to 0.34- and 0.55-fold, respectively. Downregulation in genes related to abiotic surface attachment (<italic toggle="yes">bfm</italic>R, <italic toggle="yes">bfm</italic>S) and initial attachment (<italic toggle="yes">csu</italic>A/B, <italic toggle="yes">csu</italic>E) was observed at the range of 0.25–0.29-fold. Genes responsible for the structural integrity of the biofilms (<italic toggle="yes">pga</italic>B) were downregulated by 0.19-fold, while the fibronectin binding gene (<italic toggle="yes">omp</italic>A) was downregulated to 0.10-fold as observed in MRSA (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6b</xref>). In the case of <italic toggle="yes">C. auris</italic>, fold reduction was observed in the <italic toggle="yes">erg</italic> gene which is responsible for azole resistance, while the other genes responsible for biofilm formation (<italic toggle="yes">efg</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">hgc</italic>) and efflux (<italic toggle="yes">cdr</italic>) were reduced to 0.18- and 0.15-folds, respectively (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-9"><title>Visualization of biofilm eradication on SS surfaces</title><p>From the SEM images, it can be clearly seen that the biofilms were disrupted by the compounds. The control and treated photographs show the clear difference between the matured biofilms in the control sample and dismantled biofilm architecture in the treated sample (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). A clear EPS reduction can be observed in the case of the BIC-treated SS coupons (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7c</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F7" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><title>Scanning electron microscopy images of mixed species (a) plain SS coupon, (b) control SS coupon and (c) BIC-treated SS coupon.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Healthcare facilities serve as a vector for the transmission of micro-organisms causing HAIs. Apart from infected patients, transmission takes place from frequently touched surfaces like door handles and switches, which are known as ‘high-touch surfaces’ [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Disinfection is the preliminary way of controlling any infection on inanimate objects. Currently, the majority of healthcare surface settings use neutral detergents, hypochlorite or ethanol as disinfecting agents as suggested by the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. One of the major reasons for these microbes to gain drug resistance is through their biofilm-forming ability. It was reported that ~65% of HAIs were caused by biofilm formation [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The technically important stages of the biofilm include the initial attachment, microcolony formation followed by maturation and finally dispersion. It is reported that the biofilms increase the resistance of conventional antibiotics by 1000-fold [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Various anti-biofilm molecules have been identified from natural sources, synthetic compounds and lantibiotics. The rise in demand for novel strategies is mainly focused on two approaches: (i) development of biofilm inhibitors or (ii) surface modification [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In clinical settings, the biofilms are polymicrobial. In view of that, the present study has been fully performed on mixed microbial species conditions. So, an effective anti-biofilm agent should be able to penetrate them to provide the necessary mode of action. The inter- and intra-kingdom interactions must be elucidated in order to provide a complete understanding of the mechanisms, as they promote the virulence and recalcitrance of biofilms [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Studies have shown the use of plant-based anti-biofilm agents like flavonoids, organic acids and phenolics to target MRSA. Santiago <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] showed a decrease in cell surface attachment of the biofilms when treated with extracts of the F-10 fraction of <italic toggle="yes">Duabanga grandiflora</italic> extract. The gallic and ellagic acids present in the extract of <italic toggle="yes">Cochlospermum regium</italic> inhibited the biofilm by decreasing the polysaccharide secretion in MRSA and Methicillin sensitive <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aures</italic> (MSSA) [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The alteration in biofilm structure and staphyloxanthin production was reported using Pulverulentone A, 8-desmethyl eucalyptin and eucalyptin isolated from methanol extracts of <italic toggle="yes">Callistemon citrinus</italic> [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Previous reports have shown that hexane and dichloromethane extracts of leaves of <italic toggle="yes">Allium stipitatum</italic> and major compounds of <italic toggle="yes">Syagrus coronata</italic> (octanoic acid, dodecanoic acid, decanoic acid and <italic toggle="yes">γ</italic>-eudesmol) cause disintegration of matured biofilms by penetrating deep inside the matrix [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Alibi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] showed biofilm inhibition against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> using <italic toggle="yes">Thymus vulgaris</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum verum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Eugenia caryophyllata</italic> of 88%, 97% and 91%, respectively. Methanolic extracts of <italic toggle="yes">Carum copticum</italic> showed disruption in biofilm structure reported to have thymol (40%), <italic toggle="yes">ϒ</italic>-terpinene (36%) and p-cymene (21%) as major compounds against six pathogens, namely <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus cereus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumonia</italic> [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The DCM extract of the bulbs of <italic toggle="yes">Allium stipitatum</italic> showed the reduction in biofilm viability and structure dismantling of MRSA and <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilms [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. All these methods have used the direct plant extracts obtained through solvent extraction processes, which are basically the secondary metabolites produced by the plants. But in our work, we have proposed a thermochemical conversion process known as pyrolysis as an effective way of utilizing the biomass. In this technique, the biomass is subjected to higher temperatures, which on degradation produce volatile matters that are condensed as an aqueous phase.</p><p>In our previous work [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], we showed that the wheat straw aqueous phase showed a potential anti-infective effect in disrupting the biofilms formed on SS. Through docking studies, we have also predicted the major compounds, namely furfuryl alcohol, 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol obtained through GC-MS analysis as responsible compounds for this activity. So, the present work focused on testing those individual compounds to elucidate whether these compounds possess synergistic or additive effects. In this study, the individual compounds tested showed MIC at 8%, 9% and 2% (v/v) for furfuryl alcohol, 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol, respectively, against the mixed species of pathogens. The two-compound combination an FIC showed a FIC index of 0.75, implying partial synergy between the compound combinations. Followed by the FIC of three-compound combinations showed an additive effect with an FIC index of 0.87, confirming that the anti-infective activity was due to the combinational effect and not due to a synergistic effect. Guaiacol, also known as methyl catechol, is the major product obtained from wood distillation. It has widely been used as an antiseptic and local anaesthetic. Studies have shown its antibacterial and antifungal activity. It was also shown to inhibit the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium graminearum</italic>. At 1.838 mM (2.05×10<sup>−4</sup>%), guaiacol has inhibited conidial production and germination by disrupting Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel with decreased levels of catalase, peroxidase and superoxide dismutase acting as an effective antioxidant [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Further, guaiacol oligomers synthesized by polymerization reaction showed excellent antioxidant and antimicrobial activity by reducing the bacterial load of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> [<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Chai <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> have reported furan compounds as novel tyrosinase inhibitors and antimicrobial agents with MIC of furfuryl alcohol to be 0.115 µM against <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus bacteria</italic>. A study by Goa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] has reported the by-product of pyrolysis of wheat straw condensates as an effective fungicide. They showed an antifungal activity against <italic toggle="yes">F. graminearum</italic> at a concentration of 3.1 µl ml<sup>−1</sup>, showing a higher potential than the synthetic fungicide. A study by Amin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] has reported cyclopentenone derivatives as an effective antifungal agent against <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus sydowii</italic>.</p><p>Since biofilms were one of the potential targets, we extended our study to find the biofilm eradication ability of these compounds. At 1/2<sup>nd</sup> FIC, they showed ~53% biofilm eradication against the mixed species and hence were chosen as BIC. The growth curve showed that there is no reduction in planktonic cell growth in control and BIC-treated samples, which is supported by the kill curve plots, which show an increase in log c.f.u. in control and BIC-treated samples. The non-culturable, viable cells were also visualized using live/dead fluorescence microscopy. The EPS reduction was also confirmed through SEM images.</p><p>The initial attachment stages are governed by the surface-associated proteins and biofilm-associated proteins (<italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">fnaA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">fnbB</italic>). Some species directly anchor to the matrix and mediate colonization. <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> can directly form larger aggregates (<italic toggle="yes">icaA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">icaD</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sspB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">csu</italic> and PNAG). To understand this mechanism, we tested it on the high-touch surfaces of hospitals such as SS surfaces. The eradication was performed on SS coupons. To understand the genetic level changes, the qPCR analysis was performed by extracting the RNA from the SS coupons. It can be understood from the downregulation pattern that the genes responsible for surface motility (<italic toggle="yes">aba</italic>I and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>) and EPS adhesion (<italic toggle="yes">ica</italic>) were significantly downregulated followed by the abiotic surface attachment (<italic toggle="yes">bfmR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bfmS</italic>) and biofilm formation genes (<italic toggle="yes">efg</italic>), while the QS genes (<italic toggle="yes">agrAC</italic>) and autoinducing peptide (<italic toggle="yes">ssp</italic>) were affected greatly. This array pattern unfolds the possible biofilm eradication mechanism.</p><p>The present study shows that it is the additive effect of the compounds (furfuryl alcohol, 3-methyl,2-cyclopentenone and guaiacol) present in the aqueous phase that is responsible for this anti-infective property and not the individual compound. The screened compounds show both anti-biofilm property at their BIC and anti-infective property at their FIC. The compounds were efficient in eradicating the pre-formed biofilms on high-contact SS surfaces. The qPCR analysis showed that this activity is due to the downregulation in biofilm genes, while the QS system was most affected.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The study highlights that an additive effect of the compounds present in the aqueous phase is only responsible for the observed property and it is not the effect of a single compound. To conclude, the leads from the present study would be to investigate the formulation aspects of the major compounds present in the aqueous phase as a disinfectant coating to be used on inanimate hospital materials and surfaces that act as reservoirs of multi-drug resistant (MDR) pathogens.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SF1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.001980</object-id><label>Uncited Fig. S1.</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jmm-74-01980-s001.pdf" id="d67e1469" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors Dr N.P., Dr S.S.R. and S.K. sincerely thank DST – SERB (CRG/2022/003211) for the financial support through the funded project grant. The authors gratefully acknowledge SASTRA Deemed University for research facility support. S.K. sincerely thanks CSIR for her Senior Research Fellowship (SRF), 141-74-3072/2K23/1.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>AMR</term><def><p>antimicrobial resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BIC</term><def><p>biofilm inhibitory concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CV</term><def><p>crystal violet</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EPS</term><def><p>exopolysaccharide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FIC</term><def><p>fractional inhibitory concentrations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GDP</term><def><p>gross domestic product</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HAIs</term><def><p>hospital-acquired infections</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MBEC</term><def><p>minimum biofilm eradication concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDR</term><def><p>multi-drug resistant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRSA</term><def><p>methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSSA</term><def><p>methicillin sensitive <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aures</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MTT</term><def><p>3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p>propidium iodide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QASs</term><def><p>quaternary ammonium salts</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p>quantitative PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QS</term><def><p>quorum sensing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPMI</term><def><p>Roswell Park Memorial Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCD</term><def><p>soybean casein digest</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SEM</term><def><p>scanning electron microscope</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SS</term><def><p>stainless steel</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p>World Health Organization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YPD</term><def><p>yeast peptone broth</p></def></def-item></def-list></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>WHO</collab>
</person-group><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance#:~:text=It%20is%20estimated%20that%20bacterial,development%20of%20drug%2Dresistant%20pathogens" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance#:~:text=It%20is%20estimated%20that%20bacterial,development%20of%20drug%2Dresistant%20pathogens</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifipour</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Esmkhani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khodadadi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fotouhi-Ardakani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluation of bacterial co-infections of the respiratory tract in COVID-19 patients admitted to ICU</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>646</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-020-05374-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32873235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7461753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Silori</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Panday</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products, microplastics and co-infecting microbes in the post-COVID-19 era and its implications on antimicrobial resistance and potential endocrine disruptive effects</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2023</year><volume>904</volume><fpage>166419</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.166419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37625721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lanjri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Uwingabiye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frikh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdellatifi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kasouati</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>In vitro evaluation of the susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates to antiseptics and disinfectants: comparison between clinical and environmental isolates</article-title><source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>36</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-017-0195-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28400958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5387265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Esteves</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simões</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Influence of biological fluids in bacterial viability on different hospital surfaces and fomites</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2015.09.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26577628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jabłońska-Trypuć</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Makuła</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Włodarczyk-Makuła</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wołejko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wydro</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Inanimate surfaces as a source of hospital infections caused by fungi, bacteria and viruses with particular emphasis on SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>8121</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19138121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35805776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9265696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chewins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Keevil</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An automated contact model for transmission of dry surface biofilms of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in healthcare</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2023</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2023.06.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37348564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bloomfield</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The survival and transfer of microbial contamination via cloths, hands and utensils</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1990</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.1990.tb02574.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2111304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>About List N: Disinfectants for coronavirus (COVID-19) | US EPA. (2024, April 10). US EPA</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/coronavirus/about-list-n-disinfectants-coronavirus-covid-19-0" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.epa.gov/coronavirus/about-list-n-disinfectants-coronavirus-covid-19-0</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Budhathoki-Uprety</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Increased use of disinfectants during the COVID-19 pandemic and its potential impacts on health and safety</article-title><source>ACS Chem Health Saf</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chas.1c00026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vossebein</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zille</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Efficacy of disinfectant-impregnated wipes used for surface disinfection in hospitals: a review</article-title><source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>139</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-019-0595-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31452873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6701098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Demirbas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An overview of biomass pyrolysis</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Energy Sources</italic>
</source><year>2002</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00908310252889979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelaal</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Bio-oil production and catalytic upgrade to value added product: a review on recent technologies</article-title><source>J Energy Institute</source><year>2025</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>101880</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joei.2024.101880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sivaraman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jothipandiyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatachalam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ramiah Shanmugam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Bioprospecting of aqueous phase from pyrolysis of plant waste residues to disrupt MRSA biofilms</article-title><source>Biofouling</source><year>2023</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08927014.2023.2207461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37144617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rubini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vedha Hari</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nithyanand</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Chitosan coated catheters alleviates mixed species biofilms of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> albicans</article-title><source>Carbohydr Polym</source><year>2021</year><volume>252</volume><fpage>117192</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2020.117192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33183634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Synergistic antimicrobial activity between the broad spectrum bacteriocin Garvicin KS and Nisin, Farnesol and Polymyxin B against gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-017-1375-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29058043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5809525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Biron</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Said</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Subirade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fliss</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Bacteriocin-based synergetic consortia: a promising strategy to enhance antimicrobial activity and broaden the spectrum of inhibition</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Microbiol Spectr</italic>
</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.00406-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8849083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35170996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jothipandiyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sudharsan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Transition metal complex laminated bioactive implant alleviates methicillin resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> virulence</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Biomater Adv</italic>
</source><year>2022</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>212813</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bioadv.2022.212813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35929252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jothipandiyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paramasivam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Palladium(II) metal complex fabricated titanium implant mitigates dual-species biofilms in artificial synovial fluid</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>1296</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12081296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37627716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10451766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jabłońska-Trypuć</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Makuła</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Włodarczyk-Makuła</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wołejko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wydro</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Inanimate surfaces as a source of hospital infections caused by fungi, bacteria and viruses with particular emphasis on SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>8121</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19138121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35805776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9265696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dhama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Masand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The role of disinfectants and sanitizers during COVID-19 pandemic: advantages and deleterious effects on humans and the environment</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</italic>
</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>34211</fpage><lpage>34228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-14429-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33991301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8122186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>KSS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banjare</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shaik</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A key review on oxadiazole analogs as potential methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) activity: structure-activity relationship studies</article-title><source>Eur J Med Chem</source><year>2021</year><volume>219</volume><fpage>113442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2021.113442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33878562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Donelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Strategies for combating bacterial biofilms: a focus on anti-biofilm agents and their mechanisms of action</article-title><source>Virulence</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2017.1313372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28362216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5955472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Subhadra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Surendran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Control of biofilm formation in healthcare: recent advances exploiting quorum-sensing interference strategies and multidrug efflux pump inhibitors</article-title><source>Materials</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1676</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma11091676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30201944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6163278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pompilio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scocchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mangoni</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shirooie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Bioactive compounds: a goldmine for defining new strategies against pathogenic bacterial biofilms?</article-title><source>Crit Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1040841X.2022.2038082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35313120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effect of <italic toggle="yes">Duabanga grandiflora</italic> on MRSA biofilm formation via prevention of cell-surface attachment and PBP2a production</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>4473</fpage><lpage>4482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules20034473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25764489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6272415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Galvão</surname><given-names>F de O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dantas</surname><given-names>FG da S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>CR de L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marchioro</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>CAL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Cochlospermum regium (Schrank) pilger leaf extract inhibit methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2020</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>113167</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.113167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32730885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clauditz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Resch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>K-P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peschel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Götz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Staphyloxanthin plays a role in the fitness of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and its ability to cope with oxidative stress</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2006</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>4950</fpage><lpage>4953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00204-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16861688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1539600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shehabeldine</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ashour</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Okba</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saber</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Callistemon citrinus bioactive metabolites as new inhibitors of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2020</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>112669</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.112669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32087316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karunanidhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaznavi-Rad</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamat</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pichika</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lung</surname><given-names>LTT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antibiofilm activities of nonpolar extracts of <italic toggle="yes">Allium stipitatum</italic> regel. against multidrug resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>9845075</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/9845075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30105271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6076948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Souza Dos Santos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bezerra Filho</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alves do Nascimento Junior</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brust</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bezerra-Silva</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Anti-staphylococcal activity of <italic toggle="yes">Syagrus coronata</italic> essential oil: biofilm eradication and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> action on <italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonela</italic> infection model</article-title><source>Microb Pathog</source><year>2019</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2019.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30965089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alibi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Selma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos-Vivas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smach</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Touati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Anti-oxidant, antibacterial, anti-biofilm, and anti-quorum sensing activities of four essential oils against multidrug-resistant bacterial clinical isolates</article-title><source>Curr Res Transl Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.retram.2020.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32192922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Masoumipour</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanshahian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jafarinasab</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Study the antibacterial and antibiofilm activity of <italic toggle="yes">Carum</italic> copticum against antibiotic-resistant bacteria in planktonic and biofilm forms</article-title><source>Microb Pathog</source><year>2019</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2019.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30731188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karunanidhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaznavi-Rad</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamat</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pichika</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lung</surname><given-names>LTT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antibiofilm activities of nonpolar extracts of <italic toggle="yes">Allium stipitatum</italic> regel. against multidrug resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>9845075</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/9845075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30105271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6076948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The antioxidant guaiacol exerts fungicidal activity against fungal growth and deoxynivalenol production in <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>762844</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.762844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34867894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8634675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cavaco-Paulo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Production of antimicrobial powders of guaiacol oligomers by a laccase-catalyzed synthesis reaction</article-title><source>Process Biochem</source><year>2021</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procbio.2021.07.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>W-M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H-L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Antityrosinase and antimicrobial activities of furfuryl alcohol, furfural and furoic acid</article-title><source>Int J Biol Macromol</source><year>2013</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2013.02.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23466497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taherymoosavi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DRG</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Wheat straw vinegar: a more cost-effective solution than chemical fungicides for sustainable wheat plant protection</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2020</year><volume>725</volume><fpage>138359</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32278180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>J-D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>New pyrone and cyclopentenone derivatives from marine-derived fungus <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus sydowii</italic> SCSIO 00305</article-title><source>Nat Prod Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786419.2019.1629919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31204847</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>