<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1523</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">idr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">idr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8274629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8274629.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8274629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8274629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34262306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S310081</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">310081</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phenotypic and Genotypic Characteristics of Biofilm Formation in Clinical Isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Li et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Li et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhaoyinqian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zixuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinrui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="J">Jingling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="T">Tingting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhangrui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhibin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9042-2829</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jinbo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Laboratory Medicine, the Affiliated Hospital of Southwest Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Luzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>646000</addr-line>, <addr-line>Sichuan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Jinbo Liu <institution>Department of Laboratory Medical, Affiliated Hospital of Southwest Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>25 Taiping Street</addr-line>, <addr-line>Luzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>646000</addr-line>, <addr-line>Sichuan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel/Fax +86 0830 3165730</phone> Email Liulab2019@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">372595</issue-id><fpage>2613</fpage><lpage>2624</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-04 23:25:13.090"><day>04</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021 Li et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="idr-14-2613.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Background</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is an important pathogen in clinical infections, and biofilm formation is an effective way for <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> to survive under external pressures. In this study, the aims were to examine the antimicrobial resistance, biofilm formation, and biofilm-specific resistance in clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>A total of 104 clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were collected from a large teaching hospital in Southwest China. The antibiotics susceptibilities were tested, and biofilm-forming ability was evaluated by crystal violet staining by confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM). Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC), minimum biofilm inhibitory concentration (MBIC), and minimum biofilm eradication concentration (MBEC) of ciprofloxacin, meropenem, and ceftazidime were tested on selected strains by broth microdilution method. Biofilm-associated genes were detected by polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and expression of genes at planktonic stage and biofilm stage were analyzed by real-time reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR).</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>Multidrug-resistant (MDR) isolates accounted for 65.4%, but no strain was resistant to tigecycline and polymyxin B. Moreover, non-MDR strains tended to form stronger biofilms than MDR strains, and a negative correlation between biofilm-forming ability and resistance profiles to each of tested antimicrobials were observed. The MBECs and MBICs of ciprofloxacin, ceftazidime, and meropenem were evidently increased compared with MICs and MBCs among all tested strains. Additionally, the biofilm formation ability of the <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic>-positive strains was stronger than that of the <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic>-negative strains. The strains in MDR group had higher carrying rate of <italic toggle="yes">csuA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic> genes than non-MDR group, while non-MDR strains possessed more <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> gene than MDR group. Finally, <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene was significantly up-regulated after biofilm formation.</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>These results revealed valuable data for the negative correlation between antimicrobial resistance and biofilm formation, as well as phenotypic and genotypic characteristics of biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>biofilm formation</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial resistance</kwd><kwd>gene expression</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="8"/><ref-count count="51"/><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is one of the most common nosocomial pathogen that causes several severe infections in critically ill patients, and a great number of multidrug-resistant (MDR) strains attract the attention of the whole world.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The formation of biofilm contributes to <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> adhere to various biological and non-biological surfaces, such as vascular catheters, cerebrospinal fluid shunts, and other medical devices.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Biofilm is defining composed of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) that surrounding microorganisms, which mediates microbial adhesion and makes a lifestyle that is totally different from the planktonic state.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Indeed, biofilm formation presents a significantly higher antimicrobial resistance than planktonic cells, resulting in harder eradication and easier recurrence in biofilm-associated infections.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Biofilm formation is a complex process and regulated by a variety of factors. Taking <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> for example, biofilm associated protein (Bap) is involved in the initial adhering of biofilm, promoting the maturation of biofilm and maintaining the structure of mature biofilm.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Moreover, synthesis and assembly of pili are encoded by <italic toggle="yes">csuA/BABCDE</italic> gene cluster to induce the initial adhesion process of biofilm.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The BfmR-BfmS regulatory system senses the changes of external signals then affects the synthesis and secretion of pili, and induces the biofilm formation by regulating the <italic toggle="yes">csuA/BABCDE</italic> gene cluster as well.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The <italic toggle="yes">pgaABCD</italic> locus encodes the production of poly-beta-1-6-N-acetylglucosamine (PNAG), which is not only an important virulence factor but also essential for biofilm formation.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> The self-induced synthetase gene <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> is involved in the quorum sensing (QS) system and plays an important role in later stages of biofilm maturation.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Outer membrane protein A (OmpA) is a well-known virulence factor that contributes to adhesion, invasion, and biofilm formation of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> On the other hand, the latest research has reported that biofilm growth-associated repressor (BigR) directly or indirectly regulates the expression of genes related to epithelial cell adhesion and biofilm formation.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Several biofilm-associated genes affect the antimicrobial susceptibility, indicating a relationship between biofilm formation and antimicrobial resistance.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p><p>However, it is still unclear whether there is a quantitative correlation between biofilm formation and antimicrobial resistance. The aims of this study were to analyze the antimicrobial susceptibility, biofilm formation, biofilm-specific resistance, and biofilm-associated gene carrying rate of 104 clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Furthermore, the phenotype-genotype correlation between planktonic and biofilm stage was also evaluated.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Identification and Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (AST)</title><p>A total of 104 non-repetitive <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains were isolated from January 2020 to April 2021 in the Affiliated Hospital of Southwest Medical University, and ATCC19606 was used as the reference strain in this study. Identification and antimicrobial resistance analysis were performed by the MicroScan Walk-Away 96 Plus system (Siemens, Germany), and results were interpreted according to the standards of the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) 2020-M100.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC25922 and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC27853 (purchased from China National Health Inspection Center) were used as quality control. Based on the obtained antimicrobial resistance profiles, the tested strains were classified into multidrug-resistant (MDR) group if ‘the isolates are resistant to three or more antimicrobial classes’,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and non-MDR group which the isolates are resistant to 0–2 antimicrobial classes.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Biofilm Formation Assay</title><p>Biofilm formation ability was determined by crystal violet staining method as described previously,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> with slight modifications. Briefly, the overnight culture of each strain was diluted to final optical density of 600 (OD<sub>600</sub>) = 0.1, and then 180 μL of Luria-Bertani (LB) broth (Haibo, Qingdao, China) with 1% glucose (Sigma, USA) and 20 μL of bacterial suspensions were inoculated into 96-well polystyrene microtiter plates (Costar #3524, Corning, NY, USA) in triplicate. After 24 h incubation at 37 °C, the plates were gently washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for three times and stained with 200 μL of 0.1% crystal violet (Solarbio, Beijing, China) for 20 min. After washing with PBS for three times again, the plates were solubilized with 200 μL of 95% ethanol, followed by shaking slowly at room temperature for 20 min. The absorbance was measured at OD<sub>570</sub>. The cut-off OD (ODc) was defined as three standard deviations (SD) above the mean OD of the negative control (LB broth only). Following were classification criteria: OD ≤ OD<sub>C</sub>, non-biofilm producers (-); OD<sub>C</sub> &lt; OD ≤ 2×OD<sub>C</sub>, weak biofilm producers (+); 2×OD<sub>C</sub> &lt; OD ≤ 4×OD<sub>C</sub>, moderate biofilm producers (++); and OD &gt; 4×OD<sub>C</sub>, strong biofilm producers (+++).<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Determination of Biofilm Using Confocal Laser Scanning Microscopy (CLSM)</title><p>Four strains (two strong biofilm producers, one biofilm-negative producer, and ATCC19606) were selected for biofilm visualization by CLSM (Leica, Germany). In brief, strains were cultured in LB broth for 18 h and diluted to 0.5 McFarland standard. One hundred microlitre suspension and 2 mL fresh LB broth were added in the petri dishes (FengRun, Beijing, China). After incubation at 37 °C for 24 h, the petri dishes were washed three times with PBS and fixed with 2 mL of 2.5% glutaraldehyde for 1.5 h. Then, the petri dishes were washed three times with PBS again and 200 μL fluorescein isothiocyanate-concanavalin A (FITC-ConA) (Sigma, Germany) were added and stored at 4 °C for 30 min. Two hundred microlitre propidium iodide (PI) (Sigma, Germany) were added and stored at 4 °C for 15 min after washing three times with PBS. Finally, the dishes were washed with PBS and sealed with 40% glycerol. FITC-conA binds to EPS of biofilm and reflects green fluorescence at the laser wavelength of 488 nm.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> PI binds to bacterial DNA and emits red fluorescence at 543 nm.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> If both lasers appear at the same time, an orange fluorescence will be shown.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Growth Curve Assay</title><p>The growth of eight strong biofilm producers, eight weak biofilm producers, and ATCC19606 were evaluated. For each strain, 20 μL of diluted overnight culture (0.5 McFarland standard) and 180 μL LB broth were added in 96-well plates and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h, and the OD<sub>590</sub> was detected by microplate reader every 2 h until 24 h. After biofilm modeling on plates, the OD<sub>570</sub> was measured by microplate reader every 4 h until the number of biofilm biomass decreased. All assays were repeated in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC), Minimum Bactericidal Concentration (MBC), Minimum Biofilm Inhibitory Concentration (MBIC), and Minimum Biofilm Eradication Concentration (MBEC)</title><p>Three antimicrobials that are commonly used for the treatment of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections were selected in the determination of MICs/MBCs and MBICs/MBECs. All of these nine strains were originally sensitive to tested antimicrobials. The MICs for ceftazidime, ciprofloxacin, and meropenem were assessed using broth microdilution method in 96-well plates according to the procedures described in CLSI 2020-M100 guideline.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> After MIC determination, 10 μL aliquots from the wells with no observed bacterial growth were smeared on LB agar plates and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h, and the lowest concentration of antimicrobials that making no colony grows on plates was considered as MBC. AST at biofilm stage was performed according to the procedures described previously.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Biofilm was established in 96-well plates for 24 h, and planktonic cells were removed by sterile deionized water. Each well was treated with 200 μL of LB broth containing serially diluted antimicrobials. The plates were incubated for 24 h at 37 °C. The minimum antimicrobial concentration at which OD<sub>600</sub> &lt; 0.1 was determined as the MBIC.</p><p>Following the MBIC examination, the plates were washed with sterile deionized water to remove planktonic cells and antibiotics. Two hundred microlitre of LB broth was added to each well, and the plates were incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. The lowest concentration at which OD<sub>600</sub> &lt; 0.1 was considered as the MBEC. All experiments were performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Detection of Biofilm-Associated Genes by Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and Real-Time Reverse Transcription PCR (RT-PCR)</title><p>The DNA template was prepared by boiling bacteria.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The biofilm-associated genes of all 104 clinical strains were detected by PCR, including <italic toggle="yes">bap, ompA, bigR, bfmS, bfmR, csuA, csuB, csuC, csuD, csuE, csuAB, pgaD</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=310081.docx">Table S1</ext-link></underline>). The procedures were followed by previous study with slight modifications.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Part of nucleotide sequences of PCR products were analyzed by Beijing Qingke Biotechnology Co. Ltd. The results were compared with sequences that retrieved from GenBank database by the BLAST online tool at <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link></underline>. Moreover, eight strong biofilm producers were selected to detect the expression level of 13 biofilm-associated genes by RT-PCR according to the protocol described previously.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The fold change of mRNAs expression was calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method, and the relative expression of each gene was normalized to the control sample (planktonic stage), which was assigned a value of 1 arbitrary unit.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> All assays were performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analyses and graphs were performed using GraphPad Prism 8.0.1 (GraphPad Software Inc, USA), Origin 2018 (OriginLab, USA) and SPSS 24.0 (SPSS Statistics, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Based on the distribution and homogeneity of the variances, the OD values were expressed as the mean ± SD or median (interquartile range, IQR). Spearman’s rank correlation test was used for intergroup comparison. Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test is used to analyze the carrying situation of 13 genes and biofilm formation capacity. Chi-square test was used to compare the positive rates of 13 genes and the number of genes carried in different resistance types of strains. Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was used for gene expression in planktonic stage and biofilm stage. In all analyses, a two-sided significance level of &lt;0.05 was considered as statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Distribution and Antimicrobial Susceptibility Profiles of Clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> Strains</title><p>One hundred and four clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were collected from 18 departments within the major of intensive care unit (27, 26.2%) and department of neurology (22, 21.4%). Furthermore, the majority of specimens were obtained from sputum, accounting for 72.8%, while only 12.6%, 7.7%, 4.9%, and 2% specimens were isolated from secretion, blood, cerebrospinal fluid, and urine, respectively. The AST results for 18 antimicrobials are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>. Most of isolates (68, 65.4%) were resistance to ciprofloxacin and piperacillin/tazobactam, followed by levofloxacin (67, 64.4%), cefepime (67, 64.4%), meropenem (67, 64.4%), imipenem (67, 64.4%), ceftazidime (67, 64.4%), ceftriaxone (65, 62.5%), cefotaxime (65, 62.5%), piperacillin (62, 59.6%), ampicillin/sulbactam (61, 58.7%), ticarcillin/clavulanic acid (60, 57.7%), gentamicin (54,51.9%), tobramycin (52, 50%), amikacin (52, 50%), and tetracycline (30, 28.8%). More than 65.4% of the isolates exhibited multidrug resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1B</xref>), but no strain was resistant to tigecycline and polymyxin B.<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Antimicrobial susceptibility profiles of clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. (<bold>A</bold>) Resistance rate of all strains to 18 antimicrobials; (<bold>B</bold>) approximately 65.4% of isolates exhibited MDR (including XDR).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-14-2613-g0001.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: MDR, multiple drug resistance; XDR, extensively drug resistance.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Biofilm Formation Ability and Growth Curve Analysis</title><p>The biofilm-forming capacity of each isolate was summarized. The OD<sub>570</sub> values for the reference strain (ATCC19606) and negative control were 0.84 ± 0.12 and 0.14 ± 0.008, respectively (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=310081.docx">Table S2</ext-link></underline>). The OD<sub>570</sub> values for the clinical isolates ranged from 0.14 ± 0.01 to 2.54 ± 0.26, and the IQR was 0.58 (0.36, 1.04). It is worth noting that 99% of these strains can form biofilm, of which 51.5% were strong biofilm producers. In addition, 35.6% strains produced stronger biofilm than ATCC19606. No significant difference was observed between eight strong and eight weak biofilm producers in growth curves, indicating that the difference in biofilm formation was not due to growth rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>). Furthermore, four strains were selected to observe the biofilm formation ability using CLSM. The strongest biofilm-forming strain 20047 reflected the highest fluorescence intensity, followed by strain 20192 and ATCC19606, and biofilm-forming negative strain 19014 presented the lowest fluorescence intensity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3A</xref>). The fluorescence intensities under CLSM were consistent with the OD<sub>570</sub> values obtained by crystal violet staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3B</xref>).<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Growth curves and biofilm growth curves in representative <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains. (<bold>A</bold>) Growth curves of 17 representative <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains at planktonic stage, and OD<sub>590</sub> values of each strain were measured every 2 h until 24 h; (<bold>B</bold>) growth curves for 17 representative <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains at biofilm stage, and OD<sub>570</sub> values of each strain were measured every 4 h until 48 h. The data were presented as the average of three measurements. Error bars (standard deviation &lt;10%) were omitted for simplicity.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-14-2613-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Evaluation of biofilm formation capacity of strains by confocal laser scanning microscopy. (<bold>A</bold>) Biofilm Images of four representative <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains under CLSM (<bold>B</bold>) Comparison of biofilm formation capabilities between crystal violet and CLSM. Data were expressed as mean ± SD; fluorescence intensity represents CLSM results and OD<sub>570</sub> indicates crystal violet results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-14-2613-g0003.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Correlation Between Antimicrobial Resistance and Biofilm Formation Ability</title><p>Spearman’s rank correlation analysis determined that non-MDR strains tended to form stronger biofilms than MDR strains (<italic toggle="yes">r<sub>s</sub></italic>= -0.212, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.03; <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), suggesting a negative correlation between biofilm formation capacity and antimicrobial resistance phenotypes. Moreover, the results revealed that in addition to tigecycline and polymyxin B, susceptible strains could form stronger biofilm than resistant strains, indicating a negative correlation between biofilm-forming ability and resistance profiles to each of tested antimicrobials (<italic toggle="yes">r<sub>s</sub></italic>= 0.204 − 0.288, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003 − 0.037; <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>)<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Biofilm Formation Ability of Strains with Different Antimicrobial Resistance</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistance Profile</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OD<sub>570</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">r<sub>s</sub></italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-MDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.36, 1.47)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-0.212</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.36, 0.85)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: OD<sub>570</sub>: The absorbance value at the wavelength of 570 nm. Data was shown in median (interquartile range, IQR).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation Between Biofilm Formation Ability and Antimicrobial Resistance to 18 Antimicrobials</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Antimicrobial Category</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Antimicrobial Agent</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">OD<sub>570</sub></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">r<sub>s</sub></italic></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Aminoglycosides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.34,1.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.38,0.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.211</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.032</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobramycin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.36,1.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.37,0.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.211</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.032</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.36,1.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.37,0.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.03</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Carbapenemase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imipenem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.36,1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.37,0.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.029</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meropenem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.36,1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.37,0.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.029</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Fluoroquinolones</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.36,1.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.37,0.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.031</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levofloxacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.36,1.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.37,0.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.031</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Penicillins + β-lactamase inhibitors</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin/sulbactam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.36,1.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.49,0.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.239</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.018</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin/tazobactam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.36,1.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.36,0.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.235</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.016</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ticarcillin/clavulanic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.37,1.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.36,0.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.288</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Cephalosporins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.36,1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.37,0.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.029</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftriaxone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.36,1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.37,0.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.029</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefotaxime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.37,1.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.36,0.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefepime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.36,1.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.36,0.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.235</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.016</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tetracyclines</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracycline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.38,1.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59(0.36,1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.034</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tigecycline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.36, 1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penicillins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.36,1,30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.37,0.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.037</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipopeptides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymyxin B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.36, 1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: S, sensitive; R, resistance; bold indicates <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Comparison of MICs/MBICs and MBCs/MBECs</title><p>The MICs and MBICs of three antimicrobials (ceftazidime, ciprofloxacin, and meropenem) were tested against nine strains with different biofilm-forming ability (three strong biofilm producers, three moderate biofilm producers, and three weak biofilm producers), and all strains were sensitive to these three antibiotics being investigated. MBICs for biofilms increased drastically compared with MIC for planktonic cells among all tested strains (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The increases ranged from 256- to 4096-fold for ciprofloxacin, 16- to 1024-fold for meropenem, and 128- to 1024-fold for ceftazidime. Indeed, when biofilms were established, the antimicrobial susceptibility profiles of all strains changed from sensitive to resistance.<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of MICs and MBICs of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> Strains</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strain</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Meropenem</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Ceftazidime</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC for Planktonic Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBIC for Biofilm Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC for Planktonic Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBIC for Biofilm Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC for Planktonic Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBIC for Biofilm Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20053<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20061<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20068<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20098<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20101<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20110<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20047<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20180<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20250<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Indicates weak biofilm producer, <sup>b</sup>Indicates moderate biofilm producer, <sup>c</sup>Indicates strong biofilm producer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Furthermore, MBCs and MBECs of these nine isolates were also evaluated. Undoubtedly, the MBECs were much higher than the MBCs among all tested strains (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Up to a 4096-fold increase in the concentration of ciprofloxacin and up to a 1024-fold increase in the concentration of ceftazidime and meropenem were required to eradicate biofilms compared with planktonic cells.<table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of MBCs and MBECs of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> Strains</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strain</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Meropenem</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Ceftazidime</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBC for Planktonic Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBEC for Biofilm Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBC for Planktonic Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBEC for Biofilm Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBC for Planktonic Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBEC for Biofilm Cells (µg/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20053<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20061<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20068<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20098<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20101<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20110<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20047<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20180<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20250<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Indicates weak biofilm producer, <sup>b</sup>Indicates moderate biofilm producer, <sup>c</sup>Indicates strong biofilm producer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Distribution and Expression of Biofilm-Associated Genes in Clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> Strains</title><p>In order to further explore the correlation between biofilm-forming ability and antimicrobial resistance, the presence of 13 reported biofilm-associated genes was detected by using PCR. The results showed that <italic toggle="yes">bfmR</italic> (98, 94.2%) was occurred mostly, followed by <italic toggle="yes">csuC</italic> (95, 91.3%), <italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic> (95, 91.3%), <italic toggle="yes">bigR</italic> (92, 88.5%), <italic toggle="yes">csuAB</italic> (91, 87.5%), <italic toggle="yes">csuB</italic> (90, 86.5%), <italic toggle="yes">OmpA</italic> (89, 85.6%), <italic toggle="yes">bfmS</italic> (88, 84.6%), <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic> (85, 81.7%), <italic toggle="yes">pgaD</italic> (80, 76.9%), <italic toggle="yes">csuA</italic> (76, 73.1%), <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic> (73, 70.2%), and <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> (73, 70.2%). Twenty-five clinical isolates contained all 13 tested genes, including 23 strong biofilm producers and two moderate biofilm producers (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=310081.docx">Table S3</ext-link></underline>). Remarkably, the biofilm formation ability of the <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic>-positive strains was stronger than that of the <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic>-negative strains (U = 365, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p><p>The harboring rates of 13 biofilm-associated genes among two groups were evaluated by Chi-square test. Three genes were significantly related to antimicrobial resistance. In detail, the strains in MDR group had higher carrying rate of <italic toggle="yes">csuA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic> genes than non-MDR group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05); however, the non-MDR strains possessed more <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> gene than MDR group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4A</xref>).<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Role of biofilm-associated genes in antimicrobial resistance and biofilm of clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. Baumannii</italic>. (<bold>A</bold>) Percentage of biofilm-associated gene in different antimicrobial-resistant strains; (<bold>B</bold>) the relative expression of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> in eight selected <italic toggle="yes">A. Baumannii</italic> strains. Data were shown as fold changes between planktonic and biofilm stage, and control represented planktonic cells.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-14-2613-g0004.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001.</attrib></fig></p><p>Eight strong biofilm-forming strains that carrying 13 biofilm-associated genes were selected to investigate the relationship between biofilm-associated genes and biofilm formation ability (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=310081.docx">Table S4</ext-link></underline>). The RT-PCR results showed that the expression of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene in the biofilm stage was significantly up-regulated compared with that in the planktonic stage (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4B</xref>), while no significant difference was found for the rest of the 12 genes between planktonic stage and biofilm stage.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> shows superior ability to disseminate worldwide, and the proportion of extreme drug resistance (XDR) <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> has increased from less than 4% in 2000 to more than 60% recently, even close to 90% in some regional nosocomial settings.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> According to the National Institutes of Health and the Center for Disease and Prevention, it is estimated that 65% to 80% of the human infectious are caused by biofilm-forming bacteria.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> The lifestyle changes from planktonic phenotype to biofilm is a highly regulated developmental process that depends on species-dependent environmental and genetic factors.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p>This study evaluated the biofilm-forming ability of 104 clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains, and explored the effect of biofilm production on antimicrobial susceptibility. The MDR strains have reached 65.4%, which increased the difficulty of infection treatment. The AST results revealed that all tested strains remained sensitive to polymyxin B and tigecycline, and it seemed that these two antimicrobials were the most effective strategy for MDR-<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections. However, two meta-analyses discourage using tigecycline for the treatment of MDR-<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections due to the higher in-hospital mortality and longer hospitalization when compared with other active antimicrobials.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Moreover, polymyxin B rarely used in clinical treatment because of the lack of pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic studies and highly renal toxicity.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Therefore, the optimal treatment for MDR-<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections have not been established so far.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p>Then, the crystal violet staining results demonstrated that 99% strains have biofilm-forming ability and nearly one-half of strains can produce strong biofilms, which was consistent with the previous reports.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Up to date, there is still no regular pattern in the relationship between biofilm formation ability and bacterial antimicrobial resistance, and the conclusions between different researches were even contradictory.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33–36</xref> In our research, the non-MDR strains could produce stronger biofilm compared with MDR strains, indicating that the antimicrobial resistance and biofilm formation ability were negatively correlated in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Rodriguez-Bano et al have illustrated that biofilm-forming <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were more sensitive to ciprofloxacin and imipenem,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> suggesting that these strains were not as dependent on antimicrobial resistance as non-biofilm-forming isolates for survival, which was consistent with our result. Moreover, a research has found that the biofilm-forming ability of ciprofloxacin-sensitive <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> was significantly promoted after exposure to ciprofloxacin,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> highlighting the importance of biofilms for the survival of sensitive bacteria. Therefore, it seems that the biofilm formation is another survival mechanism besides antimicrobial resistance. Furthermore, MIC/MBIC and MBC/MBEC values confirmed that the resistance of isolates was greatly enhanced after biofilm formation, regardless of whether the isolates were originally sensitive or resistant to this antimicrobial. Remarkably, antimicrobials inhibit biofilms mainly through a complex penetration process,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> however, this still cannot complete remove the bacteria in the biofilm stage due to multifactorial tolerance of biofilms.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> For example, beta-lactam antimicrobials can be inactivated by beta-lactamases in the biofilm matrix, which restricts their penetration. Biofilm-stage bacteria with low metabolic activity can resistant to kinds of antimicrobials that target processes that occur in growing bacteria, such as cell wall synthesis and DNA replication.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> In addition, the expression of specific genes and dormant state persister cells are also responsible for the failure inhibition of biofilms.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></p><p>In addition to the correlation between antimicrobial resistance and biofilm formation, the relationship between biofilm formation and biofilm-associated genes expression was also evaluated in this study. All the biofilm-associated genes were detected in more than 70% of tested strains, bring with the most frequent gene <italic toggle="yes">bfmR</italic> (98, 94.2%) as well as the least genes <italic toggle="yes">csuD and abaI</italic> (70.2%). It has been known that the chaperone usher pili assembly system is essential for the initial steps of biofilm formation.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Tomaras et al have certified that the inactivation of the <italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic> gene resulted in the disappearance of both pili formation and biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> The gene <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic> is part of the CsuA/BABCDE chaperone-usher pili assembly system, in this study, <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic>-positive strains can form stronger biofilm than <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic>-negative strains. This result was consistent with the previous study that indicating <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic> was highly expressed in stronger biofilm producers.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Moreover, in this work, three genes had a obviously distributed regularity among strains with different antimicrobial-resistant profiles. With the increase of resistance, there was a growing positive rate of <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> and a decreasing positive rate of <italic toggle="yes">csuA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic>. Although CsuA/BABCDE system is able to enhance biofilm formation, the relationship between this system and antimicrobial resistance still not clear. OmpA is a major component of outer membrane proteins (OMPs) in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, which is related to antimicrobial resistance, aggressiveness, and biofilm formation.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Smani et al first determined that the deletion of <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> decreased the MICs of chloramphenicol, nalidixic and aztreonam by 8-, 2.67-, and 8-fold, respectively.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Sanchez-Encinales et al demonstrated that overproduction of OmpA was an independent risk factor for nosocomial pneumonia, bacteremia, and higher mortality caused by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> A previous study confirmed that <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> measured by RT-PCR can be used as a rapid diagnostic factor for antimicrobial-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> due to the high consistency with MICs.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> In <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, QS system is consists of AbaI/AbaR system, which is closely interconnected with biofilm development.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene encodes the self-induced synthase which activates the synthesis of AHL signals, and <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> mutant leads a greatly reduction of biofilm formation.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> In this study, <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> was the only gene that up-regulated in biofilm stage; however, other tested genes did not show regular changes between planktonic and biofilm stages. A recent study has shown that the absence of AHL signal in shaking cultures (planktonic) seemed to be the result of low expression of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>, while the AHL signal was significantly up-regulated under static conditions (biofilm).<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Niu et al have demonstrated that the biofilm formation ability of wild type and <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> mutant was no difference at 8 h, but the biofilm formation ability of the mutant was significantly lower than that of wild type at 16 h and 24 h, which was 40% and 41%, respectively. These results suggest that the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>-directed QS pathway is required for the later stages of biofilm maturation.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The biofilms were established for 24 h in this study, and it might be the reason why only <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> was overexpressed and the expressions of other genes that contributed to the initial steps of biofilm formation were not significantly changed.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Indeed, the mechanism of biofilm-associated genes in biofilm formation and antimicrobial resistance needed to be further explored.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this study, most of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> have biofilm formation ability and high carrying rate of biofilm-associated genes. There was a negative correlation between biofilm formation ability and antimicrobial resistance, which was stronger biofilm formation occurring in non-MDR strains. Moreover, once the biofilm was formed, whether the biofilm was strong or weak, the antimicrobial resistance can be greatly improved. In addition, presence of <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic> was significantly associated with biofilm-forming capacity. The <italic toggle="yes">csuA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">csuD</italic> genes more occured in non-MDR strains, but <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> was more common in MDR strains. Notably, the expression of QS-related gene <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> up-regulated in biofilm stage. In fact, the number and type of biofilm-associated genes carried by biofilm-forming strains are quite different among different regions,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> indicating that the biofilm-forming ability is not only determined by the presence of biofilm-associated genes but a complex process depended on multiple factors. Deeper exploration of mechanisms of biofilm formation and biofilm-specific resistance in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> are highly needed.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by the grants from Sichuan Science and Technology Program (2021YFH001, 21ZDYF2148, 2019YFS0038), Southwest Medical University Science Program (2020ZRQNB025), and Luxian Government and Southwest Medical University Cooperation Program (2020LXXNYKD-04).</p></ack><sec id="s0006"><title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title><p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of affiliated hospital of southwest medical university (KY2020043). Written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors made substantial contributions to conception and design, acquisition of data, or analysis and interpretation of data; took part in drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual content; agreed to submit to the current journal; gave final approval of the version to be published; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="s0008" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hennon</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Uncovering the mechanisms of Acinetobacter baumannii virulence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29249812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6571207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rickard</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of the ability of Acinetobacter baumannii to form biofilms on six different biomedical relevant surfaces</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lett Appl Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/lam.12627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27479925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7057210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flemming</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wingender</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The biofilm matrix</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20676145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mah</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of biofilm-based antibiotic resistance and tolerance in pathogenic bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEMS Microbiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28369412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/femsre/fux010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Navidifar</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shooshtari</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between biofilm formation, structure, and the expression levels of genes related to biofilm formation and biofilm-specific resistance of Acinetobacter baumannii strains isolated from burn infection in Ahvaz, Iran</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3867</fpage>–<lpage>3881</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S228981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31853190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6914661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brossard</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campagnari</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Acinetobacter baumannii biofilm-associated protein plays a role in adherence to human epithelial cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Immun</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.05913-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22083703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3255684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Enhancing pili assembly and biofilm formation in Acinetobacter baumannii ATCC19606 using non-native acyl-homoserine lactones</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-015-0397-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4381447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaras</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flagler</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dorsey</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterization of a two-component regulatory system from Acinetobacter baumannii that controls biofilm formation and cellular morphology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology (Reading, England)</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>154</volume>(<issue>Pt 11</issue>):<fpage>3398</fpage>–<lpage>3409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.2008/019471-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pakharukova</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tuittila</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paavilainen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Structural basis for Acinetobacter baumannii biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>5558</fpage>–<lpage>5563</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1800961115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29735695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6003481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Slamti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Avci</surname>
<given-names>FY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pier</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maira-Litrán</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The pgaABCD locus of Acinetobacter baumannii encodes the production of poly-beta-1-6-N-acetylglucosamine, which is critical for biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>191</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>5953</fpage>–<lpage>5963</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00647-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2747904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shenkutie</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>MZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siu</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>BKC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname>
<given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biofilm-induced antibiotic resistance in clinical Acinetobacter baumannii isolates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics (Basel, Switzerland)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9110817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7698371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33212840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmer</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of an autoinducer synthase from Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3386</fpage>–<lpage>3392</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01929-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2347373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Outer membrane protein A (OmpA) as a potential therapeutic target for Acinetobacter baumannii infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biomed Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12929-020-0617-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31954394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6969976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>BJC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edmonds</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The response of Acinetobacter baumannii to hydrogen sulfide reveals two independent persulfide-sensing systems and a connection to biofilm regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mBio</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01254-20</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7315123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32576676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab>; <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wayne</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing, 30th Edition. CLSI M100</italic></source>. <publisher-name>CLSI</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tolmasky</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Carbapenemases: transforming Acinetobacter baumannii into a yet more dangerous menace</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomolecules</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>720</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom10050720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7277208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32384624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnamoorthy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Microbicides alter the expression and function of RND-type efflux pump AdeABC in biofilm-associated cells of Acinetobacter baumannii clinical isolates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01045-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26459900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4704159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vukovic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dakic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Savic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Svabic-Vlahovic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A modified microtiter-plate test for quantification of staphylococcal biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Microbiol Methods</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-7012(00)00122-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10699673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pakkulnan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anutrakunchai</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kanthawong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taweechaisupapong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chareonsudjai</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chareonsudjai</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Extracellular DNA facilitates bacterial adhesion during Burkholderia pseudomallei biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e0213288</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0213288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30856240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6411153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname>
<given-names>PJJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hormetic promotion of biofilm growth by polyvalent bacteriophages at low concentrations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Environ Sci Technol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>12358</fpage>–<lpage>12365</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.0c03558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32886494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role and relationship with efflux pump of biofilm formation in Klebsiella pneumoniae</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Pathog</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>104244</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2020.104244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32437832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moskowitz</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Emerson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinically feasible biofilm susceptibility assay for isolates of Pseudomonas aeruginosa from patients with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1915</fpage>–<lpage>1922</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.42.5.1915-1922.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15131149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC404629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Molecular epidemiology and risk factors of ventilator-associated pneumonia infection caused by carbapenem-resistant enterobacteriaceae</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2019.00262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30967778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6439532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moi</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>LY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biofilm formation in Acinetobacter baumannii: genotype-phenotype correlation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Molecules (Basel, Switzerland)</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>10</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24101849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6572253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31091746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bustin</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Benes</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garson</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The MIQE guidelines: minimum information for publication of quantitative real-time PCR experiments</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Chem</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>622</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1373/clinchem.2008.112797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19246619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Methods (San Diego, Calif)</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pantapalangkoor</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luna</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spellberg</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical and pathophysiological overview of Acinetobacter infections: a century of challenges</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Microbiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00058-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27974412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5217799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wolcott</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowd</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of biofilms: are we hitting the right target?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plast Reconstr Surg</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>127</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>28s</fpage>–<lpage>35s</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PRS.0b013e3181fca244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21200270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Tigecycline treatment experience against multidrug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii infections: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Antimicrob Agents</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2015.11.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26742726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kengkla</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kongpakwattana</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saokaew</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Apisarnthanarak</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chaiyakunapruk</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparative efficacy and safety of treatment options for MDR and XDR Acinetobacter baumannii infections: a systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Antimicrob Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkx368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29069421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kwa</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Polymyxin B versus colistin: an update</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1481</fpage>–<lpage>1497</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14787210.2015.1093933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26488563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garnacho-Montero</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Timsit</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Managing Acinetobacter baumannii infections</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QCO.0000000000000518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30520737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between antibiotic resistance, biofilm formation, and biofilm-specific resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>483</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4828443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regulation of Acinetobacter baumannii biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Future Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.09.5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2724675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khoshnood</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Savari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi Montazeri</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farajzadeh Sheikh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Survey on genetic diversity, biofilm formation, and detection of colistin resistance genes in clinical isolates of Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1547</fpage>–<lpage>1558</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S253440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32547124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7266307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterization of biofilm production in different strains of Acinetobacter baumannii and the effects of chemical compounds on biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PeerJ</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e9020</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.9020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32523805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7261477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez-Baño</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martí</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biofilm formation in Acinetobacter baumannii: associated features and clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Microbiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2007.01916.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18190568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of the sub-minimal inhibitory concentration and the concentrations within resistant mutation window of ciprofloxacin on MIC, swimming motility and biofilm formation of Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Pathog</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>137</volume>:<fpage>103765</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2019.103765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31586475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Theoretical aspects of antibiotic diffusion into microbial biofilms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2517</fpage>–<lpage>2522</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.40.11.2517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC163567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ciofu</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rojo-Molinero</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Macià</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antibiotic treatment of biofilm infections</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">APMIS</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apm.12673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28407419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Briales</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brochmann</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Formation of hydroxyl radicals contributes to the bactericidal activity of ciprofloxacin against Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathog Dis</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2049-632X.12120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Groote</surname>
<given-names>VN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verstraeten</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fauvart</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Novel persistence genes in Pseudomonas aeruginosa identified by high-throughput screening</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEMS Microbiol Lett</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>297</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2009.01657.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19508279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McQueary</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acinetobacter baumannii biofilms: variations among strains and correlations with other cell properties</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Microbiol (Seoul, Korea)</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12275-011-0343-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21538245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaras</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dorsey</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edelmann</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Attachment to and biofilm formation on abiotic surfaces by Acinetobacter baumannii: involvement of a novel chaperone-usher pili assembly system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology (Reading, England)</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3473</fpage>–<lpage>3484</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.26541-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14663080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Selasi</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Differences in biofilm mass, expression of biofilm-associated genes, and resistance to desiccation between epidemic and sporadic clones of carbapenem-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii sequence type 191</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e0162576</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27622249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5021322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smani</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fàbrega</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roca</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Encinales</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vila</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pachón</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of OmpA in the multidrug resistance phenotype of Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1806</fpage>–<lpage>1808</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02101-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3957889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Encinales</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Álvarez-marín</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pachón-Ibáñez</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Overproduction of outer membrane protein A by Acinetobacter baumannii as a risk factor for nosocomial pneumonia, bacteremia, and mortality rate increase</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>215</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>966</fpage>–<lpage>974</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jix010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28453834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martín-Peña</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Domínguez-Herrera</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pachón</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McConnell</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid detection of antibiotic resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii using quantitative real-time PCR</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Antimicrob Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1572</fpage>–<lpage>1575</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkt057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23435692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>López</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tomás</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Otero</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Multiple quorum quenching enzymes are active in the nosocomial pathogen Acinetobacter baumannii ATCC17978</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Cell Infect Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2018.00310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30271754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6146095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altınok</surname>
<given-names>Ö</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boral</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ergin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eser</surname>
<given-names>ÖK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Existence of biofilm and biofilm-associated virulence genes in multi-drug resistant invasive Acinetobacter baumannii isolates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mikrobiyol Bul</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5578/mb.20204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32050877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>YQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biofilm-related genes: analyses in multi-antibiotic resistant Acinetobacter baumannii isolates from Mainland China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medical Sci Monit</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1801</fpage>–<lpage>1807</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/MSM.898959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4913728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27234982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>