<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1523</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">idr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">idr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10475287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10475287.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10475287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10475287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37667809</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S417751</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">417751</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Glabridin Functions as a Quorum Sensing Inhibitor to Inhibit Biofilm Formation and Swarming Motility of Multidrug-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Lin et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Lin et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="H">Hang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="C">Cui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="KH">Kai-Hang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="YS">Yi-Shuai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="LB">Ling-Bo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="SX">Shi-Xing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="WY">Wen-Ya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2171-4710</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="TL">Tie-Li</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names initials="JM">Jian-Ming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8174-2580</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names initials="JZ">Jian-Zhong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Key Laboratory of Clinical Laboratory Diagnosis and Translational Research of Zhejiang Province, The First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>School of the First Clinical Medical Sciences, Wenhzou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Pathology Department, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>School of Laboratory Medicine and Life Science, Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Tie-Li Zhou; Jian-Zhong Ye, <institution>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Key Laboratory of Clinical Laboratory Diagnosis and Translational Research of Zhejiang Province, The First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanbaixiang Street, Ouhai District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>325000</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email wyztli@163.com; jzye89@163.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425909</issue-id><fpage>5697</fpage><lpage>5705</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-09-05 11:25:18.287"><day>05</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023 Lin et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lin et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="idr-16-5697.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is a hazardous bacterium that causes hospital-acquired nosocomial infections, and the advent of multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (MDR-AB) strains is concerning. Novel antibacterial therapeutic strategies must be developed. The biological effects of glabridin on MDR-AB were investigated in this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of glabridin against eight clinical MDR-AB strains were determined using the broth microdilution technique. Crystal violet staining was used to assess biofilm development, which has significant contribution to bacterial resistance. Swarming motility was measured according to surface growth zone of MDR-AB on LB agar medium. qRT-PCR was used to evaluate the expression of quorum sensing genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>. Glabridin and routinely used therapeutic antimicrobial agents were tested for synergistic action using the checkerboard method.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>According to our findings, glabridin suppressed MDR-AB growth at high doses (512–1024 μg/mL). The 1/4 MIC of glabridin significantly decreased MDR-AB biofilm formation by 19.98% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), inhibited MDR-AB motility by 44.27% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), whereas the 1/2 MIC of glabridin dramatically reduced MDR-AB biofilm development by 27.43% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), suppressed MDR-AB motility by 50.64% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Mechanistically, glabridin substantially downregulated the expression of quorum sensing-related genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> by up to 39.12% (P &lt; 0.001) and 25.19% (P &lt; 0.01), respectively. However, no synergistic effect between glabridin and antibacterial drugs was found.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Glabridin might be a quorum sensing inhibitor that inhibits MDR-AB biofilm development and swarming motility.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>multidrug-resistance</kwd><kwd>glabridin</kwd><kwd>quorum sensing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Major Projects of Wenzhou Science and Technology Bureau</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Key Laboratory of Clinical Laboratory Diagnosis and Translational Research of Zhejiang Province</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the Major Projects of Wenzhou Science and Technology Bureau (ZY2019011), the Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province (LY20H200004), and Key Laboratory of Clinical Laboratory Diagnosis and Translational Research of Zhejiang Province (2022E10022).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="25"/><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is a gram-negative, non-fermenting bacillus. It’s a common opportunistic pathogen in hospital-acquired infections, and it can cause invasive infections including sepsis, abdominal infection, and secondary meningitis in critically sick patients and those with compromised immune systems.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> can quickly develop antimicrobial resistance as a result of widespread and irrational use of antibacterial medications, making the infection exceedingly difficult to treat.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> As a result, novel therapies and countermeasures to combat <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infection are urgently needed.</p><p>Unlike antibacterial agents, quorum sensing inhibitors (QSIs) employ diverse mechanisms to target the quorum sensing system, including (i) inhibiting the synthesis of signal molecules; (ii) degrading signal molecules enzymatically; (iii) competing with signal molecules for receptor sites binding; (iv) interfering with signal molecules’ binding to gene promoters, thereby inhibiting gene expression; and (v) utilizing antibodies and macromolecules like cyclodextrins to scavenge autoinducers,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> thereby interfering with the virulence factors production in secretory system, the pathogenic bacteria biofilms formation, or the expression of pathogenic genes.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> This opens up new avenues for treating bacterial resistance and pathogen infection.</p><p>Licorice is a leguminous perennial plant belonging to the genus <italic toggle="yes">Glycyrrhiza</italic>. Licorice flavonoids have piqued people’s interest in recent years, notably since the discovery of its anti-HIV action,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> and their pharmacological effects have been consistently explored. Glabridin, a prominent bioactive compound found in licorice flavonoids, holds significant importance, and it has been linked to a variety of health benefits, including anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anti-tumorigenic, anti-atherogenic, anti-nephrotic, neuroprotective, and energy metabolism regulation.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Interestingly, glabridin has been demonstrated to exhibit antibacterial and antifungal properties in studies.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> flavonoids, another important component of licorice flavonoids, were found to effectively suppress the quorum sensing system and diminished the virulence of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. This was achieved by downregulating the expression of the auto-inducer synthase gene <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>, thereby inhibiting the quorum sensing system and reducing the virulence of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> However, the effect of glabridin on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is unclear. Thus, we investigated the biological effects of glabridin on multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (MDR-AB) in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Bacterial Strains and Antimicrobial Susceptibility Test</title><p>Eight multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were recovered from inpatients with bloodstream infections from the First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University. Imipenem, ceftazidime, ceftriaxone, ampicillin/sulbactam, gentamicin, tobramycin, ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin, tigecycline, and colistin were acquired from Wenzhou Kangtai Biotechnology Co., Ltd (Zhejiang, China) for this study, glabridin was purchased from Xi’an Tianguangyuan Biotechnology Co., Ltd (Shanxi, China). The antimicrobial susceptibility was assessed to determine MICs of antibiotics and glabridin using the broth microdilution method.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The MICs were interpreted using CLSI 2023 guidelines.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Effect of Glabridin on MDR-AB Growth</title><p>The effect of varying concentrations of glabridin on the growth of MDR-AB was investigated following the previously described method with minor modifications.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Briefly, the isolates were cultivated at 37°C with shaking while being exposed to different concentrations of glabridin. The optical density (OD<sub>600</sub> nm) was measured at various time points (2, 4, 6, 8, 10, and 24 h) during the experiment.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Biofilm Formation Evaluation</title><p>The biofilm-forming ability was assessed using the crystal violet staining method.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Under stationary conditions, the 8 MDR-AB strains were cultured in LB medium (200 μL) within a 96-well plate, with the presence or absence of glabridin, and maintained at 37°C. After incubation, the 96-well plate was subjected to three washes with sterile distilled water to eliminate planktonic bacterial cells. Subsequently, the biofilms were stained with 200 μL of 1% crystal violet for 10 minutes. The bound stain was then extracted using 200 μL of 33% glacial acetic acid, and the quantification was performed by measuring the absorbance at OD<sub>570</sub> nm after another round of washing.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Swarming Motility Assay</title><p>The surface motility of the bacteria was assessed using LB agar treated with glabridin (0.5 mg/mL) following the previously described method with minor modifications.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Two strains, namely BM-3994 and BM-4060, exhibiting relatively higher swarming motility, were cultivated until reaching the early stationary phase. A volume of 1 μL of the bacterial suspension was introduced onto the motility plate, followed by incubation at 37°C for 24 h, after which the surface growth zone was measured.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Quantitative Reverse Transcription PCR</title><p>To extract RNA from the eight MDR-AB strains, the strains were exposed to 1/2 MIC concentration of glabridin and concurrently grown with a control group (with the absence of glabridin) for a duration of 2 h. The isolated RNA was employed as a template for reverse transcription, utilizing the RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Scientific, MA, USA). The expression levels of the quorum sensing system genes (<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>) were assessed using qRT-PCR, employing specific primers, on an ABI 7500 real-time PCR system (Thermo Scientific, MA, USA).<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> All reactions were conducted in triplicate. The relative expression levels of the target genes were normalized to the reference gene 16S rRNA and determined using the 2-ΔΔCt method.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Synergism Testing</title><p>The checkerboard method was conducted to detect synergistic effectiveness of glabridin and imipenem, ceftazidime, ceftriaxone, gentamicin, tobramycin, ciprofloxacin, or levofloxacin.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Briefly, a 96-well plate was utilized to create a matrix by separately diluting the antibacterial agent and glabridin in 2-fold increments along the X-axis and Y-axis. Each well received 100 μL of bacterial suspension, resulting in a final concentration of roughly 5×10<sup>5</sup> CFU/mL. After incubating the 96-well plates at 37 °C for 16–18 h, the MIC values were determined. The potential synergistic activity was assessed using the fractional inhibitory concentration index (FICI). Synergistic, additive, irrelevant, and antagonistic activities were determined based on FICI values: FICI ≤ 0.5 for synergistic, 0.5 &lt; FICI ≤ 1.0 for additive, 1.0 &lt; FICI ≤ 2.0 for irrelevant, and FICI &gt; 2.0 for antagonistic. All experiments were conducted in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 23.0 and GraphPad Prism 9.0.0. The normal distribution was assessed using the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test, and the significance between the intervention groups and the control group was determined using Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was regarded as statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>The MICs of Antibacterial Agents and Glabridin Against MDR-AB</title><p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> indicated the MICs of routinely employed antibacterial agents and glabridin against 8 MDR-AB strains. The results demonstrated that the majority of these isolates exhibited susceptibility solely to tigecycline and colistin. Glabridin’s MICs varied from 512 to 1024 μg/mL.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The MICs (μg/mL) of Routinely Used Antibacterial Agents and Glabridin Against 8 Multidrug-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> Strains</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAZ</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRO</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GEN</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOB</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIP</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">COL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glabridin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-3945</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-3973</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-3974</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-3994</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-4028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-4060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-4079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM-4104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: MICs units: μg/mL.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IPM, Imipenem; CAZ, Ceftazidime; CRO, Ceftriaxone; SAM, Ampicillin/Sulbactam; GEN, Gentamicin; TOB, Tobramycin; CIP, Ciprofloxacin; LEV, Levofloxacin; TGC, Tigecycline; COL, Colistin.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Glabridin Was Shown to Have No Effect on the Growth of MDR-AB</title><p>The growth profile of the representative strain, BM-3945, was assessed to determine the impact of different concentrations of glabridin (1/16 MIC to 1/2 MIC) on growth. The results clearly indicated that the compounds did not have any detrimental effect on growth of the strain. (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). As a result, follow-up experiments were conducted at these doses.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effects of glabridin on MDR-AB growth at various doses.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-16-5697-g0001.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>MDR-AB Biofilm Development Was Reduced by Glabridin</title><p><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref> demonstrated the concentration-dependent inhibitory effect of Glabridin on MDR-AB biofilm formation, and the inhibitory effects varied between strains. Biofilm development was dramatically repressed when the concentration of glabridin was increased in BM-3994, BM-4060, BM-4079, BM-3973, BM-3974, BM-4028, and BM-4104. Notably in BM-4079, where the concentration of glabridin reached 1/2 MIC, biofilm formation was decreased by 68.3% when compared to the control group. However, glabridin showed minimal inhibitory effects on biofilm formation in BM-3945 at various concentrations. Glabridin revealed a statistically significant inhibitory effect against MDR-AB at 1/4 MIC and 1/2 MIC doses when the data from the eight strains was pooled (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). The 1/4 MIC of glabridin significantly reduced MDR-AB biofilm formation by 19.98% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), whereas the 1/2 MIC of glabridin significantly reduced MDR-AB biofilm development by 27.43% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Glabridin inhibited biofilm formation of MDR-AB. (<bold>A</bold>) Biofilm inhibition effect against representative strains of glabridin. (<bold>B</bold>) Pooled biofilm inhibition effect of glabridin. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-16-5697-g0002.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Glabridin Suppressed the Motility of MDR-AB</title><p>The effect of glabridin on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> motility was shown in <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. With increasing glabridin concentration, the migrating distance of MDR-AB decreased. At 1/2 MIC concentration, the migrating distance of BM-3994 fell from 33 mm to 16 mm, a 51.5% decrease, while the migrating distance of BM-4060 decreased from 18 mm to 12 mm, a 33.3% decrease (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). Glabridin’s suppressive effect achieved a statistically significant difference at 1/4 MIC and 1/2 MIC (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). MDR-AB motility was decreased by 1/4 MIC of glabridin by 44.27% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), whereas 1/2 MIC of glabridin suppressed MDR-AB motility by 50.64% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Glabridin suppressed motility of MDR-AB. (<bold>A</bold>) Motility suppression effect against representative strains of glabridin. (<bold>B</bold>) Pooled motility suppression effect of glabridin. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-16-5697-g0003.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Glabridin Effectively Inhibited the Expression of Quorum Sensing-Related Genes</title><p>Through qRT-PCR analysis, we confirmed that glabridin exerts a suppressive influence on the quorum sensing system. As shown in <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>, glabridin at 1/2 MIC was observed to decrease the expression of quorum sensing-associated genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> in BM-3994, BM4028, BM4060, BM-4079, and BM-4104. BM-3973 exhibited a moderate suppression, while no suppressive effect was observed in BM-3945 and BM-3974. When the expression data for <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> were pooled together after glabridin therapy, they showed a statistically significant reduction (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). Glabridin significantly lowered <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> expression up to 39.12% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), while <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> expression was significantly suppressed up to 25.19% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Glabridin suppressed the expression of genes involved in quorum sensing. (<bold>A</bold>) Gene expression changes in representative strains after glabridin treatment. (<bold>B</bold>) Pooled gene expression data. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-16-5697-g0004.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>There Was No Evidence of a Synergistic Interaction Between Glabridin and Antibacterial Agents</title><p>The checkerboard method was employed to determine the synergistic effects of glabridin in combination with classical antibacterial agents, namely imipenem, ceftazidime, ceftriaxone, gentamicin, tobramycin, ciprofloxacin, and levofloxacin. Unfortunately, there was no evidence of synergistic interaction between glabridin and antibacterial drugs (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=417751.doc" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, a major public health hazard, modulates its pathogenic factors including biofilm formation and motility by expressing quorum sensing genes.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Plant chemicals have been demonstrated in several studies to decrease quorum sensing, thus weakening pathogenicity and successfully controlling bacterial infections.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This study focused on the biological effect of glabridin on MDR-AB isolates.</p><p>Glabridin showed no effect on the development of clinically isolated MDR-AB below the MIC concentration, however at 1/4 and 1/2 MIC concentrations, it may inhibit the motility and biofilm forming capacities of MDR-AB in a dose-dependent manner. Some other plant extracts, such as chlorogenic acid,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> have a similar effect. However, glabridin had limited effect on the capacity of some strains to produce biofilms, which might be due to the differences in clinical strains.</p><p>We investigated the associated genes of the quorum sensing system in MDR-AB, <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, at sub-inhibitory doses of 1/2 MIC to further determine the anti-quorum sensing mechanism of glabridin. The expression of these genes had significantly decreased to varying degrees, according to our findings. However, glabridin had a lesser effect on the gene expression of certain strains. The quorum sensing circuit in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> encompasses formation of a complex between the activation protein and the autoinducer 3-OH-C12-HSL. This complex plays a pivotal role in regulating the transcription of diverse genes, including those associated with pathogenicity. By facilitating intercellular communication, this mechanism governs important biological processes within the bacterium.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Quorum quenching can be achieved by a variety of processes, the most prevalent of which is imitation of acyl-homoserine-lactones (AHLs), such as imitation of furanone.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Quorum sensing signals are degraded by lactonase and acyltransferase.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In addition, the expression of these signals is inhibited by mutations occurring in the receptor protein’s signal binding region. This effect has been observed with BuT-DADMe-ImmA and triclosan, highlighting their role in preventing signal expression.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> According to studies, the citrus flavonoid naringin’s population quenching activity is related to decreased formation of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> lactone molecules, as well as the impaired functioning of the RhlR receptor complex with C4-HSL.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Glabridin suppresses the generation of AHLs in the quorum sensing system by lowering the synthesis of abaI enzymes, which affects the formation of the AbaR-AHL complex, and may be the cause of reduced motility activity and biofilm development.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>Our study had some interesting findings, but it also had limitations. First, we only studied the biological effects of glabridin on multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, whether it has similar or unique effects on other pathogens is unclear. Second, there was no indication of a synergistic interaction between glabridin and antimicrobial agents, which may restrict its clinical use.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The population quenching of glabridin led to a notable decrease in MDR-AB’s motility, as well as its ability to form biofilms, and the downregulation of the self-inducible synthase genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>. This might provide a theoretical foundation for the unique therapeutic options of MDR-AB.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We sincerely appreciate the contributions of the reviewers to this manuscript.</p></ack><sec id="s0006"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are fully incorporated within this article. For any additional inquiries, please feel free to contact the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title><p>The Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University approved this study (Issuing No. 2022R048). The Ethics Committee waived the need for informed consent because it was an observational study primarily focused on microorganisms and without any treatments on patients, and all personal information of patients was correctly anonymised and de-identified during data collection. All experimental techniques in this work properly followed relevant laws, institutional guidelines, and the ethical principles specified in the Helsinki Declaration.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qureshi</surname>
<given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hittle</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O’Hara</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Colistin-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii: beyond carbapenem resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1295</fpage>–<lpage>1303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/civ048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25632010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4462660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>CJL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ikuta</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharara</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>; <collab>Antimicrobial Resistance C</collab>. <article-title>Global burden of bacterial antimicrobial resistance in 2019: a systematic analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>399</volume>(<issue>10325</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02724-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35065702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8841637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kalia</surname>
<given-names>VC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SKS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing inhibitors as antipathogens: biotechnological applications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biotechnol Adv</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2018.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30471318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lamin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kaksonen</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>IS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>XB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing inhibitors applications: a new prospect for mitigation of microbiologically influenced corrosion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioelectrochemistry</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>108050</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bioelechem.2022.108050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35074732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The antiviral and antimicrobial activities of licorice, a widely-used Chinese herb</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Pharm Sin B</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsb.2015.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26579460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simmler</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pauli</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phytochemistry and biological properties of glabridin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fitoterapia</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2013.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23850540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3795865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vaillancourt</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>LeBel</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pellerin</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Lagha</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grenier</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of the licorice isoflavans licoricidin and glabridin on the growth, adherence properties, and acid production of Streptococcus mutans, and assessment of their biocompatibility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics.</italic></source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics10020163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7915699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33562595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhargava</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Capalash</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Attenuation of quorum sensing-mediated virulence of Acinetobacter baumannii by Glycyrrhiza glabra flavonoids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Future Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1953</fpage>–<lpage>1968</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.15.107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26582430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Synergistic effect of the novel beta-lactamase inhibitor BLI-489 combined with imipenem or meropenem against diverse carbapenemase-producing carbapenem-resistant Enterobacterales</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Antimicrob Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1301</fpage>–<lpage>1305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkac037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35165715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Antibiotic susceptibility of Escherichia coli isolated from neonates admitted to neonatal intensive care units across China from 2015 to 2020</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Cell Infect Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1183736</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2023.1183736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37325509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10267875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gangwar</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Darokar</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Glabridin averts biofilms formation in methicillin-resistant staphylococcus aureus by modulation of the surfaceome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1779</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33071991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7534511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chlorogenic acid attenuates virulence factors and pathogenicity of Pseudomonas aeruginosa by regulating quorum sensing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>903</fpage>–<lpage>915</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-018-9482-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30421108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Swarming motility without flagellar motor switching by reversal of swimming direction in E. coli</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1042</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32670212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7326100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Navidifar</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rashno</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of sub-inhibitory concentrations of meropenem and tigecycline on the expression of genes regulating pili, efflux pumps and virulence factors involved in biofilm formation by Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S199993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31190904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6512781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fernando</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loewen</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhanel</surname>
<given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Triclosan can select for an AdeIJK-overexpressing mutant of Acinetobacter baumannii ATCC 17978 that displays reduced susceptibility to multiple antibiotics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>6424</fpage>–<lpage>6431</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.03074-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25136007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4249441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aleksic Sabo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skoric</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jovanovic-Santa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Janos</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knezevic</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Synergistic activity of bile salts and their derivatives in combination with conventional antimicrobial agents against Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Ethnopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>264</volume>:<fpage>113266</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.113266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32810621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dutta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Convergence of biofilm formation and antibiotic resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii Infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>793615</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.793615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8987773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Martin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dubern</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brun</surname>
<given-names>YV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>AbaM regulates quorum sensing, biofilm formation, and virulence in Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>203</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00635-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8088503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33495249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bouyahya</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chamkhi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Balahbib</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mechanisms, anti-quorum-sensing actions, and clinical trials of medicinal plant bioactive compounds against bacteria: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Molecules</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1484</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules27051484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35268585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8911727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmer</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of an autoinducer synthase from Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3386</fpage>–<lpage>3392</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01929-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2347373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Contreras</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quorum quenching quandary: resistance to antivirulence compounds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ISME J</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2011.122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21918575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3280137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum quenching enzymes and their application in degrading signal molecules to block quorum sensing-dependent infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>17477</fpage>–<lpage>17500</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms140917477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24065091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3794736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoang</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schweizer</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterization of Pseudomonas aeruginosa enoyl-acyl carrier protein reductase (FabI): a target for the antimicrobial triclosan and its role in acylated homoserine lactone synthesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>181</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>5489</fpage>–<lpage>5497</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.181.17.5489-5497.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10464225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC94060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schramm</surname>
<given-names>VL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cordovano</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Transition state analogues in quorum sensing and SAM recycling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Symp Ser</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nass/nrn038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2725438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18776260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vandeputte</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kiendrebeogo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rasamiravaka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The flavanone naringenin reduces the production of quorum sensing-controlled virulence factors in Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>Pt 7</issue>):<fpage>2120</fpage>–<lpage>2132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.049338-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>