<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1526</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontmicrobio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7431629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7431629.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7431629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7431629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32849322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01532</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antimicrobial Peptide Cec4 Eradicates the Bacteria of Clinical Carbapenem-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Biofilm</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="W">Weiwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>†</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/913841/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhaoying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>†</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/951282/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names initials="C">Chengju</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names initials="G">Guo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fei</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/948233/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names initials="S">Shan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names initials="J">Jian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/886981/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c002"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Immune Cells and Antibody Engineering Research Center of Guizhou Province, Guizhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Environmental Pollution Monitoring and Disease Control, Ministry of Education, Guizhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>The Key and Characteristic Laboratory of Modern Pathogen Biology, Basic Medical College, Guizhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>The Center for Clinical Laboratories, The Affiliated Hospital of Guizhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Luis Cláudio Nascimento da Silva, Universidade Ceuma, Brazil</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Cesar de la Fuente-Nunez, University of Pennsylvania, United States; Maria Bagattini, University of Naples Federico II, Italy; Lucas Pinheiro Dias, Federal University of Ceará, Brazil</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jian Peng, <email>jianpeng@gmc.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Jianwei Wu, <email>wjw@gmc.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p><sup>†</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>This article was submitted to Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">350391</issue-id><elocation-id>1532</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>08</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>08</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-03-28 21:25:14.707"><day>28</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2020 Liu, Wu, Mao, Guo, Zeng, Fei, Wan, Peng and Wu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu, Wu, Mao, Guo, Zeng, Fei, Wan, Peng and Wu</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fmicb-11-01532.pdf"/><abstract><p>The drug resistance rate of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> increases year on year, and the drugs available for the treatment of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (CRAB) infection are extremely limited. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, which forms biofilms, protects itself by secreting substrates such as exopolysaccharides, allowing it to survive under adverse conditions and increasing drug resistance. Antimicrobial peptides are small molecular peptides with broad-spectrum antibacterial activity and immunomodulatory function. Previous studies have shown that the antimicrobial peptide Cec4 has a strong effect on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, but the antibacterial and biofilm inhibition of this antimicrobial peptide on clinical carbapenem resistance <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is not thoroughly understood. In this study, it was indicated that most of the 200 strains of CRAB were susceptible to Cec4 with a MIC of 4 μg/ml. Cec4 has a strong inhibitory and eradication effect on the CRAB biofilm; the minimum biofilm inhibition concentration (MBIC) was 64–128 μg/ml, and the minimum biofilm eradication concentration (MBEC) was 256–512 μg/ml. It was observed that Cec4 disrupted the structure of the biofilm using scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM). A comparative transcriptome analysis of the effects of the antimicrobial peptide Cec4 on CRAB biofilm, identified 185 differentially expressed genes, including membrane proteins, bacterial resistance genes, and pilus-related genes. The results show that multiple metabolic pathways, two-component regulation systems, quorum sensing, and antibiotic synthesis-related pathways in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilms were affected after Cec4 treatment. In conclusion, Cec4 may represent a new choice for the prevention and treatment of clinical infections, and may also provide a theoretical basis for the development of antimicrobial peptide drugs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>antimicrobial peptide</kwd><kwd>Cec4</kwd><kwd>CRAB</kwd><kwd>biofilm</kwd><kwd>transcriptome</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Natural Science Foundation of Guizhou Province<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100005329</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">Guizhou Science and Technology Department<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100004001</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="56"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="0"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is a non-fermenting Gram-negative bacterium, and infections often occur in patients with poor immunity, especially in patients in intensive care units or in patients undergoing invasive surgery (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Handal et al., 2017</xref>). It can cause hospital-acquired pneumonia, especially ventilator-associated pneumonia, bacteremia, urinary tract infection, secondary meningitis, etc., with a high mortality rate (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Bentancor et al., 2012</xref>). At the same time, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is prone to drug resistance and is even resistant to carbapenem antibiotics, including imipenem and meropenem (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Maragakis and Perl, 2008</xref>). At present, most antibiotics, except tigecycline and polymyxin, do not affect it (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dafopoulou et al., 2019</xref>). Although tigecycline has a broad antibacterial spectrum and good antibacterial activity, the blood concentration is low, only 0.7–0.8 mg/L (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Cai and Wang, 2011</xref>). Therefore, it remains controversial to use tigecycline to treat blood-related infections (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Akalay et al., 2020</xref>); moreover, polymyxin has greater renal and neurotoxicity, limiting its use (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Spapen et al., 2011</xref>). By organism, the highest overall rates of multidrug resistance reported in a study were among <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates, for which 44% of isolates collected globally were multidrug-resistant bacteria. Additionally, the treatment options for infections caused by such organisms are limited, which deserves attention (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Giammanco et al., 2017</xref>). Recently, the World Health Organization (WHO) classified carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (CRAB) as the first in the list of key pathogens for the development of new antibiotics (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">O’Shea, 2012</xref>).</p><p>When <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> forms biofilms, its resistance increases rapidly (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Eze et al., 2018</xref>). Biofilms are composed of bacteria that irreversibly adhere to the surface of living or non-living organisms and are surrounded by a secreted matrix of extracellular polysaccharide, protein, and DNA. Once the special structure forms, the bacteria express completely different genes from planktonic bacteria, with significant differences in morphology, physical and chemical properties, and antibiotic susceptibility (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Jamal et al., 2018</xref>). The ability to form biofilms on abiotic surfaces under adverse conditions makes the biofilm phenotype an important virulence factor for <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infection (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Eze et al., 2018</xref>). At the same time, it is beneficial for bacteria to survive on nutritionally limited abiotic surfaces and stressful environmental conditions (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Alvarez-Fraga et al., 2016</xref>). Bacterial biofilms cause at least 65% of human infections, particularly implantable device-related infections and chronic disease infections (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Williams and Costerton, 2012</xref>). Therefore, there is an urgent need for drugs that effectively treat biofilm-associated infections. At present, it has been reported that some natural product extracts and compounds can treat bacterial biofilms. Water extract of <italic toggle="yes">Galla chinensis</italic> suppressed biofilm and extracellular matrix formation of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2019</xref>). <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al. (2014)</xref> reported the effects of two natural compounds on methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA). Ursolic acid can inhibit the formation of biofilms, while resveratrol combined with vancomycin can inhibit pre-formed mature biofilms. Silver nanoparticles do not affect the growth of planktonic <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> but can reduce the production of biofilms at a concentration of 50 μg/ml (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2019</xref>). However, in many cases, these anti-biofilm active ingredients are not sufficient enough to completely inhibit or eliminate bacterial biofilms and lack broad-spectrum anti-biofilm efficacy.</p><p>Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) have a broad antibacterial spectrum and a wide range of sources, and have unique antibacterial mechanisms, making them less prone to drug resistance. It is generally believed that AMPs exert their microbicidal activity mainly through targeting the cell membrane by penetration and cell lysis activities (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Aisenbrey et al., 2019</xref>). The MIC of human-derived cationic peptide LL-37 and its truncated fragments against drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is 16–32 μg/ml, and it inhibits the formation of biofilms (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2013</xref>). The peptide IDR-1018 exhibits broad-spectrum anti-biofilm activity against a variety of hospital pathogens, including <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumonia</italic> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">de la Fuente-Nunez et al., 2014</xref>). Therefore, antimicrobial peptides are expected to become new drugs for the treatment of bacterial biofilm and associated infections (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Neshani et al., 2020</xref>). Our previous study found that the peptide Cec4 had a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 4 μg/ml against an <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> reference strain (ATCC19606), which is superior to the reported similar cecropin antimicrobial peptides Cec1, cecropin A and fusion peptide CA. (1–8) M (1–18) (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Saugar et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Batoni et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Long et al., 2017</xref>). It was confirmed in the previous report that the semi-inhibitory concentration of Cec4 on the formation of standard <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilms (to inhibit the formation of biofilm by 50%) is about 4 μg/ml; this peptide is non-hemolytic on human red blood cells at high concentrations (100 × MIC) (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2019</xref>). However, whether the antimicrobial peptide Cec4 can inhibit CRAB and its biofilm to the same extent as with the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (ATCC19606), remains elusive. Therefore, 200 strains of clinical CRAB were collected, and their ability to form biofilms was tested. Furthermore, the susceptibility and biofilm formation of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates to the antimicrobial peptide Cec4 were evaluated, and the molecular mechanism of Cec4 on bacterial biofilm was analyzed by transcriptome analysis. In conclusion, this study is expected to provide new ideas for the treatment of clinical infections and presents a theoretical basis for research and development into new antibiotics.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2.SS1"><title>Synthesis and Preparation of Peptides</title><p>Antimicrobial peptide Cec4 (GWLKKIGKKIERVGQNTRD ATIQAIGVAQQAANVAATLKGK) was synthesized by Gil Biochemical Co., Ltd., Shanghai. Using solid-phase chemical synthesis, the purity (HPLC) &gt; 97% and the mass of the peptide determined by spectrometry. It was dissolved to 10 mg/ml with distilled deionized H<sub>2</sub>O (ddH<sub>2</sub>O) and stored at −80°C for further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS2"><title>Bacterial Isolates and Growth Conditions</title><p>From October 2017 to December 2018, 200 isolates of CRAB from clinical samples of patients from the affiliated hospital of Guizhou Medical University were collected and duplicate samples from the same patient were excluded. All of them come from sputum, blood, urine and so on. The collection and use of clinically isolated strains were approved by the Institutional review board (IRB) of Guizhou Medical University, China. The studies involving human participants were reviewed and approved by Guizhou Medical University and the affiliation of the ethics committee. The patients provided written informed consent to participate in this study. Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of these strains to nine antibiotics including amikacin, ertapenem, imipenem, meropenem, ceftazidime, ciprofloxacin, ceftriaxone, levofloxacin, and cefepime were assessed on MicroScan WalkAway 40-SI Analyzer (SIEMENS, Germany), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Resistance to cefotaxime was assessed using the standard disc diffusion method (Oxoid, Hampshire, United Kingdom). Interpretive breakpoints for susceptible, intermediate, and resistant were consistent with Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute guidelines (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Humphries et al., 2018</xref>). In order to ensure the accuracy of bacterial identification, the 16<italic toggle="yes">SrRNA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> genes of all strains were amplified, and PCR products were sequenced and analyzed. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (ATCC19606) is a biofilm-forming positive strain. <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC25922 and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC27853 were used as quality control bacteria. The above strains are stored in the Pathogen Biology Laboratory of Guizhou Medical University. Strains were grown on Mueller-Hinton Broth (MHB), Typic Soy Broth (TSB) or Luria-Bertani (LB) agar plates and incubated at 37°C.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS3"><title>Detecting the Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) Value</title><p>According to a previous study (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Wiegand et al., 2008</xref>), the MIC of Cec4 peptide against 200 strains of CRAB was assessed using the broth microdilution assay in MHB. After adding different concentrations of antimicrobial peptide Cec4, the 96-well plate was placed in a constant temperature incubator at 37°C. After incubation for 24 h, it was observed. The MIC was defined as the lowest drug concentration that can inhibit bacterial growth by visual evaluation.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS4"><title>Quantitative Biofilm Formation Assay</title><p>According to the crystal violet staining method of a previous study (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">O’Toole, 2011</xref>), the 96-well tissue culture plate method was utilized for a quantitative evaluation of biofilm formation by 200 strains of CRAB. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC19606 was used as the positive control, and TSB medium without bacteria was used as the negative control. Absorbance at 570 nm (OD570) was measured for each well to obtain quantitative data on biofilm formation as described previously (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Badmasti et al., 2015</xref>). The mean ± standard deviation of the OD value of the negative control was defined as ODc. Based on the OD value, the strains were divided into the following four groups: the OD value of the test strain was compared with ODc, and OD<sub>570</sub> ≤ ODc was negative for biofilm formation (−); ODc &lt; OD<sub>570</sub> ≤ 2 × ODc indicates weak biofilm formation (+); 2 × ODc &lt; OD570 ≤ 4 × ODc indicates moderate biofilm formation (++); 4 × ODc &lt; OD570 indicates strong biofilm formation (+++).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS5"><title>Detection of the Minimum Biofilm Inhibition Concentration (MBIC) and Minimum Biofilm Eradication Concentration (MBEC)</title><p>In order to detect the inhibitory effect of Cec4 peptide on the growth of biofilms, a method described in the literature was used with modifications (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abouelhassan et al., 2017</xref>). Briefly, 200 μl of bacterial cells (1 × 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/ml) of 10 strains (CRAB 3, 4, 53, 55, 78, 117, 120, 128, 130, 136) with the strongest biofilm formation ability was inoculated in a polyethylene 96-well plate; TSB culture medium containing no bacteria was used as the blank control, and the plate was incubated at 37°C for 24 h. The culture medium was subsequently removed, and wells were carefully washed with PBS three times to remove planktonic bacteria. And then, 200 μl of TSB culture medium containing Cec4 in serial doubling dilutions was added to each well. TSB medium without an antimicrobial peptide was used as a negative control, and plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 h. If OD600 &lt; 0.1, there was no bacterial growth, and the lowest concentration without bacterial growth at this time point was recorded; this is the MBIC. Then, cells and peptide in the 96-well cell culture plate were washed with PBS, and 200 μl of TSB culture medium was added to each well. The plate was incubated at 37°C for 24 h to re-grow the surviving biofilm bacteria. An OD600 &lt; 0.1 indicated that there was no bacterial growth. The lowest concentration at which no bacterial growth was recorded is the MBEC. In order to evaluate the eradication efficiency of Cec4 on the biofilm, the culture in the wells was removed and washed with PBS to remove non-adherent cells. The biofilm was quantified by the aforementioned method, and calculated using the equation <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="INEQ7"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mpadded width="+2.8pt"><mml:mn>570</mml:mn></mml:mpadded><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mpadded width="+2.8pt"><mml:mi>of</mml:mi></mml:mpadded><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mpadded width="+2.8pt"><mml:mi>the</mml:mi></mml:mpadded><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mi>test</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mpadded width="+2.8pt"><mml:mn>570</mml:mn></mml:mpadded><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mpadded width="+2.8pt"><mml:mi>of</mml:mi></mml:mpadded><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mi>non</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo rspace="5.3pt">-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mpadded width="+2.8pt"><mml:mi>treated</mml:mi></mml:mpadded><mml:mo>⁢</mml:mo><mml:mi>control</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo rspace="5.8pt">×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS6"><title>Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM)</title><p>According to a previous report (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Ramalingam and Lee, 2018</xref>), the biofilm of CRAB 55 was cultured <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> in a 6-well plate, and a sterile polylysine-treated cover glass and a sterile medical catheter cut at a length of 1 cm were added in advance as a biofilm growth carrier. Samples were processed by gradient dehydration with 20, 50, 70, 90, and 100% ethanol/tert-butanol mixture. The samples were dried in a critical point dryer and placed in a high vacuum evaporator, then sprayed gold with an ion sprayer and observed using a scanning electron microscope (Hitachi S-3400).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS7"><title>Confocal Laser Scanning Microscope Analysis</title><p>Confocal laser scanning microscopy analysis was carried out according to a previous study (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Bortolin et al., 2016</xref>). A sterile polylysine-treated cover glass was used as the carrier, and the biofilm of CRAB 55 was cultivated according to the method of the previous step. Then, 1 mM SYTO9 and 10 mM propidium iodide (PI) were added and incubated for 15 min in the dark. An Olympus Fluoview FV1000 confocal microscope (Olympus, Markham, ON, Canada) was used to obtain a fluorescence image. The bottom of the biofilm to the surface was scanned layer by layer along the <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-axis to record the earliest and last disappearance of fluorescence, and the corresponding biofilm thickness was calculated accordingly; each layer was 1 μm. The resulting stacks of images were quantified using an image processing package (ImageJ, United States) and subsequently rendered into three-dimensional mode using image analysis software (Imaris 7.2.3, Bitplane, Switzerland).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS8"><title>Motility Assays</title><p>As described by a previous study (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">McQueary and Actis, 2011</xref>), twitching plates were made with 10 g/l tryptone, 5 g/l yeast extract and 5 g/l NaCl and 1% Eiken agar, with different concentrations of Cec4 (or none). A single colony of CRAB 55 was picked from a normal LB agar (1.5%, wt/vol) plate and inoculated vertically to the bottom of the plate, so that it could grow at the intersection of the bottom of the agar layer and the culture dish. The plate was incubated at 37°C for 24 h, and motility was evaluated by observing the formation of a transparent halo around the growing colonies and measuring the diameter. Twitching motility assays were conducted on at least three separate occasions. As described in a previous study (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Harding et al., 2013</xref>), surface motility plates are comprised of 5 g/l tryptone, 2.5 g/l NaCl and 0.35% Eiken agar, with different concentrations of Cec4 or not. The bacteria were cultured to the logarithmic phase, then a 2 μl of aliquot of an overnight culture was stabbed into the surface of the center of the plate, and motility was measured after incubating the plate at 37°C for 24 h. Surface-associated motility assays were conducted on at least three separate occasions.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS9"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR</title><p>According to a previous study (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2015</xref>), biofilm formation of CRAB 55 was conducted as described above, and after the biofilm had been treated with Cec4 or not, it was scraped from the plate with a cell spatula. Total RNA was extracted using Trizol. RNA was quantified and quality was assessed using a NanoDrop spectrophotometer (ND-2000, Thermo Scientific, Loughborough, United Kingdom), and the final RNA concentration was adjusted to 1 ng/μl. cDNA was synthesized in a 20 μl reaction mixture using a PrimeScript RT reagent Kit with gDNA Eraser. According to the SYBR Premix Ex Taq TM Kit (Takara, Dalian, China) protocol, the reactions were run on an ABI7300 real-time PCR system using a 20 μl reaction volume. Gene expression levels were normalized to the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> 16<italic toggle="yes">S rRNA</italic>. Target genes included <italic toggle="yes">CsuE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BfmR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BfmS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bap</italic>. The primers were designed with reference to the GenBank sequences. The primer sequences are shown in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS10"><title>RNA-Seq</title><sec id="S2.SS10.SSS1"><title>RNA Isolation, Library Construction and Sequencing</title><p>The four strains CRAB 4, 55, 78, and 117 with the strong biofilm-forming ability and similar characteristics were selected as four biological replicates. The logarithmic growth culture was washed twice in sterile PBS and diluted to 10<sup>6</sup> cells/ml in TSB. Then, 4 ml of the culture was added to a flat-bottomed 6-well plate (Corning, United States) and incubated at 37°C for 24 h to form a biofilm. Samples were collected as a control group (Control 1, Control 2, Control 3 and Control 4). For the Cec4 treatment group (ABF1, ABF2, ABF3, and ABF4), after forming mature biofilms, non-adherent cells were removed, and TSB culture solution containing 4 × MIC (16 μg/ml) of Cec4 was added. Biofilm samples were collected 24 h later.</p><p>The total RNA of these samples was extracted using Trizol reagent (Sigma-Aldrich, United States) according to the previously described method. The quality and quantity were determined by a NanoPhotometer spectrophotometer (IMPLEN, CA, United States) and an Agilent 2100 bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, CA, United States). RNA-seq library construction and RNA sequencing were performed by the Novogene Corporation (Beijing, China). Sequence reads were deposited at the National Center for Biotechnology Information under BioProject <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="PRJNA607078">PRJNA607078</ext-link> as <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120700">SAMN14120700</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120701">SAMN14120701</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120702">SAMN14120702</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120703">SAMN14120703</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120704">SAMN14120704</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120705">SAMN14120705</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120706">SAMN14120706</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120707">SAMN14120707</ext-link><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="footnote1">1</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS10.SSS2"><title>Identification of Differentially Expressed Genes and Annotation</title><p>Raw reads were generated from the image data and stored as FASTQ format. Raw data were filtered to remove adaptor contaminated and low-quality sequences and to obtain clean reads. Genomic mapping of the filtered sequence was performed using Bowtie2-2.2.3 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Langmead and Salzberg, 2012</xref>). The reference genome and gene model annotation file of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> AB030 was downloaded from GenBank (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NZ_CP009257.1">NZ_CP009257.1</ext-link>). HTSeq v0.6.1 was used to count the read numbers mapped to each gene. The expected number of fragments per kilobase of transcript sequence per million base pairs sequenced (FPKM) of each gene was calculated based on the length of the gene and reads count mapped to this gene (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell et al., 2012</xref>). Differential expression analysis of two groups (four biological replicates per group) was performed using the DEGSeq R package (??) (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Anders and Huber, 2012</xref>). The resulting <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values were adjusted using the Benjamini and Hochberg approach for controlling the false discovery rate. Genes with a corrected <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 and log<sub>2</sub>(Fold change)&gt;1 found by DEGSeq were assigned as differentially expressed. Gene ontology (GO) enrichment analysis of differentially expressed genes was implemented by the GOseq R package. The GO enrichment analysis of differentially expressed genes was achieved by GOseq software, and KOBAS software was used to test the statistical enrichment of differentially expressed genes in KEGG pathways (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Kanehisa et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Young et al., 2010</xref>). Significantly enriched KEGG pathways and GO terms were identified by a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 using Fisher’s exact test and a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.01 in the hypergeometric distribution, respectively, and adjusted by false discovery rates (FDR) (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Rivals et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Boca and Leek, 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS10.SSS3"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism software version 6.0 (Graph Pad Software, San Diego, CA, United States) and Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. Data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD). All experiments were performed in triplicate. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3.SS1"><title>Cec4 Inhibits Clinical Resistant Bacteria</title><p>It was reported that large differences have been shown between <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains. In previous studies, Cec4 showed outstanding antibacterial activity against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Its MIC against standard <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>(ATCC19606)was 4 μg/ml. In order to study its antibacterial effect on clinical CRAB, the susceptibility of CRAB to Cec4 was tested. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>, 98.5% of the 200 isolates of CRAB were susceptive to the peptide Cec4 with a MIC ≤ 4 μg/ml. Only 1.5% of the strains had MIC &gt; 4 μg/ml, which were 8 and 16 μg/ml, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS2">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). Therefore, the peptide Cec4 has great antibacterial effects on the majority of clinical carbapenem resistant bacteria.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Cec4 inhibits clinical resistant bacteria and biofilms. <bold>(A)</bold> Distribution of MIC value of Cec4 against 200 CRAB clinical isolates (μg/mL). <bold>(B)</bold> Quantification of biofilm formation in 200 CRAB clinical isolates. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC19606 was used as a positive control. Experiments were performed in triplicate and each bar represents the mean ± standard deviation. <bold>(C)</bold> The effects of Cec4 on mature biofilms of CRAB. The adherent biofilm was stained by crystal violet, and then the dye was extracted with ethanol, measured at a 570-nm absorbance, and presented as percentage of biofilm remains compared to untreated wells (0 μg/mL). All experiments were done in triplicate for statistical significance. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmicb-11-01532-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS2"><title>The Biofilm Formation Ability of CRAB Strains</title><p>Bacteria in the form of biofilms have increased resistance to antibacterial drugs, external environmental pressures, and the host’s immune system, which has brought great challenges to clinical treatment. Based on crystal violet staining, the ability of 200 isolates of CRAB to form biofilms was studied. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>, the OD570 value of the positive control strain ATCC19606 in the experimental plate was 1.191 ± 0.012, and the negative control was 0.111 ± 0.005. The OD570 value of the 200 resistant bacteria was between 0.1 and 1.9 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS2">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). All 200 strains of CRAB were able to form biofilms. Among them, 53 strains (26.5%) had strong biofilm formation ability, 120 strains (60%) were moderate and 27 strains (13.5%) were weak.</p></sec><sec id="S3.SS3"><title>Cec4 Inhibits and Eradicates Biofilm of CRAB Strains</title><p>After bacteria formed the biofilm, their resistance to drugs was greatly enhanced. Our previous studies have demonstrated that antimicrobial peptide Cec4 at 0.5 μg / mL can inhibit the formation of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilm (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2019</xref>). Regarding biofilm formation ability, the 10 strongest strains were selected to evaluate the ability of Cec4 to inhibit and eradicate their biofilm. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS2">Supplementary Table S2</xref>, the antimicrobial peptide Cec4 can inhibit the biofilm of the strains with the strongest CRAB biofilm formation ability at 64–128 μg/ml, and can eradicate the biofilm at 256–512 μg/ml. In order to determine the effect of Cec4 on the removal of biofilms, after the formation of mature biofilms, different concentrations of Cec4 were added to the culture for 24 h. The crystal violet staining method was used to measure the absorbance at 570 nm to calculate the clearance rate of different concentrations of the peptide on mature biofilms. The results showed that 1 × MIC (4 μg/ml) could clear more than 20% of mature biofilms, with MBEC<sub>50</sub> of 16 μg/ml and MBEC<sub>80</sub> of 128 μg/ml (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S3.SS4"><title>Cec4 Destroys the Structure of Biofilms</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> colonizes the surface of medical equipment and indwelling medical devices (including urinary catheters) to form biofilms, leading to long-term and recurrent infections in patients (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2019</xref>). Coverslips and urinary catheters were used as carriers to evaluate the ability of Cec4 to remove the biofilms formed on them. Clinical CRAB forms biofilm on coverslips and catheters, and the effects of Cec4 on the biofilm are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. After 24 h in culture, for the untreated group, the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> that adhered to the coverslip mostly was bacilliform; the biofilm was dense and the cell membrane was intact, forming a typical “mushroom cloud” three-dimensional structure. After treatment with Cec4 at a concentration of 1 × MIC (4 μg/ml), the biofilm structure was destroyed, and the cells were loosely distributed, and some cell surfaces appeared to be attacked. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> adhered to the catheter was mostly spherical and formed a thick biofilm, covered with extracellular substrates. After treatment with Cec4 (4 μg/ml), the biofilm structure was destroyed. Moreover, small vesicles appeared on the surface of the cell membrane, and even the collapse and disintegration of cells were observed.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural images of CRAB biofilm on sterile coverslip and catheters after treated with Cec4. <bold>(A)</bold> Coverslip without treatment, <bold>(B)</bold> Coverslip after Cec4 treatment, <bold>(C)</bold> catheter without treatment, and <bold>(D)</bold> catheter after Cec4 treatment. The selected images are the best representation of biofilms on coverslips and catheters.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmicb-11-01532-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>To better understand the destructive effect of Cec4 on the biofilm, the fluorescent dyes SYTO<sup>®</sup>9 and propidium iodide were used to characterize bacteria in different states. Under the laser confocal scanning microscope, a large number of biofilm bacteria were aggregated into the control group, mainly living bacteria with green fluorescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). The total biomass was about 9 × 10<sup>6</sup> μm<sup>3</sup> and the average biofilm thickness was &gt; 16 μm. The number of dead bacteria increased gradually after treated with Cec4 (4 μg/ml) for 2 h. It was found that many bacteria in the visual field emitted red fluorescence. The total biomass was about 4 × 10<sup>6</sup> μm<sup>3</sup>, and the thickness of the biofilm was reduced to 7 μm. Therefore, the CLSM results are consistent with the SEM observations, showing that Cec4 has a strong damaging effect on CRAB strain biofilm.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>The CRAB biofilm was removed effectively with Cec4. Confocal microscopy of CRAB biofilm without treatment <bold>(A)</bold> and after treatment with Cec4 <bold>(B)</bold>. The three-dimensional reconstruction of CRAB biofilm without treatment <bold>(C)</bold> and after treatment with Cec4 <bold>(D)</bold>. The total biomass volume <bold>(E)</bold> and thickness <bold>(F)</bold> of biofilm were calculated based on the fluorescence intensity. The results were averaged from three randomly selected positions of each sample. Data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD). *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmicb-11-01532-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS5"><title>Cec4 Decreases Twitching Motility and Surface-Associated Motility in CRAB</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> adheres to the surface of the object through pili, which is the initial stage of biofilm formation. Twitching motility is a unique form of movement mediated by type IV pili. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> relies on the contraction and extension of type IV pili on the surface of the Petri dish, with the inoculation point as the center, and spreads around and forms interstitial colony expansion halo. We observed that, after incubation at 37°C overnight, two types of the colony grew on the Petri plate. There were colonies on the surface of the agar around the inoculation point (top colony) and a visible halo of bacteria that had twitched across the plate between the bottom of the agar and the plate (interstitial colony) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). Adding different concentrations of Cec4 decreased twitching motility. As the concentration of Cec4 increased, the twitching motility of bacteria decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> can also move on the surface of a semi-solid medium, forming round colonies at the inoculation site of the moving plate (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS2">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). The average colony diameter of the group with Cec4 was lower than that of the control group, which was consistent with the experimental results on twitching motility (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>The motility of CRAB and biofilm involved genes were affected after treated with Cec4. Twitching motility <bold>(A)</bold> and surface-associated motility <bold>(B)</bold> of CRAB were quantitated from three separate experiments at 37°C. Error bars represent standard deviation of the mean. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; ****<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001. <bold>(C)</bold> Effect of Cec4 on the expression levels of biofilm involved genes in CRAB strains. Error bars represent the standard deviations. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmicb-11-01532-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS6"><title>Cec4 Alters the Expression of Biofilm-Related Genes</title><p>Many studies have shown that several genes of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> are involved in the formation of biofilms and adhesion to abiotic surfaces. In order to understand the effect of Cec4 on these genes, the RNA of biofilm bacteria under different conditions was extracted. Next, the effect of Cec4 on the expression of <italic toggle="yes">CsuE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BfmR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BfmS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bap</italic> related to biofilm formation was evaluated using qRT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>). The results show that, compared with the control group, the pilus-related gene <italic toggle="yes">CsuE</italic> was down-regulated 1.8-fold; the two-component regulatory system genes <italic toggle="yes">BfmR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BfmS</italic> were down-regulated 3.6-fold and 3.9-fold, respectively; the quorum-sensing regulatory gene <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> was down-regulated 6.3-fold, and the biofilm-related gene <italic toggle="yes">Bap</italic> was down-regulated 2.6-fold. These results suggest that Cec4 inhibited the expression of these genes involved in biofilm formation.</p></sec><sec id="S3.SS7"><title>Transcriptional Stress Response of CRAB Biofilm to Cec4</title><p>The RNA sequencing results revealed the differences in gene expression between ABF and control. There were 3403 genes co-expressed in these two samples; 40 genes were specificity expressed in ABF, and 6 genes were specificity expressed in control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>). The volcano plots of the differentially expressed genes (DEGs) show that 185 genes were differentially expressed after Cec4 treatment, including 132 genes that were up-regulated (red) and 53 down-regulated genes (green) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Venn diagram analysis of gene expression. The number in each circle represents the total number of genes that are expressed in each sample, and the overlapping part of circles indicates that the gene is co-expressed in both samples. <bold>(B)</bold> The volcano plots of the differentially expressed genes. Significantly differentially expressed genes were treated with red dots (up-regulated) or green dots (down-regulated). The abscissa represents fold change, and the ordinate represents statistical significance.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmicb-11-01532-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS8"><title>Analysis of Differential Gene Expression</title><p>Transcriptome analysis revealed that the differential genes mainly included membrane protein-related genes, drug-resistant genes and pilus-related genes (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The expression of the amino acid ABC transporter permease, ATP-binding proteins (IX87_RS02655, IX87_RS02660, and artP) in the ABC transport system was down-regulated 1.68-fold, 1.61-fold, and 1.66-fold; the MFS transporter (IX87_RS20020) was down-regulated 2.96-fold, and the EamA family transporter (IX87_RS12100) expression was down-regulated 2.29-fold (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The expression of MBL fold metallo-hydrolase (IX87_RS19070) was down-regulated about 3-fold, ADC family cephalosporin-hydrolyzing class C beta-lactamase (IX87_RS08365) was down-regulated 1.27-fold; adeC/adeK/oprM family multidrug efflux complex outer membrane factor (IX87_RS16845) expression was up-regulated 1.37-fold (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The protein CsuA (IX87_RS06910) was down-regulated 1.51-fold, while the expression of pili assembly chaperone (IX87_RS02530) and type 4 fimbria biogenesis proteins FimT (IX87_RS10830) was up-regulated 1.8 and 1.42-fold (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>The genes up-regulated or down-regulated response to Cec4.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene name</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Description</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>log <sup>2</sup> Fold_change</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Corrected <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Membrane protein</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS20020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MFS transporter</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87 × 10<sup>–4</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS02655</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">amino acid ABC transporter permease</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86 × 10<sup>–3</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">artP</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">amino acid ABC transporter ATP-binding protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30 × 10<sup>–2</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS02660</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">amino acid ABC transporter permease</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.77 × 10<sup>–3</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS12100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EamA family transporter</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85 × 10<sup>–4</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Bacterial resistance</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS19070</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBL fold metallo-hydrolase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11 × 10<sup>–8</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS08365</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADC family cephalosporin-hydrolyzing class C beta-lactamase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86 × 10<sup>–2</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS16845</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adeC/adeK/oprM family multidrug efflux complex outer membrane factor</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90 × 10<sup>–2</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pili</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS06910</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">protein CsuA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.64 × 10<sup>–3</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS02530</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pili assembly chaperone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 × 10<sup>–2</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX87_RS10830</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">type 4 fimbrial biogenesis protein FimT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63 × 10<sup>–2</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S3.SS9"><title>Enrichment Analysis of GO and KEGG Pathways</title><p>To further understand the function of the DEGs underlying the effect of low concentrations of Cec4 on CRAB biofilms, GO enrichment analysis was performed with the DEGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>). Based on sequence homology, DEGs were assigned to one or more GO terms and categorized into three main categories of GO function (biological process, molecular function, and cellular component). It is noteworthy that in the category of biological process, protein folding, extracellular polysaccharide biosynthetic process, cellular polysaccharide metabolic process, secondary metabolite biosynthetic process, protein catabolic process, dsRNA transport and regulation of DNA-templated transcription are significantly enriched. Outer membrane-bounded periplasmic space and pilus are significantly enriched in the cellular component category. Enzyme activity and nucleic acid transmembrane transporter activity are enriched in the molecular function category.</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Gene Ontology (GO) analysis of differentially expressed genes. <bold>(B)</bold> Statistical enrichment of differentially expressed genes in KEGG pathways.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmicb-11-01532-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>By enrichment analysis, the main KEGG metabolic pathways involved in DEGs are carbon metabolism, oxidative phosphorylation, the two-component system, ABC transporters, nucleotide excision repair, biosynthesis of antibiotics, quorum sensing, microbial metabolism in diverse environments, and β-lactam resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>). It is indicated that Cec4 affected the energy metabolism of biofilm bacteria and the bacteria two-component system. By interfering with the expression of type IV pili assembly protein in the two-component system, bacterial motility function was affected. In addition, the β-lactam antibiotics are the most widely used group of antibiotics, which exert their effect by interfering with the structural cross-linking of peptidoglycans in bacterial cell walls. Bacterial resistance to β-lactam antibiotics can be achieved by producing inactivating enzymes called β-lactamases, altering the β-lactam targets of penicillin-binding proteins (PBPs), and so on. After Cec4 treatment, genes in the β-lactam resistance pathway were down-regulated. More importantly, quorum sensing (QS) allows bacteria to share information about cell density and adjust gene expression accordingly, and controls including virulence, motility, sporulation and biofilm formation. Therefore, the transcriptome results indicate that Cec4 mainly affected the expression of energy metabolism and quorum sensing signaling pathway genes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p>It has been reported that after bacteria form a biofilm, the MIC value for antibiotics can be increased by 1000 times or more (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Alhede et al., 2011</xref>). The antimicrobial peptide can down-regulate quorum sensing, prevent the initial adhesion of bacteria to the surface, target bacteria before they form a biofilm, kill bacteria embedded in biofilms, or destroy mature biofilms to achieve the effect of inhibiting or eradicating biofilms (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Batoni et al., 2016</xref>). Previous experiments have shown that Cec4 has the best antibacterial effect on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, and it has very low hemolysis to human red blood cells even in high concentrations (600 μg/mL) (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2019</xref>). Our experiment results also indicated that Cec4 had little cytotoxic effect on the two human cell lines HepG2 and Hela (data not shown). In this study, 200 isolates of CRAB from different clinical patients were collected to detect their biofilm formation ability and to evaluate the inhibitory effect of Cec4 on biofilms. Screening at a concentration of 4 μg/ml revealed that 98.5% of the strains were susceptive to Cec4. Thus, Cec4 has a strong inhibitory activity against standard <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and can also inhibit clinical CRAB. The crystal violet staining method showed that the collected clinical CRAB could form biofilms, and 26.5% of the strains could strongly form a biofilm. Cec4 eradicated more than 20% of mature biofilms at a concentration of 4 μg/ml, and the MBEC<sub>50</sub> was 16 μg/ml. When treated with Cec4 with a concentration of 256–512 μg/ml, the biofilm was completely eradicated. The SEM results indicated that the biofilm formed on the medical silicone catheter was thick, with extracellular polysaccharides and other substrates that completely covered the cells. After Cec4 was treated for 2 h, the biofilm was easily detached, and the cells were damaged or collapsed. The CLSM results further quantified the thickness and volume of the biofilms. The results show that, after 24 h, the biofilm that formed on the coverslips was thick and dense, and mainly composed of live bacteria with a thickness of 10–20 μm. After treatment with Cec4, the number of dead bacteria gradually increased, and the biofilm became significantly thinner. Therefore, these results indicate that Cec4 has a good eradication ability on biofilm forming of clinical CRAB.</p><p>It has been reported that <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> adheres to the surface of living or non-living organisms by pili participating in the initial stage of biofilm formation, and thereby forming a biofilm. The results show that Cec4 decreased pili-mediated motility in a concentration dependent manner. Under the action of Cec4 with a sub-inhibitory concentration (2 μg/ml), motility was also suppressed, and no transparent halo was formed. It has been reported that peptide 1037 inhibited the swimming of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14, but stimulated twitching motility (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">de la Fuente-Nunez et al., 2012</xref>). The expression of the CsuA/BABCDE chaperone complex is necessary for the assembly and production of pili associated with abiotic surface adhesion, while the Csu operon is controlled by a two-component system consisting of a BfmS-encoded sensor kinase and a BfmR-encoded response regulator. Insertion inactivation of BfmR results in the loss of expression of the CsuA/BABCDE operon, and impaired pilus production and biofilm formation (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Tomaras et al., 2008</xref>). The qRT-PCR results show that Cec4 reduced the expression of <italic toggle="yes">CsuE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BfmR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BfmS</italic> genes. Clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> M2 can produce N-acyl-homoserine lactone (3-OH-C12-HSL), a product of the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> autoinducer synthetase gene, which is very important for the formation of complete biofilms on abiotic surfaces (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Niu et al., 2008</xref>). Our research shows that Cec4 significantly reduced the expression of <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic>. Therefore, we speculate that Cec4 may affect quorum sensing in bacteria. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> encodes for a protein associated with the biofilm, Bap. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strain 307–0294, mutations in large outer membrane proteins that are highly similar to <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> biofilm-associated protein (Bap) were lost, resulting in a reduction in the volume and thickness of the biofilm formed by the strain (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Loehfelm et al., 2008</xref>). Cec4 reduced the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">Bap</italic> gene, which was consistent with its effect on the biofilm. In conclusion, Cec4 affects the expression of genes involved in the formation of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilms, such as quorum-sensing and motility genes.</p><p>Through the neutralization or decomposition of LPS and the interference of gene expression, abnormal regulation of the genes for biofilm survival, thus inhibiting the formation of biofilm (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2004</xref>). It has been reported that peptide 1018 can inhibit bacterial stress response via the (p)ppGpp signaling molecule (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Reffuveille et al., 2014</xref>); however, there are few reports on the mechanism of inhibition and eradication of biofilm by antimicrobial peptides. To further investigate the mechanism of action of Cec4, we used RNA-Seq to study the transcriptomic profile of CRAB biofilms treated with Cec4. The RNA-Seq results show that gene expression of CRAB biofilms was extensively altered after Cec4 treatment. Compared with the control group, membrane proteins, bacterial resistance and pilus-related genes were differentially expressed. Iron ion as an important signal regulator mediates the expression of adhesion, and then affects the formation of biofilms (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Gentile et al., 2014</xref>). Our results show that bacterial ferritin was down-regulated, iron ion uptake and storage-related gene expression were increased. Besides, drug efflux-related genes and ABC transporter-related genes expressions in iron-containing cells were up-regulated. GO terms were abundant in biological process categories, indicating that bacterial biological processes were significantly affected, including the synthesis and metabolism of polysaccharides and proteins. In addition, KEGG analysis showed that multiple metabolic pathways, two-component regulation systems, quorum sensing and antibiotic synthesis-related pathways in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilms were affected after Cec4 treatment. Most importantly, the two-component signal transduction system regulates ABC transporters and type IV pili assembly proteins and participates in the growth and formation of biofilm bacteria (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Xue et al., 2020</xref>). <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Whiteley et al. (2017)</xref> mentioned that quorum sensing is involved in the formation of biofilms. Cec4 may inhibit the growth of biofilms by affecting the quorum sensing signaling pathway. Therefore, the results show that Cec4 regulates the CRAB biofilm through multiple targets, and further experiments such as gene knockout verification are required to determine the key anti-biofilm mechanisms.</p><p>In summary, this study showed that Cec4 has good antibacterial activity against planktonic clinical CRAB and its biofilm. However, the biofilm formation of clinical strains has great differences. It is reported that resistant strains achieve high levels of biofilm-specific resistance despite producing weak biofilms (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Qi et al., 2016</xref>). So, the epidemiological analysis of the 200 clinic CRAB strains is very important in understanding their genetic relationship. For example, it was shown that, of the cases of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> acquisition, at least 17% were cases of patient-to-patient transmission in the Intensive Care Unit (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Harris et al., 2019</xref>). Furthermore, deeper explorations of epidemiologic studies, such as bacterial molecular typing, drug resistance, and virulence factors detecting clinical strains, would improve our understanding of their relationship. In conclusion, these results provide a new strategy for the treatment of clinical biofilm-related infections, and also lay the foundation for the development of antimicrobial peptides as new antibacterial drugs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The sequencing data in the article have been deposited at the National Center for Biotechnology Information under BioProject <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="PRJNA607078">PRJNA607078</ext-link> as <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120700">SAMN14120700</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120701">SAMN14120701</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120702">SAMN14120702</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120703">SAMN14120703</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120704">SAMN14120704</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN1412">SAMN1412</ext-link> 0705, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120706">SAMN14120706</ext-link>, and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SAMN14120707">SAMN14120707</ext-link> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/PRJNA607078">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/PRJNA607078</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>ZW and WL conceived and designed the experiments. ZW, WL, and CM performed the experiments. WL, ZW, ZZ, and GG analyzed the data. YF, SW, and ZZ contributed materials and analysis tools. JP and JW wrote the manuscript. All authors analyzed the data and contributed to the manuscript, gave final approval of the version to be published, and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This research was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81660347), the Guizhou Provincial Science and Technology Plan Project ([2017]1154), and the Key Technologies R&amp;D Program for Science and Technology Department of Guizhou Province ([2019]2823) is co-financed. Funders had no role in study design, data collection or analysis, preparation of the manuscript or the decision to publish it. We also thank proof-reading-service for proofreading the manuscript (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.proof-reading-service.com">www.proof-reading-service.com</ext-link>).</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="footnote1"><label>1</label><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/PRJNA607078">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/PRJNA607078</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec id="S8" sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2020.01532/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2020.01532/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE S1</label><caption><p>Images of twitching motility after treated with Cec4. From left to right <bold>(A–E)</bold>, the concentration of Cec4 is 0, 2, 4, 8, 16 μg/ml.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_1.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE S2</label><caption><p>Images of surface-associated motility after treated with Cec4. From left to right <bold>(A–E)</bold>, the concentration of Cec4 is 0, 2, 4, 8, 16 μg/ml.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_2.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE S1</label><caption><p>Oligonucleotide primers used in this study.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE S2</label><caption><p>The MICs, MBIC, MBEC, sample source and drug susceptibility of 200 CRAB strains.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_2.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abouelhassan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yousaf</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolfe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Nitroxoline: a broad-spectrum biofilm-eradicating agent against pathogenic bacteria.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2016.10.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28110918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aisenbrey</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marquette</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechinger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>The mechanisms of action of cationic antimicrobial peptides refined by novel concepts from biophysical investigations.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>1117</volume>
<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-13-3588-4_4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30980352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akalay</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanassche</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Munter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Tigecycline-induced life-threatening coagulopathy in a patient with a <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium abscess</italic>: a case report and step-by-step diagnostic approach.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Clin. Belg.</italic></source>
<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17843286.2020.1747197</pub-id>
<comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32255411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alhede</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kragh</surname><given-names>K. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qvortrup</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allesen-Holm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Gennip</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Phenotypes of non-attached <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> aggregates resemble surface attached biofilm.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>e27943</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027943</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22132176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3221681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Fraga</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rumbo-Feal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohneck</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Analysis of the role of the LH92_11085 gene of a biofilm hyper-producing <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strain on biofilm formation and attachment to eukaryotic cells.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Virulence</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2016.1145335</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26854744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4871663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source><italic toggle="yes">Differential Expression of RNA-Seq Data at the Gene Level-the DESeq Package.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>EMBL</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badmasti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siadat</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouzari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajdary</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahcheraghi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Molecular detection of genes related to biofilm formation in multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolated from clinical settings.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Med. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.000058</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25813817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batoni</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisetta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brancatisano</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Use of antimicrobial peptides against microbial biofilms: advantages and limits.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Curr. Med. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/092986711794088399</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21110801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batoni</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisetta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial peptides and their interaction with biofilms of medically relevant bacteria.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</italic></source>
<volume>1858</volume>
<fpage>1044</fpage>–<lpage>1060</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2015.10.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26525663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentancor</surname><given-names>L. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho-Peiro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozkurt-Guzel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pier</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maira-Litran</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Identification of Ata, a multifunctional trimeric autotransporter of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Bacteriol.</italic></source>
<volume>194</volume>
<fpage>3950</fpage>–<lpage>3960</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.06769-11</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22609912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3416510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boca</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A direct approach to estimating false discovery rates conditional on covariates.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PeerJ.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>e6035</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6035</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30581661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6292380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vecchi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toscano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattina</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drago</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Antibiofilm agents against MDR bacterial strains: is bioactive glass BAG-S53P4 also effective?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Antimicrob. Chemother</italic>.</source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkv327</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26462989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Tigecycline: benefits and risks.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Infect. Dis.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>804</fpage>–<lpage>805</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1473-3099(11)70183-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21784707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dafopoulou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vourli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsakris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pournaras</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>An update on polymyxin susceptibility testing methods for <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev. Anti Infect. Ther.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>699</fpage>–<lpage>713</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14787210.2019.1667230</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31509713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Fuente-Nunez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korolik</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bains</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breidenstein</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Inhibition of bacterial biofilm formation and swarming motility by a small synthetic cationic peptide.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>2696</fpage>–<lpage>2704</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00064-12</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22354291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3346644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Fuente-Nunez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reffuveille</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haney</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Broad-spectrum anti-biofilm peptide that targets a cellular stress response.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Pathog.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>e1004152</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004152</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24852171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4031209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eze</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chenia</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Zowalaty</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilms: effects of physicochemical factors, virulence, antibiotic resistance determinants, gene regulation, and future antimicrobial treatments.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Infect. Drug Resist.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>2277</fpage>–<lpage>2299</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/idr.s169894</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30532562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6245380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambanthamoorthy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palys</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paranavitana</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The human antimicrobial peptide LL-37 and its fragments possess both antimicrobial and antibiofilm activities against multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Peptides</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.peptides.2013.09.007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24071034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frangipani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minandri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Runci</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visca</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Iron and <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilm formation.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Pathogens</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>704</fpage>–<lpage>719</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens3030704</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4243436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giammanco</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cala</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasciana</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowzicky</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Global assessment of the activity of tigecycline against multidrug-resistant gram-negative pathogens between 2004 and 2014 as part of the tigecycline evaluation and surveillance trial.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">mSphere</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>:<issue>e00310-16</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00310-16</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28124025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5244261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Handal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Handal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qunibi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahouri</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juhari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawodi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Characterization of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains isolated from hospitalized patients in palestine.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>2017</volume>:<issue>8012104</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/8012104</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28814955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5549501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carruthers</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munson</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strain M2 produces type IV pili which play a role in natural transformation and twitching motility but not surface-associated motility.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">mBio</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>:<issue>e00360-13</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00360-13</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23919995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3735195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pineles</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Hara</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thom</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Patient-to-patient transmission of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> gastrointestinal colonization in the intensive care unit.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>:<issue>e00392-19</issue>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AAC.00392-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6658781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31085518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Biofilm formation caused by clinical <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates is associated with overexpression of the AdeFGH efflux pump.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>4817</fpage>–<lpage>4825</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00877-15</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26033730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4505227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castanheira</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingle</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hindler</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>CLSI methods development and standardization working group best practices for evaluation of antimicrobial susceptibility tests</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Clin. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>:<issue>e01934-17</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01934-17</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29367292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5869819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andleeb</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalil</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Bacterial biofilm and associated infections.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Chin. Med. Assoc.</italic></source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcma.2017.07.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29042186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nucl. Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>D480</fpage>–<lpage>D484</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm882</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2238879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.-W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J.-S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of LysSS, a novel phage endolysin, against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Glob. Antimicrob. Resist.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgar.2020.01.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32006750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3322381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wohland</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Perturbation of Lipopolysaccharide (LPS) Micelles by Sushi 3 (S3) antimicrobial peptide. The importance of an intermolecular disulfide bond in <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>3 dimer for binding, disruption, and neutralization of LPS.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Biol. Chem</italic>.</source>
<volume>279</volume>
<fpage>50150</fpage>–<lpage>50156</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M405606200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15328339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>A method to assess influence of different medical tubing on biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Microbiol. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>160</volume>
<fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2019.03.023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30928423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loehfelm</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luke</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campagnari</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Identification and characterization of an <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilm-associated protein.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Bacteriol.</italic></source>
<volume>190</volume>
<fpage>1036</fpage>–<lpage>1044</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01416-07</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2223572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of <italic toggle="yes">Musca domestica</italic> cecropin - 4 (mdCec 4) against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chin. J. Microbiol. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>891</fpage>–<lpage>896</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3760/cma.j.issn.0254-5101.2017.12.002</pub-id>
30704229</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maragakis</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perl</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: epidemiology, antimicrobial resistance, and treatment options.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Clin. Infect. Dis.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>1254</fpage>–<lpage>1263</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/529198</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18444865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McQueary</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilms: variations among strains and correlations with other cell properties.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12275-011-0343-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21538245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neshani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedighian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirhosseini</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghazvini</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zare</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahangiri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial peptides as a promising treatment option against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microb. Pathog.</italic></source>
<volume>146</volume>:<issue>104238</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2020.104238</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32387392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmer</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of an autoinducer synthase from <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Bacteriol.</italic></source>
<volume>190</volume>
<fpage>3386</fpage>–<lpage>3392</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01929-07</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2347373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Shea</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Acinetobacter in modern warfare.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2012.01.018</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22459899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Toole</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Microtiter dish biofilm formation assay.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Vis. Exp.</italic></source>
<fpage>2437</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/2437</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21307833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3182663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Antibacterial mechanism of peptide Cec4 against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Infect. Drug Resist.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>2417</fpage>–<lpage>2428</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/idr.s214057</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31496754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6689099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Relationship between antibiotic resistance, biofilm formation, and biofilm-specific resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>483</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00483</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4828443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>RNA-Seq-based transcriptome analysis of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm inhibition by ursolic acid and resveratrol.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>:<issue>5467</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep05467</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24970710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4073122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramalingam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Antibiofilm activity of an EDTA-containing nanoemulsion on multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Artif. Cells Nanomed. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>743</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21691401.2018.1468771</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29719996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reffuveille</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De La Fuente-Nunez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>A broad-spectrum antibiofilm peptide enhances antibiotic action against bacterial biofilms.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>5363</fpage>–<lpage>5371</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.03163-14</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24982074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4135845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivals</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Personnaz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taing</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potier</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Enrichment or depletion of a go category within a class of genes: which test?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl633</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17182697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saugar</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alarcon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Hernandez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Brea</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Activities of Polymyxin B and Cecropin A-Melittin Peptide CA(1-8)M(1-18) against a multiresistant strain of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>875</fpage>–<lpage>878</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aac.46.3.875-878.2002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC127505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajwade</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paknikar</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of silver nanoparticles treated <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> reveals potential targets for biofilm inhibition.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Colloids Surf. B Biointerf.</italic></source>
<volume>175</volume>
<fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colsurfb.2018.12.032</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30572157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spapen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Gorp</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troubleyn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Honore</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Renal and neurological side effects of colistin in critically ill patients.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Ann. Intensive Care</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>:<issue>14</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2110-5820-1-14</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21906345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3224475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaras</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flagler</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorsey</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Characterization of a two-component regulatory system from <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> that controls biofilm formation and cellular morphology.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology</italic></source>
<volume>154</volume>
<fpage>3398</fpage>–<lpage>3409</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.2008/019471-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Differential gene and transcript expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with TopHat and Cufflinks.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Protoc.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3334321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diggle</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Bacterial quorum sensing: the progress and promise of an emerging research area.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>
<volume>551</volume>
<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature24624</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29144467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5870893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiegand</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilpert</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>R. E. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Agar and broth dilution methods to determine the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) of antimicrobial substances.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nature Protoc.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.521</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18274517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Using biofilms as initial inocula in animal models of biofilm-related infections.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Biomed. Mater. Res. B Appl. Biomater.</italic></source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>1169</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.b.31979</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22120924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>The pathogenicity and transcriptome analysis of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in response to water extract of <italic toggle="yes">Galla chinensis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Evid. Based Complement. Alternat. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>2019</volume>:<issue>3276156</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/3276156</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31379958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6662456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raheem</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>The KdpD/KdpE two-component system contributes to the motility and virulence of avian pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Res. Vet. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>131</volume>
<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2020.03.024</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32278961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oshlack</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Gene ontology analysis for RNA-seq: accounting for selection bias.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<issue>R14</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-2-r14</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20132535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2872874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>