<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1523</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">idr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">idr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11699857</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11699857.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11699857</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11699857</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39759767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S491858</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">491858</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular Epidemiology and Genetic Characterization of Carbapenem-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Isolates from the ICU of a Tertiary Hospital in East China</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Liu et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Liu et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0007-2047-5133</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="L">Lili</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yaping</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yunlan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhongxia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiping</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuqiong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="D">Dan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoyue</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Nosocomial Infection, Anqing First People’s Hospital of Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Anqing City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Anhui Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Science and Education, Anqing Municipal Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Anqing City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Anhui Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Anqing First People’s Hospital of Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Anqing City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Anhui Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Subdean Office, Anqing First People’s Hospital of Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Anqing City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Anhui Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Xiaoyue Li, <institution>Subdean Office, Anqing First People’s Hospital of Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Intersection of Yixiu Avenue and Xuefu Road, Yixiu District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Anqing City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Anhui Province</addr-line>, <addr-line>246003</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86-556-5865167</phone>, Email 18496701@qq.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452757</issue-id><fpage>5925</fpage><lpage>5945</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-06 09:25:16.800"><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Liu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="idr-17-5925.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>To evaluate the clinical characteristics, antimicrobial resistance (AMR) phenotypes and genotypes, and homology features of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (CRAB) in intensive care unit (ICU) and to provide basis for effectively prevention, control and treatment of nosocomial infections caused by CRAB.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A total of 39 CRAB strains isolated from hospitalized patients in the ICU and neurosurgical ICU (NICU) between 2020 and 2023 were subjected to antimicrobial susceptibility testing and whole-genome sequencing (WGS). Virulence factor genes (VFGs), antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs), multilocus sequencing typing (MLST), complete genome multilocus sequencing typing (cgMLST), average nucleotide identity (ANI), and single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) analyses were performed using WGS.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>All CRAB strains were 100% resistant to ciprofloxacin, ceftazidime, piperacillin/tazobactam, and ticarcillin/clavulanic acid. A total of 48 antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs) were found in the 39 CRAB strains, including <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-66, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>ADC-30, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>ADC-73, <italic toggle="yes">gyrA, ant(3″)-IIa, aph(3″)-Ib, aph(6)-Id, tetB, tetR, sul1, sul2, LpxC and LpxA</italic> which confered resistance to carbapenems, cephalosporins, fluoroquinolones, aminoglycosides, tetracycline and sulfonamides. There were 128 VFGs, including genes encoding the AdeFGH efflux pump, lipopolysaccharide (LpsBLC), outer membrane protein A (OmpA), penicillin-binding protein (PbpG), biofilm-associated proteins (bap, pgaBCD, CsuABCDE), type VI secretion system protein (Tss), quorum sensing protein (AbaI/AbaR). Six clonal lineages were identified by Oxford MLST method, whereas one sequence type (ST2) was identified using the Pasteur MLST method. ANI analysis, heat map of SNP analysis, and phylogenetic tree based on core SNP revealed six clusters, and the strain classification results were consistent with these different methods. Ten clonal lineages were identified by cgMLST.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The CRAB strains were ST2 clones accompanied by severe resistance to commonly used antibiotics and abundant ARGs and VFGs in genotype. Strict measures should be implemented to prevent and control transmissions and infections. CgMLST and SNPs analyses showed excellent discriminatory power in homology analysis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>drug-resistance genes</kwd><kwd>homology</kwd><kwd>multilocus sequencing typing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Science and Technology Bureau</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Anhui Medical University</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100002947</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the Science and Technology Bureau Project of Anqing City, Anhui Province (grant numbers: 2021Z3003 and 2022Z3006) and the School Research funding of Anhui Medical University (grant number: 2023xkj106).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="78"/><page-count count="21"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, a significant Gram-negative opportunistic bacterium, frequently leads to severe hospital-acquired infections, particularly in immunocompromised and elderly patients in ICU around the world.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> This pathogen can cause a large number of infections, the most common of which are ventilator-associated pneumonia and bloodstream infections, with a mortality rate of up to 35%.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> ICU infections caused by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> are associated with a 50% mortality rate.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> In recent years, drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains are increasing, including multiple drug-resistant (MDR, non-susceptibility to at least one agent in three or more antimicrobial categories), extensively drug-resistant (XDR, non-susceptibility to at least one agent in all but two or fewer antimicrobial categories) and pan-drug resistant (PDR, non-susceptibility to all agents in all antimicrobial categories) hospital isolates.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5–7</xref> Increasing usage of β-Lactam antibiotics has led to the emergence of drug-resistant strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Carbapenem is used as a last-line antibiotic drug to treat infections caused by these MDR strains.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> However, the development of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (CRAB) is limiting its use. CRAB has become a worldwide problem due to its resistance to commonly use antibiotics, in addition, pandrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> emerged and posed the greatest challenge and required a comprehensive control program and treatment.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> These isolates are difficult to treat with existing drugs, exacerbated the problem of nosocomial infection caused by the bacteria.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>CRAB strains have spread globally, and multiple drug-resistance characteristics and excessive virulence factors make it a serious threat to global public health.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> CRAB was declared an urgent threat to public health by the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) in 2019 (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/pdf/threats-report/2019-ar-threats-report-508.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/pdf/threats-report/2019-ar-threats-report-508.pdf</ext-link></underline>). Data from the China Antimicrobial Surveillance Network (CHINET) showed that from 2015 to 2021, the isolation rate of CRAB was relatively high, reaching 75.2% in tertiary hospitals, showing high resistance to commonly used clinical antibacterial drugs.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p><p>The main mechanism of resistance to carbapenems in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is the acquisition of carbapenem-hydrolyzing class D β-lactamases [oxacillinases (OXAs)], encoded by <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA−24, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-58, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-143 and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-235 variants.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> In addition, ambler class A b-lactamases (<italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>CTX-M, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>TEM, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>KPC, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>SHV and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>GES-14) and metallo-ß-lactamases (<italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>VIM-like, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>IMP-like, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>NDM-1 and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>SIM-1) also lead to carbapenem resistance.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In addition to the complex mechanism of antimicrobial resistance, virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> play important roles in invasiveness and pathogenicity. Even though virulence determinants of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> are not completely understood, the genes related to outer membrane proteins, biofilm formation, cell-associated and secretion systems, and micronutrient acquisition systems, as well as resistance to xeric stress, were regarded as important factors for successfully infecting its hosts.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> The <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains possesses a wide range of virulence factors with versatile abilities in recent study.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> A better understanding of antimicrobial resistance mechanisms and virulence factors of CRAB isolates is essential for effective control and treatment.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p><p>Recent studies based on whole-genome sequencing (WGS) have highlighted the diversity of CRAB strains across different geographical regions, revealing a complex interplay of genetic factors that contribute to their resistance profiles. A global study with CRAB strains isolated from 114 study centers in 47 countries across five continents revealed that global CRAB population currently comprised at least nine clonal lineages, isolates harboring <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23 and representing international clones 2 (IC2) are predominant strains in most parts of the world till date, but the distribution of carbapenem resistance determinants and ICs can vary widely among different geographical regions.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> A prospective observational cohort study made by 46 hospitals in five global regions between 2017 and 2019 showed that although clonal group 2 (CG2) isolates remained predominant, non-CG2 strains were associated with higher mortality.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Two studies conducted in the United States illustrate the high prevalence of acquired <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA carbapenemase genes especially <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23 among CRAB isolates.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Research from Serbia identified multiple resistance genes among CRAB isolates, including <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-72 and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>NDM-1, emphasizing the global spread of these resistance determinants.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Moreover, in the context of hospital outbreaks, the transmission dynamics of CRAB have been closely monitored in recent studies.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23–25</xref> Overall, the molecular epidemiology of CRAB underscores the urgent need for continuous surveillance, molecular characterization, and the development of effective infection control strategies to combat this formidable pathogen. The ongoing research efforts are crucial for informing public health policies and improving clinical outcomes for affected patients.</p><p>The epidemiology of CRAB strains in East China is limited, particularly among ICU patients. Anqing First People’s Hospital of Anhui Medical University was established in 1953. It is a large comprehensive teaching and tertiary hospital in the eastern region of China. The hospital currently has 2630 beds, nearly 2000 employees and 49 clinical medical technology departments. In this study, we conducted a four-year surveillance in the ICU to analyze the epidemiology and antimicrobial resistance of CRAB strains. CgMLST and SNPs analyses were performed to determine the homology between CRAB strains isolated from different patients.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Bacterial Isolates</title><p>A total of 39 strains of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (CRAB) bacteria clinically isolated from the ICU and neurosurgical intensive care unit (NICU) of Anqing First People’s Hospital of Anhui Medical University, Anqing City, Anhui Province, China, from 2020 to 2023 were collected, and duplicate strains (if the same multidrug-resistant organism was detected multiple times in the same sample from a single patient, the isolate was considered only one strain)<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> were removed. Clinical information of the 39 CRAB isolates was obtained from Xinglin Real-Time Nosocomial Infection System, and the characteristics of age, sex, clinical specimen, primary ICU admission diagnosis, infection diagnosis, antibiotics used during ICU, invasive medical operation, infection type, and discharge method from the hospital were determined.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Bacterial Identification of the Isolates</title><p>Clinical specimens from different patients were inoculated on sheep blood agar plates and incubated for 18–24 hours at 37°C. A pure culture was obtained from another blood agar plate by transferring the dominant strains from the first plate. Bacterial identification was performed using matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight (MALDI-TOF) and VITEK 2 Gram-Negative Identification Card (VITEK 2 GN Test Kit). All identified carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were stored at −80°C in a tube containing 20% glycerol.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing</title><p>The antimicrobial susceptibility testing was performed according to the method recommended by the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI), and the automated identification and susceptibility testing instrument VITEK2-Compact system (Bio-Merieux, France) and Antimicrobial susceptibility testing (AST) card (VITEK 2 AST-N335) were used for drug sensitivity interpretation, supplemented by KB method (Kirby-Bauer) according to CLSI guidelines (CLSI, 2020).<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Standard strains were <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC27853, <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC25922. CRAB isolates were defined as <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains which were multidrug-resistant (MDR), extensively drug-resistant (XDR), or pandrug-resistant (PDR) as described previously.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Bacterial DNA Extraction</title><p>All strains were obtained from a strain-storage refrigerator (−80°C, 20% glycerol). After balancing to room temperature, an appropriate amount of bacterial liquid was inoculated into blood culture dishes, and the plates were cultured in a CO<sub>2</sub> constant-temperature incubator for 18–24 hours. Before DNA isolation, the isolates were re-identified using MALDI-TOF. A single large colony was selected from a blood culture plate for DNA isolation. Genomic DNA of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was extracted using the Wizard® Genomic DNA Purification Kit (Promega) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. The integrity and quality of genomic DNA were evaluated using 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. The yield and purity of the DNA were assessed using a NanoDrop™ 2000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) and a TBS-380 fluorometer (Turner BioSystems Inc, Sunnyvale, CA). High-quality DNA (OD260/280=1.8–2.0, &gt;1 μg) was used in subsequent experiments. <italic toggle="yes">16S rRNA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">16S-23S rRNA</italic> genes were amplified and sequenced to confirm the identity of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, as described previously.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Primers were listed in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline>. Gel images and sequence confirmation information were shown in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figures S1</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">S2</ext-link></underline>.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Whole-Genome Sequencing (WGS), Draft Genome Assembly and Annotation</title><p>All isolates were sequenced by Shanghai Winnerbio Technology Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China) on the NovaSeq 6000 platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). At least 1μg of genomic DNA was prepared for each <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strain during the library construction. High-quality DNA(OD260/280=1.8–2.0, &gt;1 μg) samples were sheared into 400–500 bp DNA fragments using a Covaris M220 Focused Acoustic Shearer according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Libraries for Illumina sequencing were created using fragmented DNA, which was subsequently utilized for paired-end sequencing with 2 × 150 bp reads using an Illumina NovaSeq 6000 instrument. Raw sequencing reads were evaluated using the FastQC software.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Except where otherwise, all software tools were run with default parameters. The data were trimmed by Trimmomatic v0.39 (LEADING:3; TRAILING:3; MINLEN:36) and assembled by SOAPdenovo v3.12.0.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> All the sequences were submitted to the NCBI database.</p><p>The predicted gene sequences were translated and searched against the following database for annotation: National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) non-redundant (NR) database, the UniProt/Swiss-Prot database, the protein families (Pfam), the Clusters of Orthologous Group (COG) database, and the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database. Additional annotation was carried out using Pathogen Host Interactions (PHI), Virulence Factors of Pathogenic Bacteria (VFDB), and the Antibiotic Resistance Genes Database (ARDB).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Multilocus Sequence Typing and Core Genome Multilocus Sequence Typing</title><p>Conventional MLSTs were performed with the MLST database for <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmlst.org/organisms/acinetobacter-baumannii" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmlst.org/organisms/acinetobacter-baumannii</ext-link></underline>). Sequence type (ST) codes were generated by combining the <italic toggle="yes">gltA, gyrB, gdhB, recA, cpn60, gpi</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rpoD</italic> alleles detected under the Oxford scheme<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> and <italic toggle="yes">cpn60, fusA, gltA, pyrG, recA, rplB</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> alleles detected under the Pasteur scheme.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Minimum spanning trees were drawn based on Pasteur typing results using Phyloviz software.</p><p>Core genome (cg) MLST classification was performed on 39 strains based on the cgMLST v1 classification scheme in the PubMLST database. The minimum spanning trees were marked by the sample ID, sample type, sample source, and separation time, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Whole Genome Average Nucleotide Identity Analysis</title><p>OrthANI v0.93.1 was used to calculate the Average Nucleotide Identity (ANI) values between the whole-genome sequences of the two samples, and R v4.0.2 was used to draw the ANI clustering heat map. The clustering method was “average”.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008"><title>Whole Genome Single Nucleotide Polymorphism Cluster Analysis and Core SNP Analysis</title><p>The genome sequences of all samples were mapped to the reference genome (the reference genome used in this project was the standard strain ATCC19606 (GCF_019331655) as it is a common reference strain). Phylogenetic trees based on SNPs were built using kSNP v3 (kmer = 19) with maximum likelihood algorithm, and the SNP tree was annotated using iTOL v6.9.1.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2009"><title>Statistical and Data Projection Analysis</title><p>Clinical data were obtained from Xinglin Real-Time Nosocomial Infection System (Xinglin Tec Inc., Hangzhou, China) and analyzed using SPSS software Version 26.0 (IBM SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA). The figures of AST and AMR profiles were generated by Excel (Microsoft Inc, Redmond., USA). The minimum spanning trees (MSTs), heat map ANI and SNP and phylogenetic tree were generated as described above.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>General Information of Isolates and Patients</title><p>The present study spanned from May 2020 to July 2023. A total of 39 CRAB strains, isolated from different sites, were collected from 38 patients. Detailed clinical characteristics of the 38 patients are summarized in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Most of the clinical specimens were obtained from the respiratory system (69.2%, 27/39). The most common diagnosis when these patients were admitted to the ICU was pneumonia. Nearly all patients used ventilators (94.9%, 37/39) and urinary catheters (94.9%, 37/39) during their ICU stay. Lower respiratory tract infections and ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP) accounted for 51.3% (20/39) and 17.9% (7/39) of infection diagnoses, respectively. The detection rates of bloodstream, thoracic cavity, and intra-abdominal infections were 7.7%(3/39). As the most common infection type, hospital-acquired infection was observed in 66.7% (26/39) of patients. Various antimicrobial drugs have been used to treat infections. Among them, carbapenem (imipenem and meropenem) (79.5%, 31/39) and cefoperazone-sulbactam (74.4%, 29/39) were the two predominant antibiotics. Glycopeptides, fluoroquinolones, and oxazolidinones accounted for 43.6%(17/39), 38.5%(15/39), and 38.5%(15/39), respectively.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical Characteristics of the Patients with CRAB Sequenced in This Study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.2 205.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gender, male</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (59.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Clinical specimens</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27(69.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound secretion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascitic fluid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrothorax</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(5.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(5.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catheter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midstream urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Primary ICU admission diagnosis</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pneumonia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(30.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebral trauma and cerebral hemorrhage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(28.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(25.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(15.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(12.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery procedure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(48.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Infection diagnosis</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower respiratory tract infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(51.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(17.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thoracic cavity infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intra-abdominal infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAUTI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Antibiotics used during ICU</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbapenem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31(79.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefoperazone-sulbactam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29(74.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin–tazobactam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16(41.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycopeptides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(43.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluoroquinolones</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(38.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxazolidinones:Linezolid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(38.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracyclines</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(33.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephamycins: cefoxitin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(30.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aminoglycoside</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(30.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalosporin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(15.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colistin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(10.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antifungal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(38.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Invasive medical operation</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventilator</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37(94.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urinary catheter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37(94.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasogastric tube</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37(94.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trachea cannula</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27(69.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central venous catheter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(61.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puncture drainage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemodialysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Surgery procedure</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(48.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Infection type</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-acquired infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26(66.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community-acquired infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(17.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colonization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(15.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Discharge method</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25(64.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transfer to another hospital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(28.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Died</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: All the data are presented as the number, with the percentage in parenthesis, except for the ages, which are presented as the mean and SD.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: VAP, Ventilator associated pneumonia; BSI, Bloodstream infection; CAUTI, Catheter associated urinary tract infection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Antimicrobial Susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">A.</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">Baumannii</italic> Strains</title><p>The antimicrobial resistance rates of the 39 clinical CRAB strains to 14 antibiotics are shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline>. Results revealed that CRAB were 100% resistant to carbapenems (imipenem and meropenem), piperacillin-tazobactam, ticarcillin/clavulanic acid, ceftazidime, and ciprofloxacin. The rates of antimicrobial resistance to other antibiotics were as follows: levofloxacin, 84.6%(33/39); cefepime, 82.1%(32/39); tobramycin, 76.9% (30/39); trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, 66.7% (26/39); cefoperazone-sulbactam sodium, 64.1% (25/39); tigecycline,17.9%(7/39); and minocycline, 7.7%(3/39). Colistins demonstrated the lowest resistance rate (0%, 0/39).
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The antimicrobial susceptibility of 39 CRAB isolates from intensive care units.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0001.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: TZP, piperacillin/tazobactam; TCC, ticarcillin/clavulanic acid; IMP, imipenem MEM, meropenem; CIP, ciprofloxacin; CAZ, ceftazidime; LVX, levofloxacin; FEP,cefepime; TOB, tobramycin; SXT, trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole; CSL, cefoperazone-sulbactam sodium;TGC, tigecycline; MNO, minocycline; COL,colistin.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Characterization of Antimicrobial Resistance Genes (ARGs) in CRAB Strains</title><p>A total of 48 antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs) were found in the 39 CRAB strains that responded to ten categories of antimicrobial drugs (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> and <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline>). A total of 58.3%(28/48) of the ARGs were detected in all 39 CRAB strains, and 28 ARGs shared by all strains encoded several types of antibiotics. <italic toggle="yes">LpsB, LpxC</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">LpxA</italic> encoded resistance to peptide. <italic toggle="yes">Bla</italic>OXA-66 and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23 conferred resistance to carbapenems. G<italic toggle="yes">yrA</italic> harbored resistance to fluoroquinolones. <italic toggle="yes">Ant(3</italic>″<italic toggle="yes">)-IIa, aph(3</italic>″<italic toggle="yes">)-Ib</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">aph(6)-Id</italic> encoded resistance to aminoglycosides. <italic toggle="yes">Ecol_EFTu_KIR</italic> confers resistance to elfamycin. Many Efflux pump genes were 100% detected in all the strains, including <italic toggle="yes">adeA, adeB, adeC, adeF, adeG, adeH, adeI, adeJ, adeK, adeL, adeN, adeR</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">adeS. AbeM</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abeS</italic> were 100% contained by the strains. The detection rate of <italic toggle="yes">blaADC</italic>, which encodes resistance to cephalosporins, was 100%. Two types of <italic toggle="yes">ADC</italic> genes were identified: <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>ADC-30 (30.8%,12/39) and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>ADC-73 (69.2%,27/39). The detection rates of <italic toggle="yes">tetB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">tetR</italic>, which encode tetracycline resistance, were 97.4%(38/39) and 97.4%(38/39), respectively. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>(25.6%, 10/39) and <italic toggle="yes">sul2</italic>(38.5%, 15/39) harbored resistance to sulfonamides.
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The number of CRAB isolates with each drug resistance gene.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0002.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Virulence Factor Genes (VFGs) of CRAB Genomes</title><p><underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S4</ext-link></underline> presents the detailed VFG prediction information based on the virulence factor database (VFDB). The 39 CRAB strains contained 8 classes of VFGs. The VFGs identified in this study included regulation, stress survival, adherence, biofilm formation, immune modulation, nutritional/metabolic factors, exotoxins, and effector delivery systems. There were 128 VFGs among the 39 isolates, 69.5% (89/128) of them were found in all the 39 strains. All CRAB isolates contained genes encoding the AdeFGH efflux pump, lipopolysaccharide (LpsBLC), outer membrane protein A (OmpA), penicillin-binding protein (PbpG), biofilm-associated proteins (bap), and biofilm-associated proteins (pgaBCD). The detection rates of <italic toggle="yes">CsuABCDE</italic> (biofilm-associated proteins) genes, <italic toggle="yes">tss</italic> (type VI secretion system,T6SS) genes, <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">AbaR</italic> (quorum sensing) genes and <italic toggle="yes">hemO</italic> (heme oxygenase) gene and were 97.4%(38/39), 97.4%(38/39), 84.6%(33/39) and 71.8%(28/39), respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Multilocus Sequence Typing and cgMLST Analysis</title><p>We used the MLST database (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmlst.org/organisms/acinetobacter-baumannii" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmlst.org/organisms/acinetobacter-baumannii</ext-link></underline>) Pasteur and Oxford in the classification scheme to predict MLST information for the 39 samples in this study.</p><p>In the prediction results based on the Oxford typing scheme, because of the multiple copies of the gdhB gene (different copies had different allele numbers), most samples had two ST types. Six different ST types were identified based on the Oxford typing method (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The six ST types were ST2149 or ST938, ST191,ST136 or ST1851, ST1816 or ST195, ST540, ST1791 or ST2158.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Multilocus Sequence Typing Analysis Results Based on Oxford and Pasteur Classification Scheme</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sample ID</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Isolation Date</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Clinical Department</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Clinical Specimen</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">ST type</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxford</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pasteur</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-30-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-1-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-14-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrothorax</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-17-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-20-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound secretion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-14-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-9-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU(old)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-18-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-9-2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-13-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-5-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound secretion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149, 938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-8-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136, 1851</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-22-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound secretion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136, 1851</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-24-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrothorax</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1816, 195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-11-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136, 1851</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-27-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU(old)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1816, 195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-6-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136, 1851</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-6-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU(old)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1816, 195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-8-2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU(old)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1816, 195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-10-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascitic fluid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-26-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-20-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascitic fluid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-23-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-27-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-25-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-29-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-15-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-18-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midstream urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-28-2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-22-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catheter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-23-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136, 1851</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-28-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascitic fluid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-22-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-28-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-16-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-28-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-12-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-10-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-21-2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NICU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791, 2158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>As shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, ST2149 or ST938 included ten strains: AB01-AB06, AB08-AB11. These strains were isolated from the ICU and NICU between 5–30-2020 and 8-5-2021. The ST-type AB07 strain isolated from patients in the old NICU was ST191. ST136 or ST1851 included five strains, AB12, AB13, AB15, AB17, and AB31, isolated from the ICU and NICU from 6–11-2021 to 5–23-2023. ST1816 or ST195 included six strains, AB14, AB16, AB18, and AB19, isolated from the ICU and old ICU from 11–27-2021 to 12–24-2021. ST540 included 11 strains: AB20-AB24, AB26, AB29, AB30 and AB32-AB34 isolated from the ICU and NICU from 10–10-2022 to 7–28-2023. ST1791 or ST2158 included eight strains from the NICU: AB25, AB27, AB28, and AB35-AB39, isolated from 10–25-2022 to 5–21-2023.</p><p>All 39 CRAB isolates were classified as ST2 based on the Pasteur typing formula. Minimum spanning trees were constructed based on the Pasteur typing results. In addition to the 39 samples in this study, reference strains from the Pasteur database were added for analysis, and the results were displayed in two parts. The first part included all samples from all over the world (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">B</xref>), and the second part included all samples from China in the database (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">B</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Minimum spanning tree using phyloviz software based on global data. (<bold>A</bold>) Minimum spanning tree using phyloviz software based on global data (Pasteur database). (<bold>B</bold>) Minimum spanning tree using phyloviz software based on global data (Pasteur database) of CC1.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0003.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: (<bold>A</bold>) Each circle represents an ST type; the size of the circle is positively correlated with the number of samples, and the color of the circle indicates the origin of the sample. A single circle, which is not connected with other ST circles in a net-like structure, is a singleton, indicating that this ST is very different from other ST<italic toggle="yes">’</italic>s and cannot be clustered into a cluster. A network structure formed by two or more circles is called CC, as shown in the figure above, with a total of 95 CC and 629 singletons. (<bold>B</bold>) Each circle represents an ST type; the size of the circle is positively correlated with the number of samples, and the color of the circle indicates the isolation information of the sample.</attrib></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Minimum spanning tree using phyloviz software based on China data. (<bold>A</bold>) Minimum spanning tree of China based on Pasteur database using phyloviz. (<bold>B</bold>) Minimum spanning tree of China constructed at a high level based on Pasteur database using phyloviz.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0004.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: (<bold>A</bold>) Each circle represents an ST type; the size of the circle is positively correlated with the number of samples, and the color of the circle indicates the clinical source of the sample, as detailed in the figure note. (<bold>B</bold>) Each circle represents an ST type; the size of the circle is positively correlated with the number of samples, and the color of the circle indicates the clinical source of the sample, as detailed in the figure note.</attrib></fig></p><p>As shown in <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>, North America had the largest sample size (5919), followed by Asia (3492). The largest clonal complex (CC) was CC1 (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). ST2 was included in CC1 as the group founder. In CC1, 54.7% of the samples were from North America, 30.3% were from Asia, and the remaining 15% were from other regions. The main CC group of the samples from North America and Asia was CC1. It indicated that the main epidemic types in the two regions were similar. The ancestor ST2 may have been the most original source of other strains. Different ST strains were formed after different evolutionary processes. The diversity of the strains in Asia was higher than that in North America.</p><p>Regarding sample sources in China (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">B</xref>), 699 (40.6%) samples were isolated from Hangzhou, Zhejiang Province, 453 (26.3%) samples had no clear source, 234 (13.6%) samples were isolated from Beijing, 71 (4.1%) samples were separated from Shanghai, and 66 (3.8%) samples were from Guangzhou. As shown in <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">B</xref>, ST2 was the main ST type, and isolates from Anqing City (39 CRAB strains in this study), Hangzhou City, Beijing City, Guangzhou City and so on clustered together and formed the largest circle in the figures.</p><p>According to the cgMLST classification (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S5</ext-link></underline>), 39 samples were divided into ten types, among which AB01, AB02, AB03, AB05, AB06, AB08, AB10, and AB11 belonged to the same cgMLST type. AB27 and AB28 had the same cgMLST. AB12, AB15, AB17, and AB31 belonged to the same cgMLST type. AB14, AB16, AB18, and AB19 belonged to the same type of cgMLST. AB20-AB24, AB26, AB29, AB30, and AB32-AB34 had the same cgMLST type. AB25, AB35 and AB36-AB39 belonged to the same cgMLST type. Four samples (AB04, AB07, AB09, and AB13) were classified into different types.</p><p>The minimum spanning tree was labeled with the sample ID (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>), sample separation department (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>), specimen type (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>), and isolation date (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref>). The 20 isolates from the ICU included six STs, 15 isolates from the NICU contained six STs, three isolates from the old ICU had the same ST clone, and only one strain from the old NICU had adifferent ST clone compared with other isolates (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>). Nine strains isolated in 2020 and ten strains isolated in 2021 were assigned to 4 STs, 8 isolates from 2022, and 12 isolates from 2023 were assigned to 3 STs (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Minimum spanning tree constructed based on cgMLST allelic genes. (<bold>A</bold>) Minimum spanning tree constructed based on cgMLST allelic genes labeled with sample ID. (<bold>B</bold>) Minimum spanning tree constructed based on cgMLST allelic genes labeled with sample isolation department. (<bold>C</bold>) Minimum spanning tree constructed based on cgMLST allelic genes labeled with sample type. (<bold>D</bold>) Minimum spanning tree constructed based on cgMLST allelic genes labeled with sample isolation date.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0005.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: The circles represent ST types, and the numbers on the lines represent allelic differences.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>Whole Genome Average Nucleotide Identity Analysis</title><p>As shown in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S6</ext-link></underline> and <xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>, there was high similarity among the 39 samples (ANI &gt; 0.99). According to the level of ANI similarity, the 39 samples could be divided into six clusters, and the samples in each cluster were more similar. The results were basically consistent with the Oxford typing method (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). AB07 showed a relatively large difference from the other samples and was a single group in the heat map.
<fig position="float" id="f0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Heat map for 39 CRAB strains based on ANI among strains.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0006.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007"><title>Whole Genome Single Nucleotide Polymorphism Cluster Analysis and Core SNP Analysis</title><p>The similarities among the 39 samples were analyzed at the SNP level. As shown in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=491858.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S7</ext-link></underline> and <xref rid="f0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>, the sample cluster obtained at the SNP level was consistent with the ANI results. The number of SNPs in the same cluster was less than 20. The SNP differences between AB07 and other samples were relatively large. This formed a single clade in the heat map of SNP.
<fig position="float" id="f0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Heat map for 39 CRAB isolates based on SNP distance among strains.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0007.jpg"/></fig></p><p>In <xref rid="f0008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>, the tree on the left was the phylogenetic tree of 39 CRAB strains. The distribution of drug-resistance genes and virulence genes of each sample were located in the middle and on the right of the figure, respectively. Consistent with previous results, the 39 samples were divided into six clusters. The evolutionary relationship between AB07 and the last cluster (from top to bottom in <xref rid="f0008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>) was relatively close. As can be seen from the figure, the distribution patterns of AMRs and VFGs were consistent with the results of whole-genome average nucleotide identity analysis and core-SNP evolutionary tree. We found that strains with similar whole-genome sequences had more similar distribution characteristics of resistance and virulence genes. AB20-AB24, AB26, AB29, AB32 and AB34 had more drug-resistance genes than other samples, while they had fewer virulence genes. Phylogenomic analysis revealed that the strains in the top five clusters did not contain seven resistance genes: <italic toggle="yes">AAC(3)-Ia, blaADC-30, aadA, AAC(6′)-Ib7, catB8, qacEdelta1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">sulI</italic>. Phylogenetic analysis of the virulence genes showed that the sixth cluster (AB21, AB20, AB24, AB23, AB30, AB34, AB32, AB33, AB29, AB26 and AB22) did not detected with the <italic toggle="yes">hemO, pseBCFGHI</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">tviB</italic> genes. The majority of the strains (AB20-AB24, AB26, AB29, AB32 and AB34) in this cluster were mainly isolated from the ICU during 10–10-2022 and 7–28-2023, all of which were ST540 clones based on the Oxford MLST method (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0008" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree based on core SNP and heat maps of the detection of ARGs and VFGs among the 39 CRAB isolates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-17-5925-g0008.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>It is becoming increasingly obvious that CRAB is a prominent cause of hospital-acquired infections among a variety of bacteria, especially in intensive care units (ICUs). Patients with critical illness are significantly hindered by its spread and multidrug resistance.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> There have been many cases of outbreaks in hospital ICUs caused by CRAB strains, which pose a significant infection control challenge for healthcare facilities in recent years.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> A report from US hospitals from 2014 to 2019 revealed that patients with CRAB infections have a significantly higher burden of illness and higher risk of mortality than those with carbapenem sensitive <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> The resistance heatmap of China in the China Antimicrobial Surveillance Network (CHINET) shows that the detection rate of CRAB in Anhui Province and whole China was 86.3% and 71.2%, respectively, in 2022 (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.chinets.com/Data/GermYear" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.chinets.com/Data/GermYear</ext-link></underline>). Therefore, it is necessary to detect epidemiology of CRAB and implement effective measures to curb this trend. Based on the results of this study, CRAB resistance patterns and molecular phenotypes in this area were largely consistent over the four years.</p><p>The resistance rates of CRAB to several antibiotics in this study were extremely high, such as the resistance to carbapenems (imipenem and meropenem), β-lactam drugs (piperacillin-tazobactam, cefoperazone-sulbactam, ceftazidime), and quinolones (ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin). In recent years, carbapenem resistance has increased owing to its prior use in treating multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> CRAB has emerged as an abuse of carbapenem, which poses a huge challenge to clinical treatment. Tigecycline, eravacycline, minocycline, cefiderocol, and polymyxins are currently available treatments for CRAB.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39–41</xref> Pandrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, found worldwide, clearly illustrates the impact of emerging resistance to last-resort antimicrobials (for example, tigecycline and polymyxin).<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Among which, tigecycline is considered a last-line antibiotic for the treatment of CRAB due to its strong bacteriostatic properties. Unfortunately, there has been an increase in worldwide reports of tigecycline-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> The mechanisms underlying tigecycline resistance in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> are complex and multifactorial, involving various genetic mutations and the overexpression of efflux pumps, particularly the AdeABC system.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> We found that nearly half of the CRAB strains showed intermediate to tigecycline and minocycline in this study. All isolates were susceptible to colistin. In recent years, colistin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> has emerged as a significant global health threat.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Infections caused by carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (CRAB) are notoriously difficult to treat due to limited therapeutic options. Colistin, while often considered a last-resort antibiotic, is associated with nephrotoxicity, complicating treatment regimens.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Studies have shown that colistin resistance can develop rapidly, particularly in patients undergoing prolonged treatment, underscoring the need for effective antimicrobial stewardship.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> The rise of CRAB, tigecycline-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, and colistin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> necessitates ongoing surveillance, research into resistance mechanisms, and the development of novel therapeutic strategies to combat these formidable pathogen.</p><p>According to ARG analysis, CRAB isolates from the ICU and NICU contained a wide variety of resistance genes. All the CRAB isolates contained <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23, which encodes a class D carbapenemase gene in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. There have been reports of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23 in many countries worldwide, such as in China,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> USA,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Turkiye,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> Thailand<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> and Africa<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> that reported in recent five years. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-66 was detected accompanied with the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23 gene in this study. <italic toggle="yes">Bla</italic>OXA-66 is a member of the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-51-like gene family, which is an intrinsic oxacillinase with low carbapenemase activity, found on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii’s</italic> chromosome. To date, the OXA-51 family is the most extensively mentioned group of OXA beta-lactamases and has numerous genes compared with other class D carbapenemase genes, such as OXA-23 family, OXA-24 family, OXA-58 family, OXA-143 family and OXA-134 family genes.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> Extended-spectrum β-lactamase (ESBL) genes (<italic toggle="yes">blaTEM-1</italic>,32/39), other β-lactamase genes (<italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>ADC-30,12/39; <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>ADC-73,27/39) were found in some CRAB isolates. 31/39 of the CRAB strains contained the <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic> gene, which was reported as giving high-level resistance to aminoglycosides, particularly amikacin, gentamicin, plazomicin, and tobramycin.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> On the whole, these CRAB strains contained genes that encoded resistance to β-lactams, carbapenem, aminoglycoside, tetracycline, macrolide, fluoroquinolone, peptide, phenicol and sulfonamide. The tremendous resistance genes and severe phenotypic resistance rates detected in this study revealed that hospitals must take immediate action on the rational use of antimicrobial agents.</p><p>In the present study, we identified abundant virulence-factor-associated genes. VFGs include biofilm formation, adherence, stress survival, regulation, nutritional/metabolic factors, exotoxins, effector delivery systems, nutritional/metabolic factors and immune modulation. There may be a link between these virulence genes and greater pathogenicity and severity of infection among CRAB isolates.<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> The various VFGs found in this study were basically consistent with recent researches.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> All the strains showed a lack of BfmRS which was known as an important factor in motility of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> Poly-β-(1, 6)-N-acetylglucosamine (PNAG) is encoded by a cluster of four genes (<italic toggle="yes">pgaABCD</italic>),<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">pgaB, pgaC</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pgaD</italic> were 100% found in all 39 CRAB isolates. It has been demonstrated in numerous studies that PNAG is crucial for maintaining the integrity of biofilms of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in stressful and dynamic conditions.<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> OmpA (outer membrane protein A) is one of the most widely recognized and characterized virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. It is required for the development of robust biofilms on abiotic surfaces.<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref> All the isolates in this study contained the <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> gene. A quorum sensing (QS) process allows bacteria to communicate with each other based on the density of the bacterial population. <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">AbaR</italic> regulates the QS system in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. In <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978, a functional QS system is necessary for biofilm formation and surface-associated motility.<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> Except for AB07, the other 38 isolates possessed the type VI secretion system (T6SS), which is composed of 13 core <italic toggle="yes">tss</italic> genes and a variable number of tag genes (T6SS-associated genes) at least.<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> The T6SS system is a widely spread nanomachine used by bacteria to eliminate competition and give the bacteria growth advantages in settling natural habitats.<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> The multiple VFGs should be noticed in subsequent research.</p><p>During the four years of this study, the epidemiological characteristics of the CRAB isolates did not change significantly. All isolates harbored <italic toggle="yes">blaOXA-23</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">blaOXA-66</italic>, which mediate resistance to carbapenems. The epidemic sequence type of these isolates was ST2 based on the Pasteur MLST method. In addition to being the most prevalent clonal type reported worldwide and documented in various databases, ST2 is common in China.<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref> In terms of resolution in distinguishing <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, the Oxford scheme showed a better ability than the Pasteur scheme. However, the copy of the Oxford scheme in this study makes us puzzle in the subsequent analyses. Based on the detection of seven housekeeping genes, MLST has been commonly used since 1998 for assessing clonal relationships among bacteria.<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref> A comparative analysis of the two <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> MLST schemes showed that they have complementary characteristics, each with their own advantages. The Pasteur method exhibits reduced discrimination but excels at identifying clonal lineages and generally performs better when comparing distant clones.<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> As ST2 is the most prevalent strain in China as shown in our research and related references, the Pasteur method might not be applicable for CRAB isolates.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref> Furthermore, the Oxford scheme better distinguishes between strains at short evolutionary distances and shows a higher degree of concordance with phylogenies. It should be noted, however, that an alternative gdhB locus appears in a majority (533/730) of the genomes of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in the genomic era.<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> So in our research, we chose the Pasteur scheme for MLST classification of the CRAB strains for further minimum spanning tree construction based on databases of China and the World. However, a previous study showed that neither the MLST scheme for <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was able to recover the correct relationships among the isolates. As genome sequencing becomes increasingly affordable, it will serve as an ideal method for identifying bacterial species.<xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref> Molecular typing methods with higher discriminatory ability are crucial for elucidating the epidemiology of hospital outbreaks and pathogenic bacteria.</p><p>Whole-genome sequencing (WGS) has become a promising tool for isolate identification, molecular epidemiology, and nosocomial infection outbreak analysis in microbiological laboratories over the past decade.<xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref> The core genome MLST (cgMLST) analysis based on genome sequencing results showed that all strains could be divided into ten groups. The six clusters obtained at the whole-genome SNP level were consistent with the ANI results, and the number of SNPs in each cluster was basically less than 20. In general, homologous and phylogenetic analyses based on the whole genome showed very strong similarity among the strains. The results imply several transmissions over four years. However, to date, among strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, the transmission inference threshold for <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains has not been established. Fourteen such strains collected from a single individual showed a range of 1–40 SNP differences between them which suggested that <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates have a higher threshold for inferring transmission.<xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref> In our study, SNPs distances of pair isolates less than 20 were regarded as closely related evolutionary isolates or genetically related clones. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is capable of surviving in the environment for a long time and is capable of transmitting the infection.<xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref> Multi-drug resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> can be kept in contaminated environments and equipment.<xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref> In our research, isolates belonging to the same SNP cluster from ICU (such as AB12, AB13 and AB31) isolated from different patients were sustained for several years. The results suggested that some transmissions may have taken place indirectly via contaminated environments or healthcare personnel, which is consistent with several previous studies.<xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,<xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref> In addition, we observed transmission between the ICU and NICU, as some strains clustered together from the two departments. From the heat map of SNP, the phylogenetic tree and the separation time of strains, we can also speculate that several transmissions have occurred in the ICU and NICU, as some CRAB strains were detected in a short time with the same genotype.</p><p>To our knowledge, the advantage of this research is firstly reporting of epidemiology and genomic characterizations of CRAB isolated from ICU and NICU in East China. It reveals the huge carrying of ARGs and VFGs of CRAB. High-resolution cgMLST and SNP methods showed the transmissions of ST2 clone during the four years. Effective measures should be implemented for reducing the incidence of CRAB. In addition, we compare the two schemes of MLST method (Pasteur and Oxford) in distinguishing CRAB isolates. However, there are a few limitations to our research. First, the sample size of this study is limited. The CRAB strains were not fully collected and resuscitated in our hospital. Our next plan is to collect more CRAB strains in several hospitals in the area. Second, specimens from the environment of ICU were not collected at the same time when possible transmission occurred. Absent of environmental samples leaded the difficulty of explaining the pathway of dissemination of CRAB. Finally, the genetic environment of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA23 gene was not described. The prediction of insertion sequence (IS) elements and the integrons were important to detailing the drug-resistance mechanism of CRAB.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, this is the first report on the molecular epidemiology and genetic characterization of CRAB isolates from ICU and NICU in East China. All the CRAB strains showed high rates of antimicrobial resistance and possessed multiple antimicrobial genes and virulence factor genes. All CRAB were <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23-producing strains and ST2 clones characterized by MLST during four years. This study identified the emergence of several transmissions of <italic toggle="yes">blaOXA-23</italic> CRAB ST2 clones in hospital. All in all, our findings underscore the successful dissemination of ST2 clones in a tertiary hospital in East China. CRAB strains harboring the acquired <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-23 β-lactamase gene in ICU and NICU deserve full attention in hospital as they exhibit strong phylogenetic homology. CgMLST and SNP analysis based on WGS showed excellent discrimination power in this transmission and homology research. Effective infection prevention and control measures need to be implemented in the ICUs. Further molecular epidemiology detection and containment activities in different areas are urgently needed.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0006"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>The datasets generated in this research can be found in the NCBI Bioproject with the accession number PRJNA1111166.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>This study was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of Anqing First People’s Hospital of Anhui Medical University (AQYY–YXLL–KJXM–41). This study was retrospective and associated with bacterial drug susceptibility and the genetic information of the specimens, our ethical petition for exemption from informed consent was waived. All the patient’s data in this study were collected anonymously and ensured the confidentiality of their information. This study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sarshar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Behzadi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Scribano</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. et al. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: an Ancient Commensal with Weapons of a Pathogen</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathogens</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens10040387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33804894</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8063835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Antunes</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Visca</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Towner</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: evolution of a global pathogen</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathog Dis</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2049-632X.12125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376225</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hennon</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Uncovering the mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> virulence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29249812</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6571207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bianco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Quirino</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Control of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> outbreak in an intensive care unit of a teaching hospital in Southern Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>747</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-016-2036-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27955639</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5154034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manchanda</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchaita</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Multidrug resistant acinetobacter</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Glob Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0974-777X.68538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20927292</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2946687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magiorakos</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: an international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Microbiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03570.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793988</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rafailidis</surname>
<given-names>PI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kofteridis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Proposed amendments regarding the definitions of multidrug-resistant and extensively drug-resistant bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14787210.2021.1945922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34152887</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Saryi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Kadmy</surname>
<given-names>IMS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> as an emerging concern in hospitals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Biol Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>6987</fpage>–<lpage>6998</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11033-021-06690-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34460060</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8403534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hujer</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rudin</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nosocomial Outbreak of Extensively Drug-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Isolates Containing <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic>OXA-237 Carried on a Plasmid</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e00797</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00797-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28893775</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5655091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tolmasky</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tolmasky</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Carbapenemases: transforming <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> into a Yet More Dangerous Menace</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomolecules</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>720</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom10050720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32384624</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7277208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mea</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname>
<given-names>PVC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An overview of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> pathogenesis: motility, adherence, and biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>247</volume>:<fpage>126722</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2021.126722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33618061</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiawei</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yingchun</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dawei</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Changing antimicrobial resistance profiles of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> strains in hospitals across China: results from CHINET Antimicrobial Resistance Surveillance Program, 2015-2021</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Infect Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>734</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16718/j.1009-7708.2023.06.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amyes</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>OXA β-lactamases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Microbiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00117-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24696435</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3993105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kooguchi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moriyama</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular diversity of extended-spectrum β-lactamases and carbapenemases, and antimicrobial resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Intensive Care</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40560-020-0429-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015881</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6988205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>JX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>DY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Advances in research on virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and their potential as novel therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>lxac089</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jambio/lxac089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36597783</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karampatakis</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsergouli</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Behzadi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pan-Genome Plasticity and Virulence Factors: a Natural Treasure Trove for <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics13030257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38534692</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10967457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suh</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Molecular and virulence characteristics of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates: a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19536</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-46985-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37945745</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10636183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reuter</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wille</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A global view on carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mBio</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e0226023</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mbio.02260-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37882512</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10746149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical Outcomes and Bacterial Characteristics of Carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Among Patients From Different Global Regions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciad556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37738153</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10874260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vlachos</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Daniels</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Molecular Epidemiology of Carbapenem-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in the United States, 2013-2017</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>645</fpage>–<lpage>653</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2021.0352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35639112</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9197948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bulens</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> complex in the United States-An epidemiological and molecular description of isolates collected through the Emerging Infections Program</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Infect Control</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1035</fpage>–<lpage>1042</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2024.04.184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38692307</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11979794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lukovic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kabic</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dragicevic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genetic basis of antimicrobial resistance, virulence features and phylogenomics of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>clinical isolates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infection</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>2024</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s15010-024-02316-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38856809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Darwish</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Catalan</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hospital outbreak of Carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in the context of local facility transmission</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Infect Control</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>741</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2024.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38246493</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Hassan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Elbadawi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Molecular Epidemiology of Carbapenem-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> From Khartoum State, Sudan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>628736</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.628736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33717019</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7952628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blakiston</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epidemiology of carbapenem resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in New Zealand</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NZ Med J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>1561</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26635/6965.5783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36049792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Implications of deduplication on the detection rates of multidrug-resistant organism (MDRO) in various specimens: insights from the hospital infection surveillance program</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>54</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-024-01408-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38769515</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11107067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing[S]. M100-S30. Wayne, PA: CLSI</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Misbah</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yusof</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genomic species identification of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> of clinical isolates by 16S rDNA sequencing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Singapore Med J</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123830</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sarhan</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haimour</surname>
<given-names>WO</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Identification of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> clinical isolates by polymerase chain reaction analysis of 16S-23S ribosomal ribonucleic acid internal transcribed spacer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Indian J Med Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>. <comment>PMID: 24713899</comment>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0255-0857.129797</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24713899</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>SequencErr: measuring and suppressing sequencer errors in next-generation sequencing data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Biol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-020-02254-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33487172</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7829059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bankevich</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nurk</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Antipov</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Comput Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.2012.0021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3342519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bartual</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hippler</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development of a Multilocus Sequence Typing Scheme for Characterization of Clinical Isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>4382</fpage>–<lpage>4390</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.43.9.4382-4390.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16145081</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1234098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Diancourt</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Passet</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nemec</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The population structure of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: expanding multiresistant clones from an ancestral susceptible genetic pool</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e10034</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383326</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2850921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: a challenge in the intensive care unit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1045206</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.1045206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36439795</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9684325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Outbreak of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> carrying the carbapenemase OXA-23 in ICU of the eastern Heilongjiang Province, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>452</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-4073-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31113374</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6530087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>HW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Whole-Genome Sequencing for Investigating a HealthCare-Associated Outbreak of Carbapenem-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diagnostics</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>201</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diagnostics11020201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33573077</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7910894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pogue</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kanakamedala</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Burden of illness in carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections in US hospitals between 2014 and 2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-07024-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34991499</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8740340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nordmann</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Poirel</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology and Diagnostics of Carbapenem Resistance in Gram-negative Bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>Suppl 7</issue>):<fpage>S521</fpage>–<lpage>S528</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciz824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31724045</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6853758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karakonstantis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kritsotakis</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gikas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Treatment options for <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> co-resistant to carbapenems, aminoglycosides, polymyxins, and tigecycline: an approach based on the mechanisms of resistance to carbapenems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infection</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>851</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s15010-020-01520-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32875545</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7461763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skariyachan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taskeen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ganta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Recent perspectives on the virulent factors and treatment options for multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>333</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1040841X.2019.1600472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31012772</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Talaga</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krzyściak</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bulanda</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Susceptibility to tigecycline of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains isolated from intensive care unit patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anaesthesiol Intensive Ther</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5603/AIT.a2016.0021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013253</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karakonstantis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kritsotakis</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gikas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pandrug-resistant Gram-negative bacteria: a systematic review of current epidemiology, prognosis and treatment options</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Antimicrob Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkz401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31586417</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wareth</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sprague</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Spatio-Temporal Distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in Germany—A Comprehensive Systematic Review of Studies on Resistance Development in Humans (2000–2018)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microorganisms</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8030375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32155886</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7143851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Mechanism of Tigecycline Resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> under Sub-Minimal Inhibitory Concentrations of Tigecycline</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1819</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25031819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38339095</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10855123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>[Retracted] Analysis of Efflux Pump System and Other Drug Resistance Related Gene Mutations in Tigecycline-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Comput Math Methods Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>2023</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8611542</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2023/8611542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36846201</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9957652</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10732781"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Novović</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jovčić</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Colistin Resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: molecular Mechanisms and Epidemiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>516</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12030516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36978383</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10044110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predictors of Acute Kidney Injury and 28-Day Mortality in Carbapenem-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Complex Bacteremia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1036</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2020.0312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33656377</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kousovista</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Athanasiou</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liaskonis</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quantifying the effect of in-hospital antimicrobial use on the development of colistin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains: a time series analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Hosp Pharm</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ejhpharm-2020-002606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35190451</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8899687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epidemiological and genetic characteristics of clinical carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains collected countrywide from hospital intensive care units (ICUs) in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Emerg Microbes Infect</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1730</fpage>–<lpage>1741</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2022.2093134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35730377</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9258068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kostyanev</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>García-Castillo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Phenotypic and molecular characterizations of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates collected within the EURECA study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Antimicrob Agents</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>106345</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2021.106345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33887390</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kilbas</surname>
<given-names>EPK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kilbas</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ciftci</surname>
<given-names>IH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular epidemiology of carbapenem-resistant A<italic toggle="yes">cinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates in Turkiye: systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">North Clin Istanb</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14744/nci.2022.17003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37719251</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10500232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0052"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boral</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pınarlık</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ekinci</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does Emerging Carbapenem Resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Increase the Case Fatality Rate? Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Dis Rep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/idr15050055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37888136</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10606343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0053"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chukamnerd</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singkhamanan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chongsuvivatwong</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Whole-genome analysis of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> from clinical isolates in Southern Thailand</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Comput Struct Biotechnol J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2021.12.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36284706</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0054"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kindu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Derseh</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gelaw</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moges</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Carbapenemase-Producing Non-Glucose-Fermenting Gram-Negative Bacilli in Africa, <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: a Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>9461901</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/9461901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33204275</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7658691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0055"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Angadi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jadhav</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular Characterization of Carbapenem-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> with Special Reference to Carbapenemases: a Systematic Review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>7631</fpage>–<lpage>7650</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S386641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36579124</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9791997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0056"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genetic basis of high level aminoglycoside resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> from Beijing, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Pharm Sin B</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsb.2014.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26579398</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0057"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Distribution of virulence-associated genes and antimicrobial susceptibility in clinical <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncotarget</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>31</issue>):<fpage>21663</fpage>–<lpage>21673</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.24651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29774093</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5955172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0058"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anwar</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genomic Determinants of Pathogenicity and Antimicrobial Resistance of Nosocomial <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Clinical Isolates of Hospitalized Patients (2019-2021) from a Sentinel Hospital in Hangzhou, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>2939</fpage>–<lpage>2952</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S407577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37201122</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10187652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0059"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmer</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Genetic analysis of surface motility in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>Pt 9</issue>):<fpage>2534</fpage>–<lpage>2544</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.049791-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700662</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3352170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0060"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Le Berre</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pier</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Glycomics Microarrays Reveal Differential In Situ Presentation of the Biofilm Polysaccharide Poly-N-acetylglucosamine on <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> Cell Surfaces</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2465</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21072465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32252300</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7177611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0061"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goller</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Roles of pgaABCD genes in synthesis, modification, and export of the <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> biofilm adhesin poly-beta-1,6-N-acetyl-D-glucosamine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3670</fpage>–<lpage>3680</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01920-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18359807</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2394981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0062"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Slamti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Avci</surname>
<given-names>FY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The gaABCD Locus of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Encodes the Production of Poly-β-1-6- N-Acetylglucosamine, Which Is Critical for Biofilm Formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>191</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>5953</fpage>–<lpage>5963</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00647-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633088</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2747904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0063"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaras</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> 19606 OmpA protein plays a role in biofilm formation on abiotic surfaces and in the interaction of this pathogen with eukaryotic cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Immun</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3150</fpage>–<lpage>3160</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00096-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19470746</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2715673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0064"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parga</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quorum Sensing as a Target for Controlling Surface Associated Motility and Biofilm Formation in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> ATCC® 17978TM</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>565548</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.565548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33101239</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7554515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0065"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hennon</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genetic Dissection of the Type VI Secretion System in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> and Identification of a Novel Peptidoglycan Hydrolase, TagX, Required for Its Biogenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mBio</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e01253</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01253-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27729508</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5061870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0066"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pukatzki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sturtevant</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Identification of a conserved bacterial protein secretion system in Vibrio cholerae using the Dictyostelium host model system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1528</fpage>–<lpage>1533</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510322103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16432199</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1345711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0067"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kapitein</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mogk</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Type VI secretion system helps find a niche</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Host Microbe</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2014.06.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25011102</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0068"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nigro</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emergence, molecular mechanisms, and global spread of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Genom</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e000306</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31599224</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6861865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0069"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen van Rensburg</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maiden</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>MLST revisited: the gene-by-gene approach to bacterial genomics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>728</fpage>–<lpage>736</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23979428</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3980634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0070"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaiarsa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Batisti</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Esposito</surname>
<given-names>EP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparative Analysis of the Two <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Multilocus Sequence Typing (MLST) Schemes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>930</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31130931</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6510311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0071"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Molecular characteristics of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter spp</italic>. from clinical infection samples and fecal survey samples in Southern China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>900</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-4423-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31660862</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6819553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0072"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo-Ramírez</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Graña-Miraglia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inaccurate Multilocus Sequence Typing of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Emerg Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2501.180374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30561303</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6302598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0073"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Makke</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bitar</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salloum</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Whole-Genome -Sequence-Based Characterization of Extensively Drug-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Hospital Outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mSphere</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e00934</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00934-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31941816</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6968657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0074"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gorrie</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Da Silva</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ingle</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Key parameters for genomics-based real-time detection and tracking of multidrug-resistant bacteria: a systematic analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Microbe</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e575</fpage>–<lpage>e583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00149-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35544081</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0075"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marchaim</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Navon-Venezia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Surveillance cultures and duration of carriage of multidrug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1551</fpage>–<lpage>1555</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.02424-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314222</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1865886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0076"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chapartegui-González</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lázaro-Díez</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> maintains its virulence after long-time starvation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e0201961</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0201961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30133491</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6104976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0077"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Whole-Genome Sequencing Elucidates the Epidemiology of Multidrug-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in an Intensive Care Unit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>715568</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.715568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34589072</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8473952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0078"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A gloves-associated outbreak of imipenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in an intensive care unit in Guangdong, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-015-0917-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886493</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4415246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>