<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5802823</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5802823.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5802823</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5802823</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29410443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20847-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20847</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolution of the Quorum network and the mobilome (plasmids and bacteriophages) in clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> during a decade</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>López</surname><given-names initials="M">M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rueda</surname><given-names initials="A">A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Florido</surname><given-names initials="JP">J. P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blasco</surname><given-names initials="L">L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-García</surname><given-names initials="L">L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trastoy</surname><given-names initials="R">R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Cuenca</surname><given-names initials="F">F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Martínez</surname><given-names initials="L">L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8025-3926</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Vila</surname><given-names initials="J">J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names initials="A">A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bou</surname><given-names initials="G">G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4501-0387</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomas</surname><given-names initials="M">M.</given-names></name><address><email>MA.del.Mar.Tomas.Carmona@sergas.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Departamento de Microbiología, Instituto de Investigación Biomédica de A Coruña (INIBIC), Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de A Coruña (CHUAC), Sergas, Universidade da Coruña (UDC), Coruña, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Genomics and Bioinformatics Platform of Andalusia, GBPA, Seville, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9542 1158</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411109.c</institution-id><institution>Clinical Bioinformatics Research Area, Fundación Progreso y Salud (FPS), Hospital Virgen del Rocío, </institution></institution-wrap>Seville, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 7922</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414816.e</institution-id><institution>Unidad de Enfermedades Infecciosas y Microbiología. Hospital Universitario Virgen Macarena. Departamento de Microbiología. Universidad de Sevilla. Instituto de Biomedicina de Sevilla (IBIS), </institution></institution-wrap>Sevilla, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2183 9102</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411901.c</institution-id><institution>Departamento de Microbiología, </institution><institution>Universidad de Córdoba, </institution></institution-wrap>Córdoba, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1771 4667</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411349.a</institution-id><institution>Unidad de Gestión Clínica de Microbiología, Hospital Universitario Reina Sofia, </institution></institution-wrap>Cordoba, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0445 6160</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.428865.5</institution-id><institution>Instituto Maimónides de Investigación Biomédica de Córdoba (IMIBIC), </institution></institution-wrap>Córdoba, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9635 9413</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410458.c</institution-id><institution>IS Global, Barcelona Centre for International Health Research (CRESIB), Hospital Clínic-Universitat de Barcelona, </institution></institution-wrap>Barcelona, Spain </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">304108</issue-id><elocation-id>2523</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>02</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>02</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-01 13:25:20.850"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2018_Article_20847.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">In this study, we compared eighteen clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> belonging to the ST-2 clone and isolated from patients in the same intensive care unit (ICU) in 2000 (9 strains referred to collectively as Ab_GEIH-2000) and 2010 (9 strains referred to collectively as Ab_GEIH-2010), during the GEIH-REIPI project (Umbrella BioProject PRJNA422585). We observed two main molecular differences between the Ab_GEIH-2010 and the Ab_GEIH-2000 collections, acquired over the course of the decade long sampling interval and involving the mobilome: i) a plasmid harbouring genes for <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA 24/40</sub> ß-lactamase and <italic toggle="yes">abKA/abkB</italic> proteins of a toxin-antitoxin system; and ii) two temperate bacteriophages, Ab105-1ϕ (63 proteins) and Ab105-2ϕ (93 proteins), containing important viral defence proteins. Moreover, all Ab_GEIH-2010 strains contained a Quorum functional network of Quorum Sensing (QS) and Quorum Quenching (QQ) mechanisms, including a new QQ enzyme, AidA, which acts as a bacterial defence mechanism against the exogenous 3-oxo-C12-HSL. Interestingly, the infective capacity of the bacteriophages isolated in this study (Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ) was higher in the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains (carrying a functional Quorum network) than in the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains (carrying a deficient Quorum network), in which the bacteriophages showed little or no infectivity. This is the first study about the evolution of the Quorum network and the mobilome in clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> during a decade.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2"><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is a successful nosocomial pathogen, especially in Intensive Care Units (ICUs), where sporadic disease outbreaks occur<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The species is now endemic in some ICUs and is the second or third most common pathogen in nosocomial settings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. This is due to the ability of nosocomial pathogens to persist in the hospital environment for long periods of time, as well as to the continued increase in multidrug resistance and to virulence and/or pathogenicity, which are mainly acquired via the mobile genomic elements (bacteriophages, plasmids and transposons referred to as the “mobilome”) that are the main driving forces for the genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Proliferation of mobile elements stimulates chromosomal recombination and rearrangement, leading to genome plasticity and contributing to enhanced genetic variability and adaptation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Prophages (temperate bacteriophages) can introduce a plethora of genes that provide different functions to their hosts (e.g. motility, quorum sensing and stress tolerance)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. For instance, bacteriophages can protect their hosts against secondary infections through exclusion of superinfection as they prevent similar phage particles from attaching to the host<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Such lysogenic conversions can take the form of stable phenotypic changes or increased host plasticity, thereby improving bacterial survival under stress conditions via the Quorum Sensing (QS) network and the SOS response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">On the other hand, Quorum Quenching (QQ) mechanisms can effectively interfere with any of the key processes in QS systems and this capacity could potentially be exploited to quench QS and prevent microbial infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Naturally occurring QQ mechanisms act by blocking key steps of the QS system, such as signal generation, signal accumulation and signal reception. Microorganisms exist in a multi-species, competitive environment and have developed many survival strategies to gain benefits and compete for space, nutrition and ecological niches. One of these, QS interruption, is straightforward because bacteria that produce QQ agents can inhibit the QS-regulated behaviour of competing species and therefore obtain benefits or avoid being killed by other bacteria or viruses, so that the functional network comprises both QS and QQ mechanisms.</p><p id="Par5">An AHL acylase, AmiE, has recently been identified in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> sp. strain Ooi24<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Our research group has recently described a new QQ enzyme (AidA) in a clinical isolate of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> under 3-oxo-C12-HSL pressure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Array studies revealed that only 13 proteins associated with 7 groups of families with the QQ phenotype were overexpressed in the presence of this molecule: the AidA enzyme (QQ mechanism), Glutathione-S-transferase (detoxification and DNA repair), RND transporter (efflux pump), Omp38 (OmpA), Enterocidin Ecn A/B family (stress response), Porin and 7 proteins involved in AHLs synthesis. The AidA enzyme was found to be associated with bacterial competition, as it is capable of hydrolyzing the signalling molecules used to mediate communication between species, including 3-oxo-C12-HSL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Information about bacteriophages and the network of QS/QQ mechanisms adds to a growing appreciation that plasmid carriage can have complex effects on the bacterial phenotype. For example, plasmids have been shown to alter biofilm formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, cell hydrophobicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, stress tolerance and motility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Plasmid carriage can also alter biotic interactions with bacteriophages, limiting the coevolution of bacteria and bacteriophages and altering the longer-term evolutionary trajectory of bacterial populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The plasmid-harbouring bacteria have evolved lower resistance to bacteriophages, and plasmid-carrying bacteriophages have evolved lower infectivity than plasmid-free populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">In this study, we compared the genomes of eighteen clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> belonging to the ST-2 clone and isolated from the same hospital and ICU (9 strains referred as Ab_GEIH-2000 and 9 strains referred as Ab_GEIH-2010) during the Spanish Multicentre Study (the GEIH-REIPI project). The aims of studying the collections of clinical <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> strains were as follows: i) to investigate the molecular evolution of the strains by sequencing and carrying out genome analyses; ii) to develop linear sequences of the bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105-2φ) from the representative strain of the Ab_GEIH-2010 collection (Ab105_GEIH-2010); iii) to characterize both bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105-2φ) in the Ab_GEIH-2010 clinical strains; iv) to carry out functional analysis of the network of Quorum Sensing/Quorum Quenching systems in the isolates belonging to the Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections; and v) to determine the infective capacity of bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105-2φ) in isolates from the Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections under stress conditions (3-oxo-C12-HSL) in relation to the QQ enzyme, AidA.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Genomic and phenotypic features of the isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> from Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections</title><p id="Par8">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the results of whole-genome sequencing (WGS) studies undertaken as part of the GEIH-REIPI Spanish Multicentre <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Study II 2000–2010, Umbrella BioProject PRJNA422585 (Bioproject Acc.Number in NCBI server). In total, 44.44% of the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains contained the AbATCC329/pMMCU3 plasmid harbouring <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA 24/40</sub> ß-lactamase and <italic toggle="yes">abKA/abkB</italic> genes, in contrast to 100% of the Ab_GEIH-2010 isolates. Moreover, the MICs for the strains under study are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. The MICs of imipenem (64 mg/L) and meropenem (&gt;128 mg/L) were the same for all Ab_GEIH-2010 strains, but not for the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains. Interestingly, the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains showed higher susceptibility than the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains to amikacin (resistance which is associated with aminoglycoside-modifying enzymes).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Genome Sequences. Whole genome studies carried out as part of the GEIH-REIPI Spanish Multicentre <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Study II 2000–2010 (Umbrella BioProject PRJNA422585).<sup>a</sup>CDSs: Coding Sequences for protein. <sup>b</sup>AbATCC329/pMMCU3 plasmid harbouring <italic toggle="yes">bl</italic>a<sub>OXA 24/40</sub> ß-lactamase gene and <italic toggle="yes">abKA/abkB</italic> genes from the TA system.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ST-2 Strain</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">GenBank Acc.Number<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Size (GC%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ND50</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Contigs</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDSs<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNA genes</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AbkAB toxin-antitoxin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 155_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="LJHA00000000">LJHA00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,991,758 (39.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">153263</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,759</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 158_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMC00000000">MSMC00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,860,705 (39.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7301</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">885</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,507</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 161_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMB00000000">MSMB00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,848,902 (39.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8375</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">820</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,483</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 166_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMG00000000">MSMG00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,572,409 (39.8%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5197</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1134</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,141</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 169_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMF00000000">MSMF00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,653,226 (39.5%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6485</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">973</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,273</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 175_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMI00000000">MSMI00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,744,299 (39.7%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7106</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">895</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,392</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 177_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSME00000000">MSME00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,896,859 (39.4%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14751</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">511</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,617</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 183_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMJ00000000">MSMJ00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,869,061 (39.5%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8096</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">793</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,523</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 192_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMH00000000">MSMH00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,781,564 (39.4%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13973</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">542</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,466</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 105_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="LJHB00000000">LJHB00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,092,613 (39.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">112770</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,918</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 33_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMK00000000">MSMK00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,032,038 (39.3%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16368</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">483</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,826</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 49_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMM00000000">MSMM00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,863,043 (39.4%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10937</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">626</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,620</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 54_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSML00000000">MSML00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,972,430 (39.4%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11936</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">655</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,707</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 76_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSLY00000000">MSLY00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,862,509 (39.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7456</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">888</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,523</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 103_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSLX00000000">MSLX00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,883,445 (39.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8217</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,559</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 104_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMA00000000">MSMA00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,960,610 (39.4%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12369</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,690</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 121_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSLZ00000000">MSLZ00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,987,262 (39.3%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16626</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">522</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,758</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 122_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MSMD00000000">MSMD00000000</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,839,340 (39.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8434</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">837</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,505</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Strains and susceptibility to several antimicrobials. CAZ: Ceftazidime; IMP: Imipenem; MER: Meropenem; SUL: Sulbactam; GEN: Gentamicin; TOB: Tobramycin; AMK: Amikacin; CIP: Ciprofloxacin; MIN: Minocicline; TIG: Tigecycline; COL: Colistin; DOR: Doripenem; DOX: Doxycycline; TET: Tetracycline; RIF: Rifampicin. Strains <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">coli</italic> ATCC25922 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">aeruginosa</italic> ATCC27853 strains were used as controls.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ST-2 Strain</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAZ</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">IMP</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MER</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">SUL</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">GEN</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">TOB</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AMK</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CIP</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIN</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">TIG</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">COL</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">DOR</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">DOX</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">TET</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">RIF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Ab_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 155_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 158_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 161_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 166_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 169_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">512</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 175_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 177_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 183_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 192_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Ab_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 105_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 33_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 49_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 54_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 76_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 103_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 104_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 121_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 122_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par9">The phylogenetic tree from both collections (Ab_GEIH-2000/2010) is shown in the Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. We observed the genomic similarity between strains of Ab_GEIH-2000 versus the genomic similarity of Ab_GEIH-2010 isolates.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree with multiple alignment of Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 collections. The strains from Ab_GEIH-2000 are showed in blue versus isolates of Ab_GEIH-2010 in red colour.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2023" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par10">Moreover, comparison of the chromosomal sequences (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) of the Ab_ GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 collections of strains revealed the following: i) the number of similar proteins (<underline>core-genome</underline>) was higher in the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains than in the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains (3654 proteins relative to 3301 proteins); ii) of these proteins (<underline>core-genome</underline>), 239 were located in bacteriophages in the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains, compared with 21 in the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains; and iii) of the 51 proteins present only in the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains (<underline>accessory genome</underline>), 40 proteins (79%) were located in the bacteriophages. Finally, comparison of the plasmidic sequences indicated the presence of 17 proteins only in the Ab_GEIH-2010 isolates (AbATCC329/pMMCU3 plasmid harbouring genes encoding OXA 24/40 ß-lactamase and AbKA/AbkB proteins)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Genomic comparison of the Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 collections of strains. The strains are represented by different coloured ovals depending on whether they are included in the Ab_GEIH-2000 (blue) or Ab_GEIH-2010 (yellow) collections. The number shown in the non-overlapping portions of each oval is the number of unique coding DNA sequences (CDSs) in each strain (accessory genome). The total number of CDSs within each genome is shown in brackets below the strain name, and the size of the core genome (orthologous CDSs shared by all strains) is shown in the centre of the figure. The figure was constructed using Adobe Illustrator. (<bold>B</bold>) Genomic comparison of Ab_GEIH-2000 strains. The core genome (centre), the accessory genome of each strain (blue oval). The total number of CDSs within each genome is shown in brackets below the strain name. (<bold>C</bold>) Genomic comparison of the strains in the Ab_GEIH-2010 collection. The core genome (centre), the accessory genome of each isolate (yellow oval). The total number of CDSs within each genome is shown in brackets below the strain name.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2060" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">The genome of strain Ab105_GEIH-2010 (representative of the Ab_GEIH-2010 group of strains) included two temperate bacteriophages: Ab105-1ϕ (size 41,496 bp; 63 ORFs) and Ab105-2ϕ (size 61,304 bp; 93 ORFs). The sequences were deposited in GenBank under nucleotide sequence numbers <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KT588074">KT588074</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KT588075">KT588075</ext-link>, respectively. The phages showed the best BLAST matches in <italic toggle="yes">Siphoviridae</italic> bacteriophage family YMC/09/02/B1251 ABA BP (Bphi-B1251 [<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_019541.1">NC_019541.1</ext-link>]). All open reading frames (ORFs) comprising the two bacteriophage genomes, as determined by bioinformatic analysis and PCR techniques, are shown in Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref> (Supplementary files). Completely aligned phage genomes (ORFs) are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Interestingly, the genome of the Ab155_GEIH-2000 strain (representative of Ab_GEIH-2000 strains) included phage proteins but no complete temperate bacteriophages.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Genome annotation representation for bacteriophages Ab 105-1ϕ (<bold>A</bold>) and Ab 105-2ϕ (<bold>B</bold>). The genes were predicted using GenemarkS software (trained with existing annotation of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> MDR-TJ). The resulting genes were annotated by integrating the output of Blast2Go, RAST, PHAST or PHASTER, or were manually annotated using BLAST software. This information was used to group the genes in different categories. The plot was constructed using genome tools; each box represents a predicted ORF and the arrow indicates the direction of the gene.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2092" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Finally, we observed the presence of Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ bacteriophages in all Ab_GEIH-2010 strains but not in the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Genome of bacteriophages Ab 105-1ϕ and Ab 105-2ϕ in Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 strains. The circos plot represents the genome of bacteriophages Ab 105-1ϕ and Ab 105-2ϕ, as follows, from the outer to the inner track: (1) names of the predicted ORFs; (2) genomes of both bacteriophages; (3) track of genes coloured as before; (4) similarity between the genomes of the two bacteriophages and the sequence of the other strains isolated in 2010. Red-coloured areas indicate no similarity in that region, i.e. this region is not present in the other genome or it was not detected with sufficient confidence. Green-coloured areas indicate a high level of confidence regarding the presence of the region; and (5) Equivalent plot for the strains isolated in 2000. In order to create the similarity tracks, we aligned the reads from each against the whole assembly, by using BWA software package. We used <italic toggle="yes">samtools</italic> to select those that map with high confidence in the phage regions and <italic toggle="yes">bedtools</italic> to measure the coverage. Those regions with coverage of more than 25× (expected around 150×) were flagged as very similar.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2112" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Response of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> Ab105_GEIH-2010 strain (carrying of Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ bacteriophages) under the SOS response (MMC)</title><p id="Par13">The SOS response (MMC) produced differences in microarray expression of the genes from the two bacteriophages of the Ab105_GEIH-2010. Under stress conditions by SOS response we observed an overexpression of 5% and 30% of genes by Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ bacteriophages respectively (Umbrella BioProject PRJNA422585). Only three ORFs were expressed in bacteriophage Ab105-1ϕ, while 28 ORFs were expressed in bacteriophage Ab105-2ϕ (30.10%) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Moreover, up to 40 minutes after the addition of MMC (to induce the SOS response), overexpression of ORF27 (methyltransferase-SAM or AdoMet-MTase) with a relative expression (RE) of 200 times and ORF06 (MazG-like protein) with an RE of 81.3 times that of Ab105-2ϕ was observed by qRT-PCR. After 40 minutes, the RE of ORF 93 (DNA polymerase UmuC) increased by 10 times (phage Ab105-2ϕ).<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Microarrays studies. Expression of the Ab105_GEIH-2010 genome (determined by microarray analysis under the SOS response) and lytic/metabolic expression of Ab 105-1ϕ and Ab 105-2ϕ prophage genes. <sup>a</sup>Proteins associated with viral defence against bacterial attack.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">General Function</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Expression Level</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Ab 105-1ϕ prophage</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF08</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATPaseAAA(domain protein)/Rec A-like family ATPases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Viral replication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Ab 105-2ϕ prophage</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Integrase</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lysogenic state</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.26</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.60</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>ORF03</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>SAM or AdoMet-MTase</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Viral defense</bold>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>7</bold>.<bold>09</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.83</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phage protein</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.90</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>ORF06</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>MazG-like protein</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Viral defense</bold>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>10</bold>.<bold>96</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF07</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.39</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF08</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.36</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATPaseAAA(domain protein)/Rec A-like family ATPases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Viral replication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.40</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.75</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XRE family transcriptional regulator (repressor)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lytic/ lysogenic regulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.35</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transcriptional regulator (Lambda repressor-like)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lytic/ lysogenic regulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.36</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.17</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phage replication, protein O</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Viral replication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.15</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Replicative DNA helicase</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Viral replication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.94</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.59</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Integrase</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lysogenic state</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MarR family-transcriptional regulator</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lytic/ lysogenic regulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.20</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>ORF27</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>SAM or AdoMet-MTase</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Viral defence</bold>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4</bold>.<bold>00</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.10</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.22</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DnaJ-class molecular chaperone with C-terminal Zn finger domain, putative</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DNA metabolism/replication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.83</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.54</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF33</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.16</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP/UF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORF66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rha transcriptional regulator</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lytic/ Lysogenic regulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.04</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>ORF80</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>DNA polymerase UmuC</bold> (<bold>DNA-repair protein</bold>, <bold>UmuC-like</bold>, <bold>N-terminal</bold>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Viral defence</bold>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>73</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par14">On the other hand, in the arrays results from the Ab105_GEIH-2010, there were other overexpressed bacterial genes involved in the SOS response under MMC (Umbrella BioProject PRJNA422585). Among them, we highlight several genes related to DNA repair with high overexpression (&gt;10 fold): i) Glutathione S-transferase ii) Deoxyuridine 5 -triphosphate nucleotidohydrolase (dUTPase); iii) ParB-like protein; and iv) Thymidylate synthase.</p><p id="Par15">Finally, the bacterial response after incubation with MMC is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. Bacterial lysis occurred in the presence of MMC but not in the absence of this compound. Finally, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> also shows the characteristic morphology of the phages in the <italic toggle="yes">Siphoviridae</italic> family, with a long tail and an icosahedral capsid of diameter~ 60 nm (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://viralzone.expasy.org/">http://viralzone.expasy.org/</ext-link>).<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Growth curves. (<bold>A</bold>) Ab_GEIH-2010 strains under the SOS response (induced by MMC). (<bold>B</bold>) Bacteriophages examined by TEM microscopy.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e2684" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Responses of Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections under stress conditions (3-oxo-C12-HSL and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>)</title><p id="Par16">The results of expression of the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> (QS) and the <italic toggle="yes">aidA</italic> (QQ) genes in all strains from the Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 collections under stress conditions are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. Activation of the QS system by the ROS response (presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) produced overexpression of the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene in all of the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains. In the presence of the 3-oxo-C12-HSL molecule (used to induce inhibition of the QS system), all of the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains overexpressed the <italic toggle="yes">aidA</italic> gene, while only 55.5% of the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains overexpressed this QQ enzyme and 44.4% of these strains overexpressed the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene. Therefore, the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains showed QS-deficient cells relative to the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains, which had a functional QS system.<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Relative expression (RE) of the Quorum sensing genes (<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">aidA</italic>). **Mutations or deletions in the sequence of <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene. In bold type, those isolates with no or low expression of <italic toggle="yes">aidA</italic> gene; <sup>a</sup>NCBI GenBank Database; <sup>b</sup>Inhibition of the Quorum Sensing system by Quorum Quenching activity (induced by the presence of 3-oxo-C12-HSL); <sup>c</sup>Activation of the Quorum Sensing system via the ROS response (induced by the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>). NA, Not Applicable.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">PROJECT</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strain of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> clone ST-2</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>
</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Acc. Number. Genbank<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">3-oxo-C12-HSL<sup>b</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub><sup>c</sup></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bacterial sensitivity to the Bacteriophages Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">aidA</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">aidA</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">aidA</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Ab_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 155_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ODA52665.1">ODA52665.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ODA52667.1">ODA52667.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ODA50170.1">ODA50170.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>50</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3</bold>.<bold>00</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 158_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV45102.1">OLV45102.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV48145.1">OLV48145.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV47950.1">OLV47950.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3</bold>.<bold>63</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>10</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 161_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV47680.1">OLV47680.1</ext-link>**</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV49329.1">OLV49329.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV44152.1">OLV44152.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>75</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>25</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 166_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 169_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV61375.1">OLV61375.1</ext-link>**</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV61377.1">OLV61377.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV61862.1">OLV61862.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>11</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>97</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 175_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV76671.1">OLV76671.1</ext-link>**</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV72445.1">OLV72445.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>55</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>89</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 177_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV61352.1">OLV61352.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV61354.1">OLV61354.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV60446.1">OLV60446.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>39</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>60</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 183_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV73449.1">OLV73449.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV79706.1">OLV79706.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV77156.1">OLV77156.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4</bold>.<bold>45</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>65</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 192_GEIH-2000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV66603.1">OLV66603.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV66482.1">OLV66482.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6</bold>.<bold>19</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>80</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Ab_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 105_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ODA55972.1">ODA55972.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ODA55974.1">ODA55974.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ODA53988.1">ODA53988.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3</bold>.<bold>94</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>55</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 33_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV79037.1">OLV79037.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV79035.1">OLV79035.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV80563.1">OLV80563.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>50</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>50</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 49_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV89715.1">OLV89715.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV84391.1">OLV84391.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV86104.1">OLV86104.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6</bold>.<bold>49</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>10</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 54_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV83069.1">OLV83069.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV83067.1">OLV83067.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV85628.1">OLV85628.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>50</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>5</bold>.<bold>16</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 76_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV40014.1">OLV40014.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV29965.1">OLV29965.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV34275.1">OLV34275.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>80</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>20</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 103_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV41119.1">OLV41119.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV35969.1">OLV35969.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV33173.1">OLV33173.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>77</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>80</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 104_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV48295.1">OLV48295.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV40038.1">OLV40038.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OVL46713.1">OVL46713.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>62</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2</bold>.<bold>14</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 121_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV37874.1">OLV37874.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV38310.1">OLV38310.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OVL36028.1">OVL36028.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>70</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3</bold>.<bold>14</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ab 122_GEIH-2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV58946.1">OLV58946.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OLV53842.1">OLV53842.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="OVL52031.1">OVL52031.1</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3</bold>.<bold>73</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold>.<bold>75</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par17">Finally, the absence of surface motility profile was also homogeneous (QQ phenotype) in the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains relative to the heterogeneity associated with the presence of surface motility in some isolates of the Ab_GEIH-2000 collection (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Motility of the Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 strains. (<bold>a</bold>) Ab155_ GEIH-2000; (<bold>b</bold>) Ab158_GEIH-2000; (<bold>c</bold>) Ab161_GEIH-2000; (<bold>d</bold>) Ab166_GEIH-2010; (<bold>e</bold>) Ab169_GEIH-2000; (<bold>f</bold>) Ab175_GEIH-2000; (<bold>g</bold>) Ab177_GEIH-2000; (<bold>h</bold>) Ab183_GEIH-2000; (<bold>i</bold>) Ab192_GEIH-2000; (<bold>j</bold>) Ab33_GEIH-2010; (<bold>k</bold>) Ab49_GEIH-2010; (<bold>l</bold>) Ab54_ GEIH-2010; (<bold>m</bold>) Ab76_GEIH-2010; (<bold>n</bold>) Ab103_GEIH-2010; (<bold>ñ</bold>) Ab104_GEIH-2010; (<bold>o</bold>) Ab105_GEIH-2010; (<bold>p</bold>) Ab121_GEIH-2010 and (<bold>q</bold>) Ab122_GEIH-2010.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e3599" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Impact of the Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ bacteriophages: infective capacity</title><p id="Par18">The Ab_GEIH-2010 strains, all of which carried a functional network of QS/QQ mechanisms (including the AidA protein), were infected with the bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105- 2φ). In all Ab_GEIH-2010 isolates, as well as in strain Ab177_GEIH-2000 (which harboured a functional QS/QQ network including the AidA protein), the infective capacity (PFU/CFU) of the bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105- 2φ) was not statistically significant different in the presence or absence of the 3-oxo-C12-HSL molecule. However, the bacteriophages were not able to infect those Ab_GEIH-2000 strains lacking the AidA protein (Ab175_GEIH-2000 and Ab192_GEIH-2000) or that displayed low expression thereof (Ab158_GEIH-2000 and Ab183_GEIH-2000), or those strains with mutations or deletions on the AbaR protein (Ab161_GEIH-2000 and Ab169_GEIH-2000) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Moreover, a statistically significant increase in the infective capacity of the bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105-2φ) was found in the only strain in the study that did not possess AidA, AbaI or AbaR proteins (Ab166_GEIH-2000), in the presence of the external 3-oxo-C12-HSL molecule (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Effect of the QS/QQ network (carrying the AidA enzyme) on the bacteriophage infection capacity. Three strains of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> (Ab105_GEIH-2010, Ab177_GEIH-2000 and Ab166_GEIH-2000) were infected with Ab105-1φ and Ab105-2φ, both in the presence and absence of the 3-oxo-C12-HSL molecule (light grey and dark grey, respectively), used as a QS inhibitor in <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumanni</italic>. **Indicates statistically significant differences (two-tailed Student t-test and Welch’s t-test, P &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d29e3631" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par19">Viruses that infect bacteria (bacteriophages) can influence the dynamics of the bacterial community, the evolution of the bacterial genome and the biogeochemistry of the ecosystem. However, the degree of influence differs depending on whether the bacteriophages establish lytic, chronic or lysogenic infections. The analysis of different ecosystems by comprehensive modelling will help provide a better understanding of the diverse lifestyles and ecological impacts of lysogens in nature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. In this study of the genomic evolution in 18 <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> strains belonging to ST-2 clone isolated in the same ICU in 2000 (9 strains referred to collectively as Ab_GEIH-2000) and in 2010 (9 strains referred to collectively as Ab_GEIH-2010), we found that the Ab_GEIH-2010 strains harboured two conserved temperate bacteriophages (Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ), which displayed lytic activity and activated the SOS response (in the presence of MMC). Microarray assays revealed overexpression of three viral proteins associated with protection of the virus against bacterial attack during the lytic activation of the bacteriophages. Moreover, qRT-PCR studies confirmed the overexpression of the genes coding the three proteins, 40 min after induction with MMC: i) the SAM-dependent methyltransferases or AdoMet-MTases (ORF27 from Ab 105-2ϕ), which have been associated with protection of the viral genome of the host restriction enzymes from the bacteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>; and ii) MazG (ORF06), which is a pyrophosphohydrolase enzyme located in bacteriophages that infect <italic toggle="yes">Burkholderia cenocepacia</italic> and in marine bacteriophages (especially cyanophages), thus facilitating viral infection in the environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. In <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, the MazG protein has been associated with a decrease in activity of the MazF toxin (MazEF toxin-antitoxin system), a defence mechanism that inhibits the spread of phage P1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>; and iii) the mutation-inducing UmuC protein may have significant implications for the evolution of virulence and antibiotic resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par20">Several are the studies where has been demonstrated by NGS analysis the high degree of variation in <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> clinical isolates, including single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and large DNA fragment variations in the resistance island (RI) regions, the type VI secretion system (T6SS) and the bacteriophages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. One of the key determinants of the size, composition, structure and development of a microbial community is the predation pressure exerted by bacteriophages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Bacteria have accordingly evolved a battery of anti-phage defence strategies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Evidence that QS signalling may be involved in regulating the response to phages is increasing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. For example, in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in the presence of QS signals, i.e. N-acyl-L-homoserine lactones (AHLs), there is a significant reduction in levels of the phage receptor LamB<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, which protects the bacterium against attack from the λ phage. Moreover, in <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio anguillarum</italic>, mutants that are permanently locked in a high-cell density state are almost completely immune to the phage KVP40, due to the QS-mediated downregulation of the OmpK receptor used by the phage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. In other pathogens such as <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, the QS system has also been associated with populations evolving with bacteriophages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. It has recently been demonstrated that the presence of lysogenic bacteriophages acts as a powerful driving force for the selection of functional bacterial QS systems both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> strains, by stabilizing bacterial cooperation and therefore virulence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Interestingly, in all strains of the Ab_GEIH-2010 collection, a new QQ enzyme (AidA) and the AbaI protein were overexpressed in the presence of exogenous 3-oxo-C12-HSL (a QS inhibitor) and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (ROS response), respectively. These results indicated the presence of a functional QS/QQ network in these cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. These molecular features were not present in the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains (lacking or displaying low expression of the AidA protein as well as mutations or deletions in AbaR protein), hence showing a QS/QQ-deficient<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, which was not infected by the Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ bacteriophages.</p><p id="Par21">Interestingly, in a single strain which did not possess AidA, AbaI or AbaR, the low infective capacity of the bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105-2φ) increased significantly (**P &lt; 0.05, Student’s t-Test) in the presence of the external 3-oxo-C 12 -HSL molecule. The AidA enzyme was previously described by our research group in clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> (non surface motile strains) associated with bacterial competition, as it is capable of hydrolyzing the signalling molecules (including 3-oxo-C12-HSL) mediated between species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Weiland and colleagues described several QQ enzymes displaying hydrolytic activity against AHLs and AI-2 signals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Therefore, several authors propose the use, together with lytic phage therapy, of QS modulators, i.e. quorum quenchers, to decrease the phage resistance mediated by the QS system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">Another molecular difference between the strains in the two collections (Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010) was the presence/absence of a plasmid harbouring genes encoding the OXA 24/40 ß-lactamase (resistance to carbapenems) and AbkA/AbkB proteins. This AbkA/AbkB toxin-antitoxin (TA) system was described by Mosqueda <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. in 2014<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> in all plasmids carrying the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA 24/40</sub> ß-lactamase gene that confers resistance to carbapenems in strains of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> in Spanish hospitals. In plasmids, TA systems have been associated with plasmid stabilization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, although it has been hypothesised that TA loci serve only to maintain plasmid DNA at the expense of the host organism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Other authors suggest that these systems have evolved to favour the competitive ability of plasmids in cell progeny<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. This hypothesis has been corroborated by the results of computer modelling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. The clinical antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains have been shown to display higher susceptibility to environmental phages than antibiotic-sensitive strains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Our results regarding the clinical multiresistant strains in the Ab_GEIH-2010 collection, which showed higher sensitivity to the Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ phages, is also consistent with the aforementioned finding.</p><p id="Par23">In conclusion, two main molecular changes occurred during adaptation of clinical <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> strains to a hospital environment during a decade: i) acquisition of a plasmid harbouring genes for OXA 24/40 ß-lactamase (associated with resistance to carbapenems) and AbKA/AbkB proteins (TA system), implicated in plasmid stabilization, and ii) acquisition of two temperate bacteriophages, Ab105-1ϕ (63 proteins) and Ab105-2ϕ (93 proteins), containing important proteins associated with protection of the viral genome against bacterial attack (the SAM-dependent methyltransferases or AdoMet-MTases, as well as MazG and UmuC). Interestingly, the Ab_GEIH-2000 strains showed a QS/QQ-deficient network relative to the functional QS/QQ network observed in Ab_GEIH-2010 strains under stress conditions, which could indicate the molecular evolution to a functional network of QS and QQ cells by these temperate bacteriophages (Ab105-1ϕ and Ab105-2ϕ) in the Ab_GEIH-2010 collection. The functional QS/QQ network included a new QQ enzyme, AidA, which acts as a bacterial defence mechanism and was overexpressed in the presence of a QS inhibitor (exogenous 3-oxo-C12-HSL). The aforementioned molecular characteristics have an important influence on the evolution of bacterial pathogens and how these adapt to the host environment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> from Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections</title><p id="Par24">We studied eighteen genetically related clinical strains of A. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> (ST2 indicated by Multilocus Sequence Typing, MLST) isolated from patients in the same ICU of a Spanish hospital, in 2000 (Ab_GEIH-2000 group of strains) and 2010 (Ab_GEIH-2010 group of strains)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> (Umbrella BioProject PRJNA422585 Acc.Number in NCBI server). The strains were identified during the II Spanish Multicentre Study (GEIH-REIPI <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> 2000-2010) in which 654 strains of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> were isolated in 42 participating hospitals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">We determined the antibiotic susceptibility profile by microdilution, according to CLSI recommendations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. We used PCR to determine the presence of the OXA 24/40 ß-lactamase and an AbkA/AbkB toxin-antitoxin system in all strains from the Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 collections.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Analysis of the genomes from Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections by next generation sequencing (NGS)</title><p id="Par26">The Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 strains (including Ab105_GEIH-2010 and Ab155_GEIH-2000 isolates) were analyzed by next generation sequencing (NGS) in a Roche 454 GS FLX+ sequencer and Illumina MiSeq system. Isolates Ab155_GEIH-2000 and Ab105_GEIH-2010 reads were assembled using newbler Roche assembler. The other isolates were assembled using Velvet (Velvet v1.2.10 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/~zerbino/velvet/">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/~zerbino/velvet/</ext-link>). Putative ORFs were predicted from assembled contigs using the GeneMarkS gene prediction program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>, which was previously trained with the <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> genome (GI:83207914). Blast2Go<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> and RAST<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup> were used for functional annotation of each predicted protein. rRNA and tRNA were identified using RNAmmer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> and tRNAscan-SE 1.21<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par27">The phylogenetic tree with multiple alignment was developed by Progressive Mauve software (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.darlinglab.org/mauve/mauve.html">http://www.darlinglab.org/mauve/mauve.html</ext-link>) and painted through dendroscope tool (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dendroscope.org/">http://www.dendroscope.org/</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par28">Construction of the pan genomes (all proteins), core genomes (similar proteins) and accessory genomes (no similar proteins) of the Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 strains was carried out using the PanSeq.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> and Spine tools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">The bacteriophage sequence was isolated from Ab105_GEIH-2010 (a strain representative of the Ab_GEIH-2010 collection) and manually assembled to improve the continuity of phage sequences. PCR amplification was used to confirm <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> assembly results used as a negative control for the Ab155_GEIH-2000 strain. Reconstructed phage tools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. All phage proteins detected were manually annotated using the Protein BLAST<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> and InterProScan tools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> and displayed ≥50% protein homology. The <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> assembly results were confirmed by PCR amplification.</p><p id="Par30">The bacteriophage genomes of all strains analyzed in this study were compared following the indications of Krzywinski and collaborators<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Study of the temperate bacteriophages of Ab105_GEIH-2010 (representative strain from Ab_GEIH-2010 collection)</title><p id="Par31">Mitomycin C (MMC)-induced bacteriophages were analyzed in the Ab105_ GEIH-2010 strains by three methods: (i) gene expression by microarrays and qRT-PCR; (ii) growth curves; and (iii) isolation of the bacteriophages and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) studies.</p><sec id="Sec12"><title>Gene expression studies by microarrays and qRT-PCR</title><p id="Par32">For the microarray studies, we obtained Dnase-treated RNA from a mid-exponential growth phase culture (optical density at 600 nm, 0.5). The cultures were treated with MMC (at a final concentration of 10 μg ml<sup>−1</sup>) and incubated for 1 h to induce an SOS response. The samples were removed for RNA extraction with the High Pure RNA Isolation Kit (Roche, Germany). The corresponding controls were processed in the same way but without addition of the above-mentioned compounds.</p><p id="Par33">The microarrays were specifically designed for the Ab 105_GEIH-2010 isolates by Bioarray Diagnostico Genético (Alicante, Spain) and using eArray (Agilent). The microarray assays were performed with 15,744 probes to study 4,017 genes. Labelling was carried out by two-colour microarray-based prokaryote analysis and Fair Play III labelling, version 1.3 (Agilent). Three independent RNAs per condition (biological replicates) were used in each experiment. Statistical analysis was carried out using Bioconductor, implemented in the RankProd software package for the R computing environment. A gene was considered induced when the ratio of the treated to the untreated preparation was ≥1.5 and the P value was &lt;0.05<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par34">Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) was used to examine the expression of bacteriophage genes in relation to interaction with the bacterial host (host-virus interactions). We used the Lightcycler 480 RNA MasterHydrolysis Probe (Roche, Germany) for the qRT-PCR studies. The UPL Taqman Probes (Universal Probe Library-Roche, Germany), Taqman probes and primers used are listed in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> (Supplementary files). We adjusted the concentrations of the samples to achieve efficiencies of 90–110% and performed all experiments in triplicate from three RNA extractions (50 ng per RNA sample). For each strain, we normalized the expression of all genes relative to the single-copy <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> housekeeping gene. We then calibrated the normalized expression of each gene of interest relative to its expression by untreated Ab_GEIHs RNA, which was assigned a value of 1.0.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Growth curves</title><p id="Par35">About 100 ml LB broth was inoculated with 1:100 (v/v) of clinical strain Ab105_GEIH-2010 and was cultured overnight under shaking at 37 °C. In order to induce bacteriophages, one of the bacterial cultures, in which the optical density (OD) at 600 nm had reached 0.6, was exposed to MMC (Fischer Scientific, Loughborough, UK) at a final concentration of 10 µg/ml. Aliquots (1 ml) of the culture were removed for RNA extraction and the OD was measured every 20 minutes, and then every hour.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Isolation of the bacteriophages and TEM studies</title><p id="Par36">Broth culture of strain Ab105_GEIH-2010 was induced as previously described for bacteriophage induction. Lysates were centrifuged at 3400 × g for 10 min and the supernatant was filtered through a 0.22 nm filter (Millipore). NaCl was added, to a final concentration of 0.5 M, and the suspensions were mixed thoroughly and left on ice for 1 h. The suspensions were then centrifuged at 3400 × g for 40 min at 4 °C, and the supernatants were transferred to sterile tubes. PEG 6000 (10% wt/vol) was added and dissolved by rocking the tubes at room temperature for 1 h and subsequent overnight incubation at 4 °C. Bacteriophages were then precipitated at 3400 × g for 40 min at 4 °C and resuspended in SM buffer (0.1 M NaCl, 1 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.2 M Tris-HCl, pH 7.5)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. The samples were stored at 4 °C until being processed for TEM. The samples were negatively stained with 1% aqueous uranyl acetate before being examined in a JEOL JEM-1011 electron microscope.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>QS/QQ network in Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections: QS/QQ genes</title><p id="Par37">We used qRT-PCR to examine expression of the network of QS/QQ genes (the <italic toggle="yes">aba</italic><italic toggle="yes">I</italic> gene from the QS system and the <italic toggle="yes">aid</italic><italic toggle="yes">A</italic> gene from the QQ system)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. We obtained DNAse-treated RNA from cultures treated with either non-native 3-oxo-C12-HSL (associated with inhibition of the QS system)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> or H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (ROS response implicated in activation of the QS system)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. We used the Lightcycler 480 RNA MasterHydrolysis Probe (Roche, Germany) for the qRT-PCR studies. The UPL Taqman Probes (Universal Probe Library-Roche, Germany), Taqman probes and primers used are listed in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> (Supplementary files). We adjusted the concentrations of the samples to yield efficiencies of 90–110% and normalized them with housekeeping gene (<italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic>), as previously mentioned.</p><p id="Par38">We also studied the surface motility (Quorum Sensing phenotype)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> of all strains. The motility assays were performed in plates of modified LB-LN (nutrient depleted)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> containing 2 g tryptone, 1 g yeast extract and 5 g NaCl. Assays were carried out with 0.25% Difco (Bacto<sup>TM</sup> agar)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Extraction of bacteriophages of Ab105_GEIH-2010 (representative strain from Ab_GEIH-2010 collection)</title><p id="Par39">The lysogenic bacteriophages (Ab105-1φ and Ab105-2φ) were isolated from a culture of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> strain Ab105_GEIH-2010, obtained by culturing the bacterium in LB medium at 37 °C until it reached the late log phase of growth. In order to lyse the cells and obtain the bacteriophages contained within, the culture was first incubated in the presence of 10% chloroform for 30 minutes and centrifuged at 3000 × g for 15 minutes before the supernatant was recovered and filtered through Millipore 0.22 μm membranes. The bacteriophages were then concentrated by the double agar overlay method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> and used to infect <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> strain Ab177_GEIH-2000, which did not harbour any bacteriophages. The plates were washed with 3 ml of phage buffer (10 mM Tris-HCL pH 7.5 and 1.8 MgSO 4) under stirring for 3 hours, after which the buffer was recovered and the phages were refiltered.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Estimation of bacterial sensitivity to bacteriophages from Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections</title><p id="Par40">All strains from the Ab_GEIH-2000/2010 collections were grown overnight. The cultures were subsequently diluted 1:100 in LB medium and in LB medium supplemented with 10 μM 3-oxo-C12-HSL (exogenous AHL that inhibits the detection of quorum in <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic>). When the OD at 600 nm reached 0.1, the cultures were infected with the previously purified bacteriophages of strain Ab105_GEIH-2010 at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 10 (calculated by dividing the number of bacteria [colony-forming units CFUs] the number of phages [plaque-forming units, PFUs], in a given volume of infection mixture). The cultures were then incubated at 37 °C and shaken at 180 rpm for 4 hours. An aliquot of each culture was used to establish the number of CFUs by means of serial dilution. The bacteriophages were then extracted as described above and finally the PFUs were enumerated by the double layer agar method using strain Ab177_GEIH-2000 as substrate for infection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Nucleotide sequence accession number</title><p id="Par41">The WGS and arrays studies of the Ab_GEIH-2000 and Ab_GEIH-2010 strain collections form part of the II Spanish Multicentre Study. GEIH-REIPI <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> 2000-2010 project (Umbrella BioProject PRJNA422585).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec19"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2018_20847_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>M. López and A. Rueda contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-20847-7.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was funded by grants PI13/02390 and PI16/01163 awarded to M. Tomás within the State Plan for R + D + I 2013-2016 (National Plan for Scientific Research, Technological Development and Innovation 2008–2011) and co-financed by the ISCIII-Deputy General Directorate of evaluation and Promotion of Research-European Regional Development Fund “A way of Making Europe” and Instituto de Salud Carlos III FEDER. M.Tomás was financially supported by the Miguel Servet Research Programme (SERGAS and ISCIII). A. Muras was financially supported by a predoctoral fellowship from the Xunta de Galicia (Plan I2C). L. Fernández-García was financially supported by a predoctoral fellowship from the Xunta de Galicia (GAIN, Axencia de Innovación). We thank All Genetics S.L, A Coruña, Spain (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.allgenetics.eu">http://www.allgenetics.eu</ext-link>), who contributed to the WGS studies. We are grateful to the following organizations and researchers who participated in the study GEIH-GEMARA (SEIMC, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.seimc.org">http://www.seimc.org</ext-link>) and the REIPI (Spanish Network for the Research in Infectious Disease-REIPI, RD12/0015/0010 and RD16/0016/0001): Virgen Macarena (Jesús Rodriguez-Baño) Virgen Rocío (Jerónimo Pachón, Jose Miguel Cisneros, Younes Smani, José Garnacho, Antonio Gutierrez Pizarraya, Juan Antonio Márquez Vácaro), Hospital Marqués de Valdecilla (María Eliecer Cano, M. Carmen Fariñas), Hospital SAS La Línea (Antonio Sánchez Porto, Gloria Esteban Meruendano, Luis Barbeyto Vales, Javier Casas Ciria, Luis Vallejo), Complejo hospitalario de Ourense (Begona Fernández Pérez, José Carlos Villar Chao), Hospital Gregorio Maranón (Belén Padilla Ortega, Emilia Cercenado Mansilla), Hospital de Navarra (José Javier García Irure), Hospital Costa del Sol-Marbella (Alfonso del Arco Jiménez), Hospital General de Valencia (Concepción Gimeno Cardona, Juan Carlos Valía, Núria Tormo Palop, Vicente Abril, Josefina Rifa, Maria Jesus, Martinez Garcia), Consorci Hospitalari de Vic (Joseph Vilaró Pujals, Marian Navarro Aguirre, Ana Vilamala), Policlínica Guipúzkoa (José Antonio Jiménez Alfaro, Carlos Reviejo Jaca), Hospital Puerta del Mar (Pilar Marín Casanova, Francisca Guerreo, Evelyn Shaw, Virginia Plasencia,), Complejo Hospitalario de Soria (Teresa Nebreda Mayoral, María José Fernández Calavia, Susana García de Cruz, Carmen Aldea Mansilla), Hospital Universitario de Alicante (Esperanza Merino de Lucas, Alfredo Zorraquino, Sergio Reus Bañuls), Hospital Infanta Cristina (Eugenio Garduno Eseverri, Luis López Sánchez), Hospital Universitario Central de Asturias (Ana Fleites Gutiérrez, Azucena Rodríguez Guardado, Alfonso Moreno), Hospital Donostia (José María García-Arenzana Anguera), Complejo Hospitalario Torrecárdenas (Serafín López Palmero, Manuel Rodríguez Maresca), Complejo Hospitalario Xeral-Calde Lugo (Fernando García Garrote, José Varela Otero, María del Pilar Alonso), Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía de Córdoba (Elisa Vidal Verdú, Fernando Rodríguez López), Hospital Universitario Santiago Compostela (Fernanda Pardo Sánchez, E. Ferrer Vizoso, B.Regueiro Garcia), Hospital Sant Pau (Mercé Gurgui, Roser Pericas,Virginia Pomar), Hospital Galdakao-Usansolo (Pedro María Olaechea Astigarraga, Rafael Ayarza Igartua), Hospital Son Dureta (María Dolores Maciá Romero, Enrique Ruiz de Gopegui Bordes), Hospital Puerta de Hierro (María Isabel Sánchez Romero), Hospital Juan Grande (Jesús García Mata, María José Goyanes, Cristina Morales Mateos), Hospital San Cecilio (José Hernández Quero, Trinidad Escobar Lara), Hospital Sant Joan de Reus (Frederic Ballester Bastardie, Simona Iftimie, Isabel Pujol Bajador), Hospital de Motril (María Isabel Galán Navarro, María Luz Cádiz Gurrea), Hospital San Agustín (Carmen Amores Antequera, Montserrat Gómez,Purificación Cantudo), Hospital de Granollers (Carmina Martí Salas, Jordi Cuquet Peragosa,Antonio Moreno Flores, Luis Anibarro García), Hospital de Segovia (Susana Hernando Real, Pablo A. Carrero González), Complejo Hospitalario de Pontevedra (María Angeles Pallarés González, Sergio Rodríguez Fernández), Hospital de Bellvitge (Miquel Pujol Rojo, Fe Tubau), Hospital Virgen de la Victoria de Málaga (Enrique Nuno Alvarez, María Ortega Torres), Hospital Doctor Moliner (Salvador Giner Almaraz, María Rosa Roca Castelló, Manuela Castillo, Elena Hortelano), Hospital 12 de Octubre (Fernando Chaves Sánchez, Ana García Reyne), Hospital del Mar (Juan Pablo Horcajada Gallego, Concha Segura), Hospital San Agustín de Avilés (Gema Sierra Dorado, Raquel Yano Escudero), Complejo Hospitalario Materno Insular de Gran Canaria (María Elena Dorta Hung, CristóbalRosarioQ).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>M.L. performed laboratory experiments and analysed results. A.R. performed bioinformatic analysis. J.P.-F. performed bioinformatic analysis. L.B. performed laboratory experiments, analysed results and critically reviewed the manuscript. L.F.G. performed laboratory experiments and analysed results. R.T. performed laboratory experiments and analysed results. F.F.-C. contributed materials and critically reviewed the manuscript. L.M.-M. contributed materials and critically reviewed the manuscript. J.V. contributed materials and critically reviewed the manuscript. A.P. contributed materials and critically reviewed the manuscript. G.B. contributed materials and critically reviewed the manuscript. M.T conceived the study, analysed results and wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par42">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>del Mar Tomas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hospital outbreak caused by a carbapenem-resistant strain of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumanni</italic>i: patient prognosis and risk-factors for colonisation and infection</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2005.01184.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15966971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garnacho-Montero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in critically ill patients: Molecular epidemiology, clinical features and predictors of mortality</article-title><source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eimc.2015.11.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26821549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology and control of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in health care facilities</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>1;42</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/500202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16447117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diene</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The rhizome of the multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter aerogene</italic>s genome reveals how new “killer bugs” are created because of a sympatric lifestyle</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23071100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkshoorn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An increasing threat in hospitals: multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18007677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obeng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratama</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsas</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Significance of Mutualistic Phages for Bacterial Ecology and Evolution</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2015.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26826796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis and relatedness of P2-like phages of the <italic toggle="yes">Burkholderia cepacia</italic> complex</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>599</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-11-599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3091744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20973964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Matos, R. C. <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> prophage dynamics and contributions to pathogenic traits. <italic toggle="yes">PLoS Genet</italic><bold>9</bold>(6) 10.1371/journal.pgen.1003539 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3675006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23754962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard-Varona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abedon</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lysogeny in nature: mechanisms, impact and ecology of temperate phages</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2017.16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28291233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5520141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum-quenching microbial infections: mechanisms and implications</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>29</volume><issue>362(1483)</issue><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2007.2045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2435583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochiai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morohoshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AmiE, a novel N-acylhomoserine lactone acylase belonging to the amidase family, from the activated-sludge isolate A<italic toggle="yes">cinetobacter</italic> sp. strain Ooi24</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>6919</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02190-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25172868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4249007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bzdrenga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biotechnological applications of quorum quenching enzymes</article-title><source>Chem Biol Interact.</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><issue>267</issue><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2016.05.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27223408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">López, M. <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. GEIH-GEMARA (SEIMC). Quorum sensing network in clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">baumanni</italic>i: AidA is a new quorum quenching enzyme. <italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic><bold>22</bold>;12(3), 10.1371/journal.pone.0174454 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0174454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5362224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28328989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stacy</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attenuation of quorum sensing in the pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> using non-native N-Acyl homoserine lactones</article-title><source>ACS Chem Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><issue>7(10)</issue><fpage>1719</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cb300351x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3477293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22853441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural conjugative plasmids induce bacterial biofilm development</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>26</volume><issue>412(6845)</issue><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35086581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dougherty, K. <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. Multiple phenotypic changes associated with large-scale horizontal gene transfer. <italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic><bold>21</bold>(9(7)), 10.1371 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0102170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4105467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25048697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zgoda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A relationship between RP4 plasmid acquisition and phenotypic changes in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> R2fN</article-title><source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source><year>2001</year><volume>79</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010262817895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11520003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harrison, E. <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. Plasmid carriage can limit bacteria-phage coevolution. <italic toggle="yes">Biol Lett</italic><bold>11</bold>(8), 10.1098/rsbl.2015.0361 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1098/rsbl.2015.0361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4571675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26268992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosqueda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GEIH-GEMARA (SEIMC) and REIPI. Characterization of plasmids carrying the <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-24/40</sub> carbapenemase gene and the genes encoding the AbkA/AbkB proteins of a toxin/antitoxin system</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2014</year><volume>69</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2629</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dku179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24879663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alivisatos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unified Microbiome Initiative Consortium.MICROBIOME. A unified initiative to harness Earth’s microbiomes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>350</volume><issue>6260</issue><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aac8480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26511287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahony</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nauta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Sinderen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteriophage orphan DNA methyltransferases: insights from their bacterial origin, function, and occurrence</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>79</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>7547</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02229-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24123737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3837797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Methyltransferases acquired by lactococcal 936-type phage provide protection against restriction endonuclease activity</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2164-15-831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4190342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25269955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of two phenotypically-similar but genomically-distinct <italic toggle="yes">Burkholderia cenocepacia</italic>-specific bacteriophages</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2164-13-223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3483164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelberg-Kulka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> mazEF-mediated cell death as a defense mechanism that inhibits the spread of phage P1</article-title><source>Mol Genet Genomics</source><year>2004</year><volume>272</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-004-1048-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15316771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witkowski</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grice</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prophage induction and differential RecA and UmuDAb transcriptome regulation in the DNA damage responses of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baylyi</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><issue>9(4)</issue><fpage>e93861</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3978071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24709747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Touchon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genomic diversification of the whole <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> genus: origins, mechanisms, and consequences</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6(10)</issue><fpage>2866</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evu225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4224351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25313016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> clinical isolates reveals extensive genomic variation and diverse antibiotic resistance determinants</article-title><source>BMC Genomics.</source><year>2014</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>1163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2164-15-1163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4367897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graña-Miraglia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid Gene Turnover as a Significant Source of Genetic Variation in a Recently Seeded Population of a Healthcare-Associated Pathogen</article-title><source>Front Microbiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>1817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5611417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28979253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chibani-Chennoufi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruttin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillmann</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüssow</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phage-host interaction: an ecological perspective</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3677</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.12.3677-3686.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15175280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC419959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing in bacteria</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.55.1.165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Labrie</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moineau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteriophage resistance mechanisms</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abedon</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteriophage host range and bacterial resistance</article-title><source>Adv Appl Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2164(10)70007-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20359459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Høyland-Kroghsbo</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maerkedahl</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svenningsen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A quorum-sensing-induced bacteriophage defense mechanism</article-title><source>MBio</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4(1)</issue><fpage>e00362</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mBio.00362-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3624510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23422409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gram</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middelboe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vibriophages and their interactions with the fish pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio anguillarum</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3128</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.03544-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24610858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4018917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middelboe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vibriophages Differentially Influence Biofilm Formation by <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio anguillarum</italic> Strains</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>81</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>4489</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00518-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25911474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4475874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diggle</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cámara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>4-quinolone signalling in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: old molecules, new perspectives</article-title><source>Int J Med Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>296</volume><issue>2-3</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmm.2006.01.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16483840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diggle</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acyl-homoserine lactone quorum sensing: from evolution to application</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-micro-092412-155635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23682605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saucedo-Mora</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection of Functional Quorum Sensing Systems by Lysogenic Bacteriophages in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>1669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5583629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28912771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiland-Bräuer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinnow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel reporter for identification of interference with acyl homoserine lactone and autoinducer-2 quorum sensing</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>81</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1477</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.03290-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25527543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4309711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiland-Bräuer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kisch</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinnow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly Effective Inhibition of Biofilm Formation by the First Metagenome-Derived AI-2 Quenching Enzyme</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4942472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27468282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoque</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quorum Regulated Resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio cholerae</italic> against Environmental Bacteriophages</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>37956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep37956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5124996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27892495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diggle</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friman</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial cell-to-cell signaling promotes the evolution of resistance to parasitic bacteriophages</article-title><source>Ecol Evol</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><issue>7(6)</issue><fpage>1936</fpage><lpage>1941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5355186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28331600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurenaite</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markuckas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suziedeliene</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of type II toxin-antitoxin systems in the opportunistic pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2013</year><volume>195</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>3165</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00237-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23667234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3697630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fernández-García, L. <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. Toxin-Antitoxin Systems in Clinical Pathogens. <italic toggle="yes">Toxins</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Basel</italic>) <bold>20</bold>;8(7), 10.3390/toxins8070227 (2016)<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/toxins8070227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4963858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27447671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Melderen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saavedra De Bast</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial toxin-antitoxin systems: more than selfish entities?</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e1000437</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19325885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2654758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yahara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic addiction: selfish gene’s strategy for symbiosis in the genome</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>172</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1309</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.105.042895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16299387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1456228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Melderen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxin-antitoxin systems: why so many, what for?</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2010.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21041110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical Antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Strains with Higher Susceptibility to Environmental Phages than Antibiotic-sensitive Strains</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><issue>7(1)</issue><fpage>6319</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-06688-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5524697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28740225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GEIH/GEMARA/REIPI-Ab20101 Group. Epidemiologic and clinical impact of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> colonization and infection: a reappraisal</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2014</year><volume>93</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000000036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25181313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4602455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Cuenca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>grupo del proyecto GEIH-REIPI-Ab 2010. <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> activity of 18 antimicrobial agents against clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> spp.: multicenter national study GEIH-REIPI-Ab 2010</article-title><source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eimc.2012.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22939566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rumbo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spanish Group of Nosocomial Infections and Mechanisms of Action and Resistance to Antimicrobials (GEIH-GEMARA); Spanish Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases (SEIMC); Spanish Network for Research in Infectious Diseases(REIPI). Contribution of efflux pumps, porins, and β-lactamases to multidrug resistance in clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2013</year><volume>57</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5247</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00730-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23939894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3811325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lukashin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borodovsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GeneMark.hmm: new solutions for gene finding</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><issue>26(4)</issue><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/26.4.1107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC147337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><issue>21(18)</issue><fpage>3674</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The RAST Server: rapid annotations using subsystems technology</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2164-9-75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2265698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18261238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagesen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNAmmer: consistent and rapid annotation of ribosomal RNA genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>3100</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1888812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>1</volume><issue>25(5)</issue><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.5.0955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC146525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2010. Pan-genome sequence analysis using Panseq: an online tool for the rapid analysis of core and accessory genomic regions</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2105-11-461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2949892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20843356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the core and accessory genomes of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> using bioinformatic tools Spine and AGEnt</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2164-15-737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4155085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25168460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PHAST: a fast phage search tool</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><issue>(Web Server issue)</issue><fpage>W347</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21672955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3125810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PHASTER: a better, faster version of the PHAST phage search tool</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><issue>44(W1)</issue><fpage>W16</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4987931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27141966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2012. BLAT-the BLAST-like alignment tool</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.229202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC187518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>InterProScan–an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.9.847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krzywinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.092759.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19541911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2752132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colvin</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clokie</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clokie</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetically diverse <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium difficile</italic> strains harboring abundant prophages in an estuarine environment</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>79</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>6236</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01849-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23913427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3811203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhargava</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capalash</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyocyanin stimulates quorum sensing-mediated tolerance to oxidative stress and increases persister cell populations in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2014</year><volume>82</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3417</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01600-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24891106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4136213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of surface motility in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology.</source><year>2011</year><volume>157</volume><issue>Pt 9</issue><fpage>2534</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.049791-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3352170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kropinski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of the rate of attachment of bacteriophage to cells</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>501</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60327-164-6_15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19066819</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>