<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Synth Syst Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Synth Syst Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3301</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ssb</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Synthetic and Systems Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-805X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>KeAi Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10965436</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10965436.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10965436</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10965436</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38545458</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.synbio.2024.03.002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-805X(24)00036-X</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity and mechanism of X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qunlin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuanxiu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="B">Bin</given-names></name><email>zhangbin2919@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>College of Bioscience and Bioengineering, Jiangxi Agriculture University, Nanchang, 330045, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Jiangxi Engineering Laboratory for the Development and Utilization of Agricultural Microbial Resources, Nanchang, 330045, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Collaborative Innovation Center of Postharvest Key Technology and Quality Safety of Fruits and Vegetables in Jiangxi Province, Nanchang, 330045, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. College of Bioscience and Bioengineering, Jiangxi Agriculture University, Nanchang, 330045, China. <email>zhangbin2919@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0015">Those authors contributed equally to this study.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">456111</issue-id><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-17 00:25:13.560"><day>17</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is a pathogenic bacterium widespread in human environments, especially in intensive care units, and is associated with high morbidity and infection rates. Multiple drug resistance in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> frequently leads to the death of patients, making the development of multi-effect antibacterial agents against this bacterium a research hotspot. We have previously found that the X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide can effectively inhibit the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium digitatum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic>. Herein, we evaluated the antibacterial activity of X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> by determining the minimum inhibitory concentration, inhibition zone, and growth curve. The increase in extracellular alkaline phosphatase and the leakage of intracellular compounds confirmed the effect of X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide on the cell wall and membrane. Changes in reactive oxygen species, malondialdehyde, ATP, reducing sugar, soluble protein, and pyruvate content demonstrated that the incubation with X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide affected energy metabolism and oxidative stress. Consistent with the physiological characteristics, transcriptomics analysis indicated that incubation with X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide significantly induced changes in the expression of 2339 genes, including 1262 upregulated and 1077 downregulated genes, which participate in oxidative phosphorylation, ribosome, quorum sensing, fatty acid degradation, glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, and citrate cycle pathways. These results provide a fundamental basis for investigating the mechanism of X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide as a potential drug against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><alt-text id="alttext0010">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ga1.jpg"/></fig></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>Antimicrobial agents</kwd><kwd>Antibiotic resistance</kwd><kwd>Hospital-acquired infections</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010"><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is the most significant opportunistic pathogen in hospital settings and is capable of high transmissibility, morbidity, and mortality in immunocompromised individuals [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Because of its plastic genome, when faced with adversity and stress (desiccation, extreme pH and temperature, nutrient levels, and antibiotic use), the bacterium rapidly mutates to adapt and survive in harsh environments (human or environmental vectors) [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The use of antibiotics has led to an increase in antibiotic resistance, posing a threat to social health. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections mainly manifest as ventilator-associated pneumonia, meningitis, skin or soft tissue infections, and wound infections [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Hospital-acquired infections present in patients with severe trauma or burns, invasive surgical procedures, immunosuppressants, medical device use, and community-acquired infections are common in individuals with serious underlying diseases (diabetes mellitus, alcoholism, and obstructive pulmonary disorders) [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> has a mortality rate of up to 68% and an attributable mortality rate of up to 36.5% and contributes to the mortality associated with COVID-19 [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">Currently, β-lactams, fluoroquinolones, tetracyclines, polymyxins, aminoglycosides, lincosamides, and macrolides, capable of interfering the synthesis of nucleic acid, protein, cell wall, and cell membrane, are used for the treatment of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> develops drug resistance by changing membrane permeability, overexpressing efflux pumps, expressing β-lactamase and aminoglycoside modifying enzyme, and changing the target sites [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Thus, owing to the pressure of drug resistance and scarcity, new therapeutic strategies, such as antimicrobial peptides, metabolic interference therapy, photodynamic therapy, and phage therapy are urgently required [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) found in various organisms are small molecular peptides generally composed of 10–60 amino acids with excellent antibacterial, antiviral, and antitumor effects. AMPs are effective and promising substitutes for antibiotics because of their ability to destroy cell membranes and walls, inhibit the synthesis of proteins and nucleic acids, and induce apoptosis and necrosis [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Almost all known bioactive microbial metabolites are produced by prokaryotes and eukaryotic fungi. Among them, <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces</italic> produce 39% of all microbial metabolites in eukaryotes [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Secondary metabolites produced by <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces</italic> exhibit crucial activities and can be used as drugs to treat cancer, bacterial infections, and other immune diseases [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. For instance, vancomycin produced by <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces orientalis</italic> possesses antimicrobial activity against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition, various AMPs, including ZY4, cecropin-4, WLBU2-cationic amphipathic peptide, CL defensin, and FLIP 7 display significant therapeutic effects against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p id="p0020">In a previous study, we isolated an antimicrobial oligopeptide from <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces lavendulae</italic> X33, named X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide (X33 AMOP), and found that it has superior bactericidal effect against <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium digitatum</italic> [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In the present study, we assessed the antibacterial potential of X33 AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and elucidated its intrinsic inhibitory mechanism. This is the first report on the antibacterial effect and plausible mechanism of action of X33 AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, which contributes to the development of a novel strategy for anti-inflammatory drugs.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Strains and culture conditions</title><p id="p0025"><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 was obtained from the Institute of Pathogenic Microorganisms, College of Bioscience and Bioengineering, Jiangxi Agricultural University, China. The strain was cultured on Luria-Bertani (LB) agar at 37 °C and stored at 4 °C for further use. The preparation of the X33 AMOP was consistent with that of a previous study [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Growth inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in response to X33 AMOP</title><p id="p0030">The antibacterial effect of X33 AMOP was studied using the standard broth dilution method and observing <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> visible growth. The lowest X33 AMOP concentration without visible growth after shaking for 24 h is the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC). To determine the minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC), the suspension from the test tube without visible growth in the MIC determination, was placed on LB agar and the number of colonies was counted after incubation. The MBC is the lowest antimicrobial concentration depicting no bacterial growth on the LB agar, as previously described [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The experiment was performed in triplicates.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Antibacterial assay using the Oxford cup method</title><p id="p0035">The antibacterial effect of X33 AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was determined using the Oxford cup method, as previously described [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The diameter of antibacterial circle was expressed as the mean ± standard error.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Effect of X33 AMOP on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> growth kinetics</title><p id="p0040">A growth curve was constructed to determine the growth inhibitory effect of X33 AMOP on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. The growth kinetics of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> with and without X33 AMOP treatment was determined. Bacteria were grown at 37 °C with 200 rpm shaking, and the absorbance at 600 nm was determined through ultraviolet spectrophotometry every 2 h. Growth curves were drawn using the absorption determined, as previously described [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Cell viability determination using XTT</title><p id="p0045">XTT [2, 3-bis (2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium-5-carboxanilide] (0.5 mg/mL) was dissolved in PBS, and menadione (1 mmol/L) was dissolved in acetone. XTT and menadione were filtered through a 0.22 μm sterile filter stored at −20 °C. Cells were added to LB medium containing different concentrations of X33 AMOP. For use, menadione was added to XTT at a final concentration of 1 μmmol/L. In this study, the cells were added to the LB media with different concentrations of X33 AMOP for 4 and 8 h. Then, collected the cells by centrifugation and added the XTT-menadione solution to the samples and incubated for 2 h before the absorbance at 490 nm was determined [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Scanning electron microscope and alkaline phosphatase (AKP) assay</title><p id="p0050">To visually observe the effect of X33 AMOP on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, we used a scanning electron microscope (SEM). Bacteria were exposed to the MIC for X33 AMOP for 8 h. Bacteria were fixed with 2.5% glutaraldehyde for more than 12 h at low temperatures (4 °C). SEM imaging was performed as described previously [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The cells were cultured with concentrations of X33 AMOP, and supernatants samples were taken by centrifugation to measure the content of AKP. The extracellular AKP activity was measured using an AKP kit (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China), the measurement method was performed as described previously [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Reducing sugar and protein determinations</title><p id="p0055">To measure reducing sugar and protein leaking from the membrane, bacteria were added to LB media with different X33 AMOP concentrations, and incubated for 4 and 8 h at 37 °C with 200 rpm shaking. Samples were centrifuged at 1000 rpm for 10 min, and the supernatant were collected to determine reducing sugar and proteins.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) determination</title><p id="p0060">ROS produced by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were evaluated using a ROS assay kit (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute). 2′, 7′-dichlorofluorescein diacetate can be oxidized by ROS to dichlorofluorescein, which has a maximum absorption peak at an excitation wavelength of 488 nm and emission wavelength of 525 nm [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The bacterial culture was treatment with X33 AMOP and incubated at 37 °C with 200 rpm shaking. After incubation for 2, 4, 6, and 8 h, the cells were exposed to the DCFH-DA in the dark for 60 min to determine ROS production.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Membrane lipid peroxidation test</title><p id="p0065">Lipid peroxides are indicators of oxidative stress, and malondialdehyde (MDA) is the product of membrane lipid peroxidation, which reflects the degree of lipid peroxidation and, subsequently, the degree of cellular damage. MDA forms complexes with thiobarbituric acid and can be quantified spectrophotometrically [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Briefly, bacterial were treated with X33 AMOP and collected by centrifugation after 4 and 8 h of incubation. After cell disruption, TBA solution was added and incubated at 95 °C for 40 min. The supernatant was centrifuged to determine the absorbance value after cooling to room temperature with ice water.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Pyruvate determination</title><p id="p0070">Normal pyruvate metabolism is crucial for catabolism and anabolism, affecting the synthesis of carbohydrates and proteins. Therefore, we measured the content of pyruvic acid. Cells and different X33 AMOP concentrations were added to LB medium. The cultured samples were collected and subsequently used to determine the pyruvic acid content, as previously described [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><label>2.11</label><title>ATP, reducing sugar, and soluble protein determinations</title><p id="p0075">The cells were exposed to different concentrations of X33 AMOP for 8 h at 37 °C with 200 rpm shaking. Centrifuge collection of bacterial cells and the intracellular ATP levels were measured using an ATP content kit ((Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute) [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Bacteria were collected after culturing for 4 h and 8 h. The supernatant obtained after grinding and crushing bacteria was used to determine the reducing sugar and soluble protein contents. An anthrone-sulfuric acid assay was used to test the reducing sugar content, and protein was detected using a protein detection kit (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute), the measurement method was performed as described previously [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><label>2.12</label><title>RNA sequencing</title><p id="p0080">Bacteria were cultured in LB medium for 4 h and divided into a treatment group with the MIC for X33 AMOP and a control group without X33 AMOP. After cultured, the cells were collected and RNA was extracted using the TRIzol® reagent. The concentration, purity, and integrity of the RNA were tested and used for subsequent library construction after meeting the requirements. A TruSeq™ RNA sample preparation kit was used to construct the RNA-seq library. After removal of rRNA using the Ribo-Zero Magnetic kit, mRNA was used as template for reverse transcription synthesis of cDNA using the SuperScript double-stranded cDNA synthesis kit, and then an A base was added at the 3′ end. Following PCR amplification, the paired-end RNA-seq library was sequenced using an Illumina HiSeq X Ten.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.13"><label>2.13</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0085">Data for experimental results were the mean and standard deviation values from three independent experiments and are expressed as mean ± standard deviation. To analyze the difference between control and treatment groups, one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Duncan's post hoc test were performed using SPSS statistical software. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values of &lt;0.05 were regarded significant and asterisks are used to indicate significant differences between control and treatment groups.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>X33 AMOP antibacterial activity against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic></title><p id="p0090">To investigate the antibacterial activity of X33 AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, we first conducted a standard broth dilution method that resulted in a MIC and MBC of 78.13 and 312.50 μg/mL, respectively (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, the Oxford cup test revealed bacteriostasis when the cells were treated with X33 AMOP. The antimicrobial diameter at X33 AMOP concentration of 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC reached 14.16 ± 0.83, 15.94 ± 0.87, and 16.88 ± 0.71 mm, respectively (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). The degree of growth disturbance of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in response to X33 AMOP was concentration-dependent. Furthermore, the growth of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was seriously disturbed by the treatment with X33 AMOP (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). The OD<sub>600</sub> of the 1/4 MIC treatment group was 0.33 ± 0.0001 after 12 h of cultivation and represents a 68.97% decrease compared with that of the control group (1.07 ± 0.02). To further confirm the growth inhibitory effect of X33 AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, we used the XTT assay, which determines cell viability, to assess the living state of the cells. In viable cells, mitochondrial dehydrogenase reduces XTT to a formazan product, which can be determined through spectrophotometry to evaluate cell viability [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>C, after 4 h of X33 AMOP treatment at 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC, the surviving cells of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were 63.18%, 54.82%, and 49.75%, respectively. The surviving cells of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> decreased by 30.27%, 25.98%, and 23.02%, respectively, after 8 h of X33 AMOP incubation. These findings show that X33 AMOP significantly retarded <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> growth.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The MIC and MFC determination.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Concentrations (μg/mL)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2500</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1250</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">625</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">312.5</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">156.25</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.125</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.0625</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clear (-, +) a</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Colony (-, +) b</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>a Minimum inhibitory concentration, Minimum bactericidal concentration.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Effects of X33 AMOP on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. (A) The zone of inhibition of different X33 concentrations AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. (B) The growth curves of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. The different colors show the growth curves at different X33 AMOP concentrations. (C) Surviving cells of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> after treatment with X33 AMOP. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, NS: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Effect of X33 AMOP on cell structure and wall</title><p id="p0095">To investigate the changes in the physiological phenotypes induced by X33 AMOP, we first performed a morphological imaging test that revealed significant variations in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. The cell surface of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> treated with X33 AMOP for 4 h was clearly deformed and sunken, whereas that of the control group (0 h) was smooth and regular (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A and B). When treated with X33 AMOP for 8 h, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> cells were further crumpled into a wrinkled and severely damaged morphology (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>C). These images indicated that X33 AMOP induced changes in cell morphology and damage. We evaluated AKP activity to determine the effect of X33 AMOP on the cell wall. Changes in extracellular AKP levels reflect changes in the cell wall permeability and integrity. As shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>D, the extracellular AKP levels increased after treatment with X33 AMOP for 4 h. The AKP content for the 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC treatment groups was 1.85 ± 0.04, 2.15 ± 0.02, and 2.48 ± 0.23 U/L, respectively, which was higher than that of the control group (1.57 ± 0.04). These results suggested that X33 AMOP caused cell wall damage and increased cell wall permeability.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Effects of the different X33 AMOP concentrations on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> cell structure. Scanning electron microscopy of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> cells treated with X33 AMOP at the MIC for (A) 0 h, (B) 4 h, and (C) 8 h. (D) Alkaline phosphatase activity of the different X33 AMOP concentrations on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii.</italic> (E) Reducing sugar leakage of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> after treatment by X33 AMOP. (F) Protein leakage of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> after treatment by X33 AMOP. The different colors show the growth of the different X33 AMOP concentrations. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, NS: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>X33 AMOP incubation destroyed <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> cell membrane integrity</title><p id="p0100">The cell membrane is responsible for the uptake and release of cellular substances. Cell membrane integrity is commonly measured based on the secretion of reducing sugars and proteins [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Compared with the control group (37.36 ± 0.47 μg/mL), the extracellular reducing sugar increased by 1.73-fold (1/4 MIC), 1.84-fold (1/2 MIC), and 2.92-fold (MIC) after treatment with X33 AMOP for 4 h (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>E). In contrast, the extracellular reducing sugar contents reached 62.08 ± 2.25, 84.03 ± 5.41, and 112.22 ± 1.71 μg/mL when exposed to 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC for X33 AMOP for 8 h, respectively, and represents a higher amount than that of the control group (42.24 ± 0.76 μg/mL) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>E). In addition, after the incubation of 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC of X33 AMOP for 8 h, the protein leakage from <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> reached 14.28 ± 0.10, 16.29 ± 0.03, and 18.51 ± 0.07 μg/mL, higher than that for the control group (12.36 ± 0.13 μg/mL) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>F). These findings suggest that X33 AMOP causes dose- and time-dependent protein and reduced sugar leakage in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>X33 AMOP induced ROS accumulation in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic></title><p id="p0105">Accumulation of ROS accelerates cell death. In the present study, ROS levels increased after exposure to X33 AMOP in a time- and concentration-dependent manner. As shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>A, the highest ROS levels were observed after exposure to X33 AMOP MIC. The MDA concentration, an oxidative product of ROS, also increased upon exposure to X33 AMOP. As shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B, the MDA contents after incubation with X33AMOP 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC reached 8.05 ± 0.08, 9.10 ± 0.38, and 10.14 ± 0.15 μmol/g and represents a remarkable increase in the MDA content in the treatment group. These results suggest that X33 AMOP increases oxidative damage in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Effects of the different X33 AMOP concentrations on the oxidative stress level in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. (A) The fluorescence intensity of dichlorofluorescein (fluorescence intensity is proportional to ROS). (B) The MDA contents at the different X33 AMOP concentrations. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, NS: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Effect of X33 AMOP on changes in the cellular content</title><p id="p0110">To further evaluate whether <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> cell contents were affected by X33 AMOP, we measured the intracellular concentrations of pyruvic acid, ATP, reducing sugars, and proteins. Intracellular pyruvic acid content decreased by 3.47%, 10.52%, and 23.34% after 4 h of incubation with 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC of X33 AMOP, respectively (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). The amount of pyruvic acid produced decreased over time (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). ATP determination using the luciferase bioluminescence assay showed that the fluorescence significantly decreased after treatment with X33 AMOP, indicating that X33 AMOP inhibited energy metabolism in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>B). Subsequently, the intracellular protein levels in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were determined at 0, 2, 4, 6, and 8 h after treatment with X33 AMOP. As shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>C, the intracellular <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> proteins were reduced to 6.06, 5.02, and 4.89 g/L when induced with 1/4 MIC, 1/2 MIC, and MIC XXE AMOP concentration and were significantly lower than that of the control group (8.16 g/L). We measured the intracellular content of reducing sugars after 2–8 h of incubation. Consistent with our hypothesis, the intracellular reducing sugar content was significantly reduced following treatment with X33 AMOP (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>D). These results suggest that X33 AMOP disrupts the anabolism of the cellular components of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Effects of the different X33 AMOP concentrations on the cellular contents of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. (A) The pyruvic acid content of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> at the different X33 AMOP concentrations. (B) The intracellular ATP of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> at the different X33 AMOP concentrations (The fluorescence value is proportional to ATP). (C) The intracellular protein contents of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> at the different X33 AMOP concentrations. (D) The intracellular reducing sugar content of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> at the different X33 AMOP concentrations. The different colors show different concentrations of X33 AMOP. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, NS: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Transcriptome profiling of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> exposed to X33 AMOP</title><p id="p0115">According to the physiological and biochemical findings, X33 AMOP inhibited <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> growth. Subsequently, we used RNA-seq to examine the inhibitory mechanisms and determine the molecular mechanism of action of X33 AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, which may serve as a guide for the development of new medications. Quality trimming was applied to the raw reads to produce clean reads. As shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>,2.55 million clean reads were acquired from 2.91 million raw reads in the control group, while 2.5 million clean reads were obtained from 2.86 million raw reads in the treatment group (treated with 78.13 μg/mL X33 AMOP, or the T group). The read quality macroscopically mirrored the caliber of the library building and sequencing of the sample. The findings demonstrated that Q20 and Q30 were higher than 85% and that the error rate was less than 0.1%, demonstrating that all sequencing samples were clean and met the criteria for transcriptional analysis. Correlations between groups C and T were examined. Higher levels of expression similarity or better correlation between samples were indicated by a correlation coefficient closer to 1. According to <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A and B, the correlation coefficients between three parallel samples of the C group were 1.00–0.96, while those between C and T group were 0.24–0.41, indicating strong similarity between samples and high disparities across groups. A total of 4376 genes were expressed simultaneously, with 1262 upregulated and 1077 downregulated genes (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>C).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The quality of sequencing.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameters</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">C gruop</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">T group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Raw reads (million)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.91</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clean Reads (million)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clean Error Rate (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clean Q20 (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clean Q30 (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.68</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Expression analysis of different genes between the samples. (A) Biological replicate correlation analysis of samples. Different colors indicate correlation coefficients, while colors closer to red indicate higher gene expression similarity between samples. (B) Principal component analysis (PCA) of the samples. The x-axis represents the contribution of principal component 1 (PC1) to the sample, and the y-axis represents the contribution of principal component 2 (PC2) to the sample. (C) A volcano plot showing the expression analysis of the different genes. Volcano plot of DEGs with 1262 upregulated gene (red dots), and 1077 downregulated genes (blue dots), and the grey dots represent genes without significant expression differences.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><label>3.7</label><title>Kyoto Encyclopedia of genes and genomes (KEGG) and gene ontology (GO) analyses of differentially expressed genes (DEGs)</title><p id="p0120">To extensively examine the biological mechanisms and pathways involving DEGs, their biological functions were annotated and categorized based on GO and KEGG analyses. The top 20 upregulated genes were involved in biological processes and molecular functions according to GO analysis (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A). The distribution of DEGs among the biological processes was split between the regulation of RNA, cellular, and protein metabolisms. The DEGs were responsible for the following molecular functions: DNA binding, heterocyclic compound binding, organic cyclic compound binding, nucleic acid binding, transcription regulator activity, and DNA-binding transcription factor activity (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A). GO analysis showed that the downregulated genes were enriched in two term types and 64 hierarchies, including oxidoreductase activity, catalytic activity, oxidoreductase activity, NAD(P)H, tricarboxylic acid cycle, carboxylic acid catabolic process, organic acid catabolic process, and cellular catabolic process (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>B). Next, we performed KEGG pathway annotation and enrichment analysis of these DEGs to understand their functions. As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figs. 6</xref>C and 26 upregulated genes were clustered into ribosomes, biosynthesis of various secondary metabolites (part 3), and quorum sensing pathways. Downregulated genes were enriched in 31 pathways (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The top 20 pathways are shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>D, comprising a two-component system, pyruvate metabolism, citrate cycle, glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, and oxidative phosphorylation.<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>The GO and KEGG enrichment analyses of DEGs. The vertical axis represents GO Term or KEGG Pathway, while the horizontal axis represents the enrichment factor. The dot size represents the number of genes in the GO Term or KEGG Pathway, and the dot color corresponds to the different P-values. (A) Top 20 GO functions of the upregulated genes. (B) Top 20 GO functions of the downregulated genes. (C) Top 20 KEGG pathways enrichment of the upregulated genes. (D) Top 20 KEGG pathways enrichment of the upregulated genes.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0125">As <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is an opportunistic pathogen, antibiotics are the mainstay of treatment. New non-antibiotic medicines are urgently needed because of the strong bacterial survival owing to the complex drug resistance mechanisms, and AMPs are a possible substitute. To develop novel medications that can replace antibiotics, we explored the mechanism of action of X33 AMOP against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Cell wall damage in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> induced by X33 AMOP</title><p id="p0130">Peptidoglycan is a unique macromolecular structure in the bacterial cell wall that has important structural and physiological functions. Inhibition or interference of peptidoglycan biosynthesis is a key target for bacterial inhibition [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. We found that X33 AMOP affected cell wall-related metabolic pathways, such as those for starch, sucrose, and amino sugar metabolism [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The peptidoglycan biosynthesis-related genes, <italic toggle="yes">dacC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">murC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">murF</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">mrcB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ponA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">murG</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">mrdA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">murB</italic> were dramatically downregulated (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Penicillin-binding proteins (PBPs) participate in the synthesis of the cell wall and are the target proteins of β-lactam drugs. Antibiotics known as β-lactams attach to PBPs, prevent transglycosylase and transpeptidase activity, further impairs peptidoglycan synthesis, and cause cell wall lysis [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In this study, the transcription of the PBP-encoding genes <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_12920</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">dacC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">mrcB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ponA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">mrdA</italic> was reduced 1.14- to 4.61-folds, which is consistent with previous results that claimed that tetracycline therapy resulted in considerable downregulation of the genes responsible for the cell wall peptidoglycan production pathway [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. AKP is present between the cell wall and cell membrane and is an indicator of cell wall integrity [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Litsea cubeba</italic> essential oil can induce AKP leakage, thereby damaging the cell wall integrity [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Similar to the <italic toggle="yes">L. cubeba</italic> essential oil, the increase in extracellular AKP concentration further revealed the damage caused by X33 AMOP to the cell walls of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. X33 AMOP interferes with cell wall synthesis in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> to achieve bacteriostasis.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Differentially expression genes.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene name</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene description</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Log2FC(Treated/Control)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Padjust</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Regulate</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="11" align="left" colspan="1">Peptidoglycan biosynthesis<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">dacC</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">D-alanyl-d-alanine carboxypeptidase PBP5/6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.01E-236</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">murC</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UDP-N-acetylmuramate--l-alanine ligase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.06E-134</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">murF</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UDP-N-acetylmuramoyl-tripeptide--D-alanyl-d-alanine ligase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.69E-52</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mrcB</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">penicillin-binding protein 1B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.12E-81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ponA</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">penicillin-binding protein PBP1a</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.72E-51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">murG</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">undecaprenyldiphospho-muramoylpentapeptide beta-N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81E-59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mrdA</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">penicillin-binding protein 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.11E-47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">17525</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">d-alanine--d-alanine ligase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73E-29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">murB</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UDP-N-acetylmuramate dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.43E-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">02540</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">phosphatase PAP2 family protein</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.84E-15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">12920</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">substrate-binding domain-containing protein<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.61<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">lipopolysaccharide<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">18735</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">polysaccharide biosynthesis tyrosine autokinase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.13E-127</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">07855</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LPS-assembly protein LptD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.62E-87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_06305</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lauroyl acyltransferase<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.01<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09E-217<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Two-component system<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_11050</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">two-component system sensor histidine kinase PmrB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12E-23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_14515</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DNA-binding response regulator PmrA<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.83<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54E-09<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">Histidine metabolism<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">basG</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">acinetobactin biosynthesis histidine decarboxylase BasG</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003044706</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_00400</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">imidazolonepropionase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.03E-146</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">hutG</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">formimidoylglutamase<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.23<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22E-221<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Catalase<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">katE</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">catalase HPII</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">katG</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">catalase/peroxidase HPI<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.77<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Glutathione peroxidase<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_07425</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">glutathione peroxidase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72E-100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_18175</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">glutathione peroxidase<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.13<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.85E-101<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" align="left" colspan="1">TCA cycle<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_08825</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-oxo acid dehydrogenase subunit E2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.06E-54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">lldD</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FMN-dependent l-lactate dehydrogenase LldD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.36E-11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">citrate (Si)-synthase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.58E-45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">lpdA</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53E-250</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">lpdA</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.88E-80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_14275</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-oxoglutarate dehydrogenase E1 component</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.88E-50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">odhB</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-oxoglutarate dehydrogenase complex dihydrolipoyllysine-residue succinyltransferase<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.94<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.45E-218<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" colspan="1">Glycolysis/gluconeogenesis<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_13680</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">class 1 fructose-bisphosphatase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81E-42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_14360</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">iron-containing alcohol dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_02505</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADP-dependent glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.10E-257</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">pgi</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">glucose-6-phosphate isomerase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20E-63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_04235</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">phosphomannomutase/phosphoglucomutase</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.61E-86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ppsA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">phosphoenolpyruvate synthase<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.13<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06E-48<hr/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="23" align="left" colspan="1">Oxidative phosphorylation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_18205</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F0F1 ATP synthase subunit alpha</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.71E-48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">atpB</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F0F1 ATP synthase subunit A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02E-71</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">atpE</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F0F1 ATP synthase subunit C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.37E-30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">18215</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F0F1 ATP synthase subunit B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.45E-36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">18210</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F0F1 ATP synthase subunit delta</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.96E-35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">10020</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytochrome ubiquinol oxidase subunit I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">07260</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytochrome ubiquinol oxidase subunit I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20E-35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">cydB</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytochrome d ubiquinol oxidase subunit II</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.91</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">cydB</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytochrome d ubiquinol oxidase subunit II</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.16E-24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">cyoB</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytochrome o ubiquinol oxidase subunit I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66E-168</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">cyoC</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytochrome o ubiquinol oxidase subunit III</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18E-78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H0N28_11530</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytochrome o ubiquinol oxidase subunit IV</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.19E-26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoC</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit C/D</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.88E-50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoE</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit NuoE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14E-41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoF</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit NuoF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03E-138</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoG</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit NuoG</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoH</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit NuoH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.14E-256</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoI</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit NuoI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.91</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.74E-274</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoJ</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit J</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.30E-224</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoK</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit NuoK</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.96E-92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoL</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit L</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.57E-289</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoM</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">nuoN</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit NuoN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.14E-267</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><label>4.2</label><title>Change in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> cell membrane permeability induced by X33 AMOP</title><p id="p0135">The intracellular environment is partially stabilized by the cell membrane, which serves as a crucial barrier to the entry and exit of chemicals. In the present study, the significant increase in extracellular proteins and reducing sugars, and changes in cell structure (deformation and shrinkage) indicated that X33 AMOP may disrupt the cell membrane structure, leading to changes in the cell composition. Similar results were obtained in our previous study on <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium digitatum</italic> [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Membrane proteins are a crucial part of the cell membrane and are incorporated into the cell via lipopolysaccharides [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Downregulation of the genes <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_18735</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_07855</italic> related to lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis indicated that X33 AMOP had an effect on the cell membrane. In addition, we found that the pathways, including glycerophospholipid and glycerolipid metabolisms, related to cell membrane were affected by X33 AMOP [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The two-component system is a signal transduction pathway that senses and signals changes in the external environment and consists of a sensor kinase (histidine kinase) and its response regulator [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The two-component system is repaired when the cell membrane is damaged. In response to environmental stimuli, PmrB activates PmrA via phosphorylation. Consistent with our assumptions, various crucial genes related to the two-component system pathway were significantly downregulated after treatment with X33 AMOP. Among them, <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_14510</italic> encoding the two-component system sensor histidine kinase PmrB, <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_14515</italic> encoding the DNA-binding response regulator PmrA, <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_00400</italic> encoding imidazolone propionase, and <italic toggle="yes">hutG</italic> encoding formimidoylglutamase were significantly downregulated (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The changes in the expression of these genes were similar to those in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> treated with <italic toggle="yes">L. cubeba</italic> essential oil [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Based on the findings of cell content leakage, SEM, and additional integration with the transcriptome data, X33AMOP interferes with the cell membrane to exert an effect on it.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><label>4.3</label><title>X33 AMOP induced oxidative stress in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic></title><p id="p0140">Oxidative stress refers to the excessive production of ROS or metabolic disorders that exceed the ability of the endogenous antioxidant defense system to eliminate it. ROS include free radicals, which eventually lead to lipid peroxidation and damage cellular proteins, DNA, and ATP [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. After treatment with X33 AMOP, ROS, and MDA levels increased significantly, suggesting that X33 AMOP induced the production of toxic products. Superoxide dismutase, catalase, and glutathione peroxidase scavenge reactive oxygen species and reduce cell damage [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, the expression of genes encoding catalase (<italic toggle="yes">katE</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">katG</italic>) and glutathione peroxidase (<italic toggle="yes">H0N28_07425</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_18175</italic>) was downregulated by 2.11- to 4.95-folds, which prevented the synthesis of enzymes that scavenge ROS, resulting in oxidative damage to cells and cell membrane. Similar investigations have revealed that catalase and glutathione peroxidase are downregulated by alpha-mangostin to prevent biofilm development [<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Furthermore, the integrity of the cell membrane may change due to lipid peroxidation, which alters the lipid content of the membrane.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><label>4.4</label><title>X33 AMOP induced energy metabolism changes in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic></title><p id="p0145">Energy metabolism, consisting of the citrate cycle (TCA cycle), pyruvate metabolism, glycolysis, and oxidative phosphorylation, is extremely important for normal cellular activities. X33 AMOP treatment significantly affects the TCA cycle, pyruvate metabolism, glycolytic pathways, and oxidative phosphorylation in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. In response to X33 AMOP treatment, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> showed downregulation of 24 of 28 pyruvate metabolism genes, 16 of 17 TCA cycle genes, 31 of 32 oxidative phosphorylation genes, and 17 genes involved in glycolysis/gluconeogenesis. The rate-limiting enzymes in the pyruvate pathway, <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_08825</italic> encoding pyruvate dehydrogenase subunit E2, and <italic toggle="yes">lldD</italic> encoding FMN-dependent <sc>l</sc>-lactate dehydrogenase LldD, were considerably downregulated in pyruvate metabolism [<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In addition, the expression of genes related to TCA and glycolysis/gluconeogenesis were significantly downregulated, including rate-limiting enzyme citrate (Si)-synthase (<italic toggle="yes">gltA)</italic>, α-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase <italic toggle="yes">(lpdA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">lpdA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_14275</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">odhB)</italic>, fructose-bisphosphatase (<italic toggle="yes">H0N28_13680</italic>), phosphomannomutase/phosphoglucomutase (<italic toggle="yes">H0N28_04235</italic>), and phosphoenolpyruvate synthase (<italic toggle="yes">ppsA</italic>). Similarly, RNA-seq results after tetracycline induction in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> revealed downregulation of TCA gene expression, along with downregulation of glycolysis/gluconeogenesis gene expression [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Oxidative phosphorylation is a biochemical process involving coupling reactions between the energy released during the oxidation of substances and the synthesis of ATP by inorganic phosphate and ADP through the respiratory chain. The DEGs involved in energy generation and transformation, including F0F1 ATP synthase (<italic toggle="yes">H0N28_18205</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">atpB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">atpE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_18215,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_18210</italic>), cytochrome ubiquinol oxidase (<italic toggle="yes">H0N28_10020</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_07260</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cydB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cydB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cyoB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cyoC</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">H0N28_11530</italic>), and NADH-quinone oxidoreductase (<italic toggle="yes">nuoC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoF</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoG</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoH</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoI</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoJ</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoK</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoL</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuoM,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">nuoN</italic>) were downregulated, indicating that oxidative phosphorylation was blocked, which is consistent with the results of tobramycin treatment on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</p><p id="p0150">Numerous medications that are available to treat infection have MICs greater than X33 AMOP, such as imipenem (256 μg/mL) and Litsea cubeba essential oil (1.04 mg/mL), suggesting that X33 AMOP has a super inhibitory effect [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, current medications, like peptide Cec4, have a better therapeutic impact than X33 AMOP [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. But prior studies have shown that X33 AMOP is non-toxic, has no adverse effects, and inhibits both <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium digitatum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic>. For these reasons, X33 AMOP provides a good alternative against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infection.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0155">To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to demonstrate that X33 AMOP can inhibit <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> growth. X33 AMOP interfered with the TCA cycle, glycolysis, oxidative phosphorylation, pyruvate metabolism, and cell composition, which finally inhibited <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> cell growth. The discovery of X33 AMOP as a novel agent against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> highlights the great potential of peptides in the treatment of bacterial infections. We confirmed the potential efficacy of X33 AMOP in treating <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections. Therefore, the results of this study provide a possible target against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and a theoretical basis for the antibacterial activity of antimicrobial peptides.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0160">This study was funded by <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100012259</institution-id><institution>Major Discipline Academic and Technical Leaders Training Program of Jiangxi Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> [No. 20212BCJ23012], the <funding-source id="gs3">Department of Science Technology of Jiangxi Province</funding-source> (Grant No. 20171ACF60006), the Collaborative Innovation Center of Postharvest Key Technology and Quality Safety of Fruits and Vegetables in Jiangxi Province, and <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> [No. 32000057 and 32360021].</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec7"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="p0165">Not application.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0170"><bold>Qunlin Lu:</bold> Investigation, Methodology, Writing – original draft. <bold>Xiaoyu Wu:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Supervision, Writing – original draft. <bold>Yuan Fang:</bold> Investigation, Methodology. <bold>Yuanxiu Wang:</bold> Supervision, Validation. <bold>Bin Zhang:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Funding acquisition, Project administration, Supervision, Writing – review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interests</title><p id="p0175">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships thatcould have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Donoghue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sleator</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: an emerging opportunistic pathogen</article-title><source>Virulence</source><volume>3</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/viru.19700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3442836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennon</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uncovering the mechanisms of A<italic toggle="yes">cinetobacter baumannii</italic> virulence</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>16</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29249812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6571207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadani</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solanki</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of anti-bacterial activity of zinc oxide nanoparticle against carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1218</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29928271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5997932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyriakidis</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasileiou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pana</surname><given-names>Z.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tragiannidis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> antibiotic resistance mechanisms</article-title><source>Pathogens</source><volume>10</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10373</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens10030373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8003822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33808905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dexter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostoulias</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peleg</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanisms of disease caused by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1601</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31379771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6650576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Iron-rich conditions induce OmpA and virulence changes of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>12</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">725194</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.725194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8525545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34675899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rangel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chagas</surname><given-names>T.P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De-Simone</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections in times of COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Pathogens</source><volume>10</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1006</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens10081006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34451470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8399974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrancianu</surname><given-names>C.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheorghe</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czobor</surname><given-names>I.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chifiriuc</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance profiles, molecular mechanisms and innovative treatment strategies of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><volume>8</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>935</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8060935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32575913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7355832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vena</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giacobbe</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic options for difficult-to-treat <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections: a 2020 perspective</article-title><source>Expet Opin Pharmacother</source><volume>22</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14656566.2020.1817386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32915685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talapko</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mestrovic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juzbasic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eric</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horvat Aleksijevic</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides-mechanisms of action, antimicrobial effects and clinical applications</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1417</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11101417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36290075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9598582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berdy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thoughts and facts about antibiotics: where we are now and where we are heading</article-title><source>J Antibiot</source><volume>65</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ja.2012.27</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22511224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zin</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Badya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanafiah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latip</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-bacterial activity of endophytic Streptomyces sp. towards <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Annu Res Rev Biol</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>4075</fpage><lpage>4083</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samaddar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ammanathan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yarlagadda</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vancomycin derivativeinactivates carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and induces autophagy</article-title><source>ACS Chem Biol</source><volume>15</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>884</fpage><lpage>889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acschembio.0c00091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32195571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and proteomic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium digitatum</italic> in response to X33 antifungal extract treatment</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">584331</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.584331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7677231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33240238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and transcriptome analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> in response to X33 antimicrobial oligopeptide treatment</article-title><source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source><volume>13</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1123393</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2023.1123393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9892945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36743308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity and mechanism of <italic toggle="yes">Litsea cubeba</italic> L. Essential Oil against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><volume>16</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1934578X21999146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickliffe</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Limitation of the MTT and XTT assays for measuring cell viability due to superoxide formation induced by nano-scale TiO<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Toxicol Vitro</source><volume>25</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>2147</fpage><lpage>2151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tiv.2011.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21798338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel multifunctional silver nanocomposite serves as a resistance-reversal agent to synergistically combat carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>ACS Appl Mater Interfaces</source><volume>13</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>30434</fpage><lpage>30457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsami.1c10309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34161080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.-X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial mechanism and activities of black pepper chloroform extract</article-title><source>J Food Sci Technol</source><volume>52</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>8196</fpage><lpage>8203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13197-015-1914-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26604394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4648884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synergistic activity of capsaicin and colistin against colistin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: in vitro/vivo efficacy and mode of action</article-title><source>Front Pharmacol</source><volume>12</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">744494</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2021.744494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8484878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34603057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imène</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roger C</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catherine</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology of Mur ligases as an antibacterial target</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>94</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25130693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Putative hexameric glycosyltransferase functional unit revealed by the crystal structure of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> MurG</article-title><source>IUCrJ</source><volume>8</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/s2052252521003729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8256705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34258006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malkmes</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial mechanism and transcriptome analysis of ultra-small gold nanoclusters as an alternative of harmful antibiotics against Gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>J Hazard Mater</source><volume>416</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">126236</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.126236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34492988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vashist</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapil</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajeswari</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of penicillin-binding proteins (PBPs) in carbapenem resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Indian J Med Res</source><volume>133</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><comment>PMCID: PMC3103161</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3103161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tetu</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pokhrel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The transcriptomic signature of tigecycline in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">565438</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.565438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7652931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33193153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decreased biofilm formation ability of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> after spaceflight on China's Shenzhou 11 spacecraft</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>8</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e00763</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mbo3.763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6562233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30379419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koretke</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lupas</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>P.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of two-component signal transduction</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>17</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>1956</fpage><lpage>1970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a026297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Memon</surname><given-names>F.U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of drug-resistance <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> under the stress condition caused by <italic toggle="yes">Litsea cubeba</italic> L. essential oil via RNA sequencing</article-title><source>Genes</source><volume>12</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1003</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes12071003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34210052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8307839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thombre</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinde</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thaiparambil</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zende</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity and mechanism of inhibition of silver nanoparticles against extreme halophilic archaea</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>7</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1424</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27679615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5020055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowell</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Silva</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KatG and KatE confer <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> resistance to hydrogen peroxide but sensitize bacteria to killing by phagocytic respiratory burst</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><volume>148</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2016.02.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26860891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4792659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivaranjani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aravindraja</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karutha Pandian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veera Ravi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effect of alpha-mangostin on <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilms - an in vitro study</article-title><source>Biofouling</source><volume>34</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08927014.2018.1473387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29869541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress responses of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> strain Y during phenol degradation</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><volume>199</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-016-1310-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27771745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murarka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clomburg</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic analysis of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and a pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (PDHC)-deficient derivative reveals the role of PDHC in the fermentative metabolism of glucose</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>285</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>31548</fpage><lpage>31558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.121095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20667837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2951229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome profiling of lung innate immune responses potentially associated with the pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> acute lethal pneumonia</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>708</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32391015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7188829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashyap</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capalash</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobramycin stress induced differential gene expression in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><volume>79</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-022-02788-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35129693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial mechanism of peptide Cec4 against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Infect Drug Resist</source><volume>12</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>2417</fpage><lpage>2428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S214057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31496754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6689099</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0180">We thank Editage for the English corrections.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d36e968"><p id="ntpara0010">Peer review under responsibility of KeAi Communications Co., Ltd.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>