<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Iran J Pharm Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Iran J Pharm Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2163</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijpr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Brieflands</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Iranian Journal of Pharmaceutical Research : IJPR</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1735-0328</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1726-6890</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Brieflands</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12297010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12297010.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12297010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12297010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40718444</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5812/ijpr-160772</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Investigation of Peppermint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic>) Extract on the Inhibition of Biofilm Formation by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Strains Isolated from Clinical Samples</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="idm6860e9d350641" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Majidi Fard</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zahra</given-names></name><email>zahra.majidi.fard.79@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-6002-4341</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="idm6860e9d350649" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irani Mavi</surname><given-names initials="N">Negin</given-names></name><email>neginmv.79@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0002-6750-8784</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="idm6860e9d35064a" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names initials="S">Shokoofeh</given-names></name><email>shoko.akbari1376@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-7561-3579</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="idm6860e9d35064c" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erfani</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yousef</given-names></name><email>yerfani@sina.tums.ac.ir</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor6860e9d35064e" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0508-8123</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="idm6860e9d35068f" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eghtedari</surname><given-names initials="S">Sanaz</given-names></name><email>eghtedari.sanaz74@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7250-7925</contrib-id></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Biology, Faculty of Convergent Sciences and Technologies, Islamic Azad University, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Biology, Faculty of Basic Sciences, Central Tehran Branch, Islamic Azad University, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Medical Laboratory Sciences, School of Allied Medical Sciences, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Cellular and Molecular Research Center, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor6860e9d35064e"><label>*</label>Corresponding Author: Department of Medical Laboratory Sciences, School of Allied Medical Sciences, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. Email: <email>yerfani@sina.tums.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">493601</issue-id><elocation-id>e160772</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-29 13:25:35.133"><day>29</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025, Majidi Fard et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Majidi Fard et al</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This open-access article is available under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 (CC BY 4.0) International License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which allows for unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided that the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ijpr-24-1-160772.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is a hospital-acquired opportunistic pathogen, with biofilm formation playing a crucial role in its multidrug resistance. Given the rise in antibiotic resistance, herbal medicines, including peppermint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic>), have gained attention for their potential antibacterial properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>This study aimed to evaluate the inhibitory effects of peppermint extract on biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains isolated from clinical samples.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A total of 25 <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains were isolated from clinical samples at the Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Tehran. Their biofilm-forming ability and antibiotic susceptibility against nine antibiotics were assessed using the disk diffusion method. The antibacterial activity of peppermint extract was evaluated by well diffusion, with its minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) compared to ciprofloxacin. Synergistic effects between the extract and ciprofloxacin were analyzed, followed by a time-kill assay. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was used to detect the presence of <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> genes linked to biofilm formation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The study found that 88% of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains exhibited strong biofilm formation. Peppermint extract effectively inhibited biofilm formation, with MIC values ranging from 1.5 to 6 mg/mL (mean MIC: 3.75 ± 1.38 mg/mL) and MBC values equivalent to their respective MIC concentrations. For ciprofloxacin, the MIC for all samples was greater than 2048 mg/mL. No significant synergistic effect was observed between peppermint extract and ciprofloxacin. Both <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> (involved in biofilm matrix synthesis) and <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> (quorum sensing-related autoinducer synthase) genes were present in all tested strains.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Peppermint extract demonstrates biofilm-inhibitory properties against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, suggesting its potential as an alternative therapeutic approach for combating biofilm-associated infections.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>Biofilm</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic></kwd><kwd>Peppermint</kwd><kwd>PCR</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. Background</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is an aerobic, non-glucose-fermenting, gram-negative bacillus widely found in the environment (<xref rid="A160772REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). It causes various infections, primarily ventilator-associated pneumonia and bloodstream infections, with mortality rates reaching 35%. Its spread is often linked to multidrug resistance, including strains resistant to all available antibiotics (<xref rid="A160772REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Over recent decades, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> has developed resistance to many antimicrobials, including broad-spectrum cephalosporins, penicillins, fluoroquinolones, and aminoglycosides. A key virulence factor is biofilm formation, regulated by specific genes. Biofilms — three-dimensional bacterial communities encased in an extracellular matrix — significantly enhance resistance to antimicrobial agents (<xref rid="A160772REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="A160772REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Biofilm formation complicates treatment and facilitates transmission, contributing to hospital outbreaks. Surfaces like heart valves, prosthetic joints, ventilators, and catheters provide ideal conditions for biofilms. Clinical isolates show greater biofilm-forming ability on inert surfaces than non-clinical ones, promoting persistent hospital infections (<xref rid="A160772REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="A160772REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>Biofilms also protect <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> from the immune system and treatments, increasing antibiotic tolerance up to a thousand-fold. Within biofilms, bacteria more readily acquire resistance through horizontal gene transfer, enhancing survival (<xref rid="A160772REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Medicinal plants have been used for centuries due to their biological effects. World Health Organization (WHO) reports that 80% of people in developed countries use them for treatment (<xref rid="A160772REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Peppermint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic> L) is known for antimicrobial and anticancer properties. Studies confirm its antibacterial effects, effective against both gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria (<xref rid="A160772REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>Genes like <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> regulate <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilms. <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> encodes an enzyme for quorum sensing, influencing biofilm development, while <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic>, part of the <italic toggle="yes">PgaABCD</italic> locus, is involved in synthesizing PNAG, a key biofilm component. Though detection of these genes helps assess biofilm potential, it doesn't always reflect their expression or biofilm strength. Understanding these genes is vital for developing anti-biofilm therapies (<xref rid="A160772REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="A160772REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="intro"><title>2. Objectives</title><p>This study aimed to investigate the inhibitory effect of peppermint plant extract on biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>3. Methods</title><sec><title>3.1. Clinical Sample Collection Period</title><p>Clinical samples were collected over a 12-month period from April 2023 to March 2024 from patients admitted to various units of a hospital in Tehran. A total of 500 clinical specimens were obtained, including respiratory secretions, wound exudates, blood cultures, and urinary samples. The samples were collected as part of routine diagnostic procedures and were transferred to the microbiology laboratory within 2 hours of collection under appropriate transport conditions. All samples underwent standard microbiological processing for the isolation and identification of potential pathogens, with a specific focus on identifying <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates.</p></sec><sec><title>3.2. Collection and Preparation of the Plant and Extraction</title><p>Fresh and dried peppermint leaves were obtained from an herbal shop and authenticated by the Department of Plant Systematics, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran. For extraction, 50 g of dried, crushed leaves were soaked in 450 mL ethanol (total 500 mL) for two days. The mixture was filtered, and ethanol was evaporated naturally in an open tray to yield a dried powder. The extract was weighed and reconstituted in ethanol as needed for experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>3.3. Chemical Characterization of Peppermint Extract</title><p>Following extraction, the chemical characterization of peppermint extract was conducted to identify and quantify its main bioactive components. Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis was performed using an Agilent 7890B GC system with a 5977A mass selective detector. The extract, diluted in methanol (1:100), was injected (1 μL) into an HP-5MS capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm, 0.25 μm film).</p><p>The oven temperature was set to 60°C (2 min), increased to 240°C at 5°C/min, and held for 10 min. Helium served as the carrier gas (1 mL/min). The MS was operated in electron impact mode (70 eV) with an ion source temperature of 230°C. Compounds were identified by comparing mass spectra with the NIST library (v2.0) and matching retention indices to literature data.</p><p>High-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) was also used to quantify major phenolic compounds. Analyses were carried out with a Shimadzu LC-20AD system and SPD-M20A diode array detector on a C18 column (250 mm × 4.6 mm, 5 μm) at 30°C. The mobile phase included 0.1% formic acid in water (A) and acetonitrile (B), with gradient elution. Flow rate was 1 mL/min, and detection was done at 280 nm. Quantification used standard curves for menthol, menthone, and rosmarinic acid (<xref rid="A160772REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>3.4. Disk Diffusion Agar Test Method</title><p>The test followed Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines. Mueller-Hinton agar plate (Merck, Germany) was prepared with a pH of 7.2 - 7.4. A standardized microbial suspension was spread evenly on the agar using a sterile cotton swab (lawn culture method). After 15 minutes at room temperature, nine antibiotic discs, also at room temperature, were placed on the agar with at least 2.5 cm spacing between discs and plate edges. Plates were incubated at 37°C for 18 - 24 hours. Inhibition zone diameters around each disc were then measured and recorded.</p></sec><sec><title>3.5. Determination of the Effectiveness of Peppermint Extract by Well Diffusion Method</title><p>A suspension of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> equivalent to a 0.5 McFarland standard was prepared in physiological saline and inoculated onto Mueller-Hinton agar plates. Four wells were made in the agar using a sterile punch. Peppermint extract at concentrations of 3.1, 6.25, 12.5, and 25 mg/mL was added to the wells. Plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 hours, after which inhibition zone diameters were measured and recorded.</p></sec><sec><title>3.6. Determination of Minimum Inhibitory Concentration of Peppermint Extract and Ciprofloxacin Antibiotic</title><p>The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was determined using the serial microdilution broth method in a 96-well microplate. Each well received 100 µL of Mueller-Hinton broth, followed by serial dilutions of test compounds: Peppermint extract (starting at 12 mg/mL) and ciprofloxacin (starting at 2048 mg/mL). Then, 100 µL of a standardized bacterial suspension (10⁶ CFU/mL) was added to each well. Positive controls (broth + solvent) and negative controls (broth + solvent + bacteria) were included. Plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 hours, and bacterial growth was then assessed.</p></sec><sec><title>3.7. Ranking Method for Antibiotic Resistance Analysis</title><p>Antibiotic susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates was assessed following CLSI guidelines (M100-S30, 2024). Inhibition zone diameters were measured and classified as resistant (R), intermediate (I), or susceptible (S) based on CLSI breakpoints for <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> species (<xref rid="A160772REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>Antibiotics were ranked by the percentage of resistant isolates, with higher resistance ranked first. When resistance percentages were equal, clinical importance and frequency of use (per institutional protocols and MDR guidelines) were considered.</p><p>Antibiotics were also grouped into classes (e.g., carbapenems, fluoroquinolones, aminoglycosides, polymyxins) to assess class-specific resistance patterns. The Multiple Antibiotic Resistance (MAR) Index was calculated for each isolate using the formula: MAR = Number of antibiotics resisted/Total antibiotics tested.</p><p>Isolates with MAR ≥ 0.2 were considered from high-risk sources with frequent antibiotic exposure.</p><p>This systematic ranking allowed for a comprehensive evaluation of resistance profiles and identification of effective treatment options, while also highlighting concerning resistance trends.</p></sec><sec><title>3.8. Determination of Minimum Bactericidal Concentration of Peppermint Extract and Ciprofloxacin Antibiotic</title><p>Ten microliters from the wells where bacterial growth was inhibited (the wells after the MIC wells) were transferred onto Mueller-Hinton agar plates and incubated at 37°C for 24 hours. After the incubation period, the plates were examined for bacterial growth. The last concentration in which no colony growth occurred was identified as the MBC.</p></sec><sec><title>3.9. Evaluation of Acinetobacter baumannii Biofilm Formation Inhibition</title><p>A TSB medium with 2% glucose was prepared, and <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> suspensions were adjusted to 0.5 McFarland turbidity. A volume of 200 µL of the suspension was added to each well of a 96-well plate, incubated at 37°C for 24 h. Three wells containing only media (no bacteria) served as negative controls to determine the optical density cut-off (ODc) for biofilm classification.</p><p>After incubation, the medium was discarded and wells were washed twice with 200 µL PBS. Wells were fixed with 200 µL of absolute methanol for 10 minutes, stained with 200 µL of 1% crystal violet for 5 minutes, and then rinsed with distilled water. Finally, 200 µL of 33% glacial acetic acid was added to each well to solubilize the stain.</p><p>Absorbance was measured at 640 nm using an ELISA reader. While 590 - 595 nm is standard, 640 nm was used due to equipment constraints; previous studies confirm its validity for ODc-based classification. Biofilm production levels were categorized as shown in <xref rid="A160772TBL1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> (<xref rid="A160772REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="A160772REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="A160772TBL1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Biofilm Production and Average Optical Density Classification <sup><xref rid="A160772TBL1FN1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biofilm Production</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average OD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Negative</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OD ≤ ODc</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Weak</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODc ≤ OD ≤ 2 × ODc</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Moderate</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 × ODc ≤ OD ≤ 4 × ODc</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Strong</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 × ODc &lt; OD</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="A160772TBL1FN1"><p><sup>a</sup> ODc: Optical density cut-off value calculated as the mean OD of negative control wells (no bacterial growth) plus three standard deviations. This value is used as a baseline to categorize biofilm formation intensity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the initial method, biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was assessed without the addition of any extract. To evaluate the potential effect of peppermint extract on biofilm formation, 200 µL of the extract at its MIC was added to the bacterial suspension in TSB medium supplemented with 2% glucose, after adjustment to 0.5 McFarland turbidity. The biofilm quantification procedure was then repeated as previously described.</p><p>In a separate experiment, 200 µL of the extract at 2MIC was added under the same conditions, and the steps were repeated accordingly. Finally, the biofilm classification results from the three experimental conditions (control, MIC, and 2MIC) were compared to assess the impact of the peppermint extract on biofilm formation.</p></sec><sec><title>3.10. Time Kill Method</title><p>One of the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains was selected, and a 0.5 McFarland suspension was prepared. The suspension was then divided into two groups: The control group, which received no treatment, and the treatment group, to which the MIC concentration of peppermint extract was added. Sampling was performed at 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, and 24 hours, and colony counts were conducted for each time point.</p></sec><sec><title>3.11. Evaluation of the Combined and Synergistic Effect of Peppermint Extract and Ciprofloxacin Antibiotic by the Checkerboard Method</title><p>The concentration range of the drugs used in the checkerboard method was the same as that used in the broth microdilution method. Fifty µL of each concentration was transferred into the wells of a sterile 96-well microtiter plate. The ciprofloxacin antibiotic concentration was equal to the MIC concentration of the peppermint extract. The ciprofloxacin concentrations ranged from 2048 to 16 mg/mL, while the peppermint extract concentrations ranged from 3 to 0.0234375 mg/mL.</p><p>First, 50 µL of ciprofloxacin antibiotic was added horizontally into the wells of the microtiter plate. Then, 50 µL of peppermint extract was added vertically into the wells. Following this, 100 µL of a bacterial suspension (equivalent to 10<sup>6</sup> CFU) was added to all the wells. The microtiter plates were incubated at 37°C for 18 to 24 hours. After this incubation period, the MIC values were read again.</p></sec><sec><title>3.12. Detection of Biofilm-Associated Genes</title><p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was conducted to detect the <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> genes in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates (<xref rid="A160772REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Each 25 μL reaction contained 12.5 μL of 2X PCR master mix (Ampliqon, Denmark), 1 μL (10 pmol) of each primer (<xref rid="A160772TBL2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), 2 μL of template DNA (~50 ng), and 8.5 μL of nuclease-free water. Amplification was carried out on a Bio-Rad T100™ thermal cycler under the following conditions: Initial denaturation at 95°C for 5 min; 35 cycles of 95°C for 30 s, 58°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 45 s; with a final extension at 72°C for 7 min.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="A160772TBL2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Primer Size and Sequence Information Used in the Study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Product Size</th><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer Forward</th><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer Reverse</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>AbaI</bold>
</italic>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCGCCTTCCTCTAGCAGTCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAAACCCGCAGCACGTAATAA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>PgaA</bold>
</italic>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCCGACGGTCGCGATAC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATGCACATCACCAAAACGGTACT</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Polymerase chain reaction products were resolved on a 1.5% agarose gel stained with 0.5 mg/mL ethidium bromide, run in 1× TAE buffer at 80 V for 60 min. A 100 bp DNA ladder (Smobio, Taiwan) was used as a size marker. The presence of 150 bp bands indicated successful amplification of the target genes. This qualitative analysis was performed to confirm the biofilm-related genetic potential of the isolates before testing the anti-biofilm effects of peppermint extract.</p></sec><sec><title>3.13. Polymerase Chain Reaction Reference Control</title><p>For PCR validation and quality control purposes, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 19606 was employed as the reference strain and positive control. This well-characterized strain is known to possess both the <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> genes and exhibits strong biofilm-forming capabilities, making it an appropriate benchmark for our molecular analyses. The genomic DNA extracted from ATCC 19606 consistently produced clear amplification bands at the expected 150 base pair region for both target genes, confirming the specificity and efficiency of our primer design and PCR conditions (<xref rid="A160772REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>3.14. Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed with SPSS version 25.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). Experiments were done in triplicate, and results are shown as mean ± SD. One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s post-hoc test was used to analyze the inhibitory effects of peppermint extract on biofilm formation and differences in inhibition zone diameters across concentrations. For the time-kill assay, bacterial counts (CFU/mL) were log-transformed and analyzed by repeated measures ANOVA with Bonferroni correction. The distribution of biofilm strength categories was assessed by chi-square test. A P-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>4. Results</title><sec><title>4.1. Antibiotic Sensitivity Pattern of the Samples</title><p>According to the results obtained, colistin was the only antibiotic that showed sensitivity (92% sensitive). Ampicillin, with 12% sensitivity, ranked second, while all other antibiotics tested were 100% resistant (<xref rid="A160772TBL3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). </p><table-wrap position="float" id="A160772TBL3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Antibiotic Resistance, Sensitivity, and Intermediate Sensitivity results</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistant</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Susceptible</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Meropenem</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ciprofloxacin</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Colistin</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazol</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Peperacillin</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ampicillin-sulbactam</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ceftazidime</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gentamycin</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Tetracycline</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>4.2. Chemical Characterization of Peppermint Extract</title><p>The chemical profile of the peppermint extract was analyzed using GC-MS and HPLC. Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry analysis revealed the presence of several key volatile compounds. The most abundant constituents identified were:</p><p>- Menthol (31.6%)</p><p>- Menthone (22.4%)</p><p>- 1,8-Cineole (Eucalyptol) (12.8%)</p><p>- Menthyl acetate (9.3%)</p><p>- Limonene (6.7%)</p><p>- β-Caryophyllene (5.1%)</p><p>High-performance liquid chromatography quantification confirmed the presence of:</p><p>- Menthol: 19.2 mg/g dry weight</p><p>- Menthone: 13.7 mg/g dry weight</p><p>- Rosmarinic acid: 8.4 mg/g dry weight</p><p>These compounds are known for their antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, and antioxidant properties and are likely contributors to the observed antibacterial and anti-biofilm effects of the extract.</p></sec><sec><title>4.3. Antibacterial Activity of Peppermint Extract on Acinetobacter baumannii Using the Agar Well Diffusion Method</title><p>The results indicated that peppermint extract inhibits the growth of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. At a concentration of 25 mg/mL, 80% of the strains were inhibited; at a concentration of 12.5 mg/mL, 92% of the strains were inhibited; at a concentration of 6.25 mg/mL, 92% of the strains were inhibited; and at a concentration of 3.1 mg/mL, 96% of the strains showed resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>4.4. Evaluation of Minimum Inhibitory Concentration and Minimum Bactericidal Concentration of Peppermint Extract and Ciprofloxacin Against Acinetobacter baumannii</title><p>In the study of 25 <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains, the MIC of peppermint extract was found to be 1.5 mg/mL for 4% (1/25) of the strains, 3 mg/mL for 68% (17/25) of the strains, and 6 mg/mL for 28% (7/25) of the strains, with a mean MIC value of 3.75 ± 1.38 mg/mL. For ciprofloxacin, the MIC for all samples (25/25, 100%) was greater than 2048 mg/mL. The minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) values were equivalent to the respective MIC values for both peppermint extract and ciprofloxacin in all tested strains, indicating bactericidal activity at the same concentrations that inhibited growth.</p></sec><sec><title>4.5. Investigation of Biofilm Formation Inhibition of Acinetobacter baumannii by Peppermint Extract</title><p>To assess inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilm formation, three conditions were tested. In the control group, 88% (22/25) of isolates formed strong biofilms (mean OD640 = 0.89 ± 0.21), 8% (2/25) moderate (0.56 ± 0.08), and 4% (1/25) weak (0.31 ± 0.04). At the MIC concentration of peppermint extract, 84% (21/25) remained strong biofilm producers (0.79 ± 0.18), 12% (3/25) moderate (0.52 ± 0.07), and 4% (1/25) weak (0.29 ± 0.03), with no significant reduction versus control (P = 0.087).</p><p>At 2MIC, only 20% (5/25) formed strong biofilms (0.62 ± 0.14), 16% (4/25) moderate (0.48 ± 0.06), and 64% (16/25) weak (0.24 ± 0.07), showing a highly significant reduction compared to control and MIC groups (P &lt; 0.001).</p><p><xref rid="A160772FIG1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> illustrates that 2MIC significantly reduced strong biofilm formation from 88% to 20% and increased weak biofilm formation from 4% to 64% (P &lt; 0.001), indicating a potent anti- biofilm effect.</p><fig position="float" id="A160772FIG1" fig-type="inline" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Biofilm formation strength of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates under different treatment conditions. The bar graph compares the distribution of biofilm production categories (strong, moderate, weak) among control, minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), and 2MIC treatment groups. Error bars represent standard deviations of OD640 (optical density at 640 nm) values within each group. Statistical significance was assessed using chi-square and one-way ANOVA. *** P &lt; 0.001 compared to control and MIC groups.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ijpr-24-1-160772-i001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>4.6. Results of Time-Killing Assay</title><sec><title>4.6.1. Diameter of Inhibition Zones in Agar Well Diffusion Assay</title><p>Time-kill kinetics of peppermint extract against a representative <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strain were assessed over 24 hours. At 0 hours, bacterial counts were 0.22 × 10⁵ CFU/mL in the control and 0.3 × 10⁴ CFU/mL in the treatment group. The control group exhibited exponential growth, reaching 0.14 × 10²¹ CFU/mL at 24 hours, while the treatment group showed a significant, time-dependent decline, with complete eradication (no detectable colonies) by 24 hours.</p><p>As shown in <xref rid="A160772TBL4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, fold-reduction (control CFU/treatment CFU) increased from 7.3-fold at baseline to total elimination at 24 hours, demonstrating strong bactericidal activity. Repeated measures ANOVA revealed significant differences between groups at all time points (P &lt; 0.001), confirming the extract’s potent and time-dependent antibacterial effect.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="A160772TBL4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Results of the Time-Killing Assay with Fold Reduction</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hour</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group (CFU/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Strain (CFU/mL)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Reduction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 × 10<sup>5</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 × 10<sup>4</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 × 10<sup>5</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 × 10<sup>4</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 × 10<sup>5</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 × 10<sup>4</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 × 10<sup>6</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121 × 10<sup>2</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 × 10<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 × 10<sup>7</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 × 10<sup>1</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 × 10<sup>6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>24</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 × 10<sup>21</sup></td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete killing</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The inhibition zone diameters demonstrated a clear dose-dependent response, with the highest concentration (25 mg/mL) yielding the largest zones (15.6 - 20.3 mm). Two isolates (AB-19 and AB-24) were completely resistant, showing no inhibition at any concentration. Mean inhibition zone diameters were 17.7 ± 1.5 mm at 25 mg/mL, 14.8 ± 1.3 mm at 12.5 mg/mL, 11.2 ± 1.1 mm at 6.25 mg/mL, and 7.1 ± 1.0 mm at 3.1 mg/mL. Detailed results for each isolate are provided in <xref rid="A160772TBL5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. </p><table-wrap position="float" id="A160772TBL5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Inhibition Zone Diameters (mm) for Peppermint Extract Against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Clinical Isolates <sup><xref rid="A160772TBL5FN1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Isolate ID</th><th colspan="4" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1">Peppermint Extract Concentration</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 mg/mL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 mg/mL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25 mg/mL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 mg/mL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-01</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-02</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-03</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-04</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8 ± 0.7</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-05</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 ± 0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-06</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-07</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 ± 0.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-08</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8 ± 0.7</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7 ± 0.7</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-09</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-10</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-11</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-12</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-13</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1 ± 0.7</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 ± 0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-14</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-15</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-16</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-17</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 ± 0.7</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 ± 0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-18</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-19</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-20</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-21</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-22</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0 ± 0.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-23</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 ± 0.7</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-24</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-25</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4 ± 0.6</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2 ± 0.4</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 ± 0.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 ± 0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean ± SD</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7 ± 1.5</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8 ± 1.3</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 ± 1.1</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 ± 1.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="A160772TBL5FN1"><p><sup>a</sup> Values represent mean ± standard deviation of three independent experiments. Zero (0) indicates no inhibition zone observed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>One-way ANOVA confirmed significant differences across all concentrations (P &lt; 0.001), validating the concentration-dependent antibacterial effect of peppermint extract against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>4.7. Results of Synergistic and Combined Effect of Peppermint Extract and Ciprofloxacin Antibiotic by Checkerboard Method</title><p>The interaction between peppermint extract and ciprofloxacin was assessed using the Fractional Inhibitory Concentration Index (FICI). Only 4% (1/25) of combinations showed synergy (FICI ≤ 0.5), 16% (4/25) were additive (0.5 &lt; FICI ≤ 1.0), 4% (1/25) had an unequal response, and 76% (19/25) showed no interaction (FICI &gt; 1.0). The mean FICI was 1.38 ± 0.47, indicating mainly indifferent interactions. These results suggest that combining peppermint extract with ciprofloxacin does not significantly improve antibacterial efficacy compared to using each alone (P = 0.72).</p></sec><sec><title>4.8. Results of AbaI and PgaA Gene Analysis</title><p>Following DNA extraction, PCR was employed to detect the presence of the <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> genes. The resulting PCR products were then analyzed using gel electrophoresis with a Gel Documentation system. A clear band at approximately 150 base pairs confirmed the presence of the <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> gene in every sample. In fact, all 25 <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates tested positive for <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic>. Similarly, the <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> gene was detected as a 150 bp band in all samples (<xref rid="A160772FIG2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), indicating its universal presence among the isolates. These findings demonstrate the consistent occurrence of both the <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> genes in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii,</italic> which could have important implications for understanding the organism’s pathogenic mechanisms.</p><fig position="float" id="A160772FIG2" fig-type="graph" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) gel electrophoresis results for the detection of <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> genes in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> samples. The clear presence of a band at the 150 base pair region indicates the existence of these genes in all 25 samples examined.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ijpr-24-1-160772-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>5. Discussion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is the second most common non-fermentative bacterial pathogen and a major cause of hospital-acquired infections, especially in ICUs, with mortality rates from 7.8% to 43% (<xref rid="A160772REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Its ability to form biofilms — structured bacterial communities within an extracellular matrix — greatly increases resistance to antimicrobials. Biofilms are involved in at least two-thirds of bacterial infections, complicating clinical treatment due to their antibiotic resilience.</p><p>Rising antibiotic resistance highlights the need for alternative therapies. Plant-based antimicrobials are promising because many medicinal plants contain compounds that inhibit biofilm formation, boost antibiotic effectiveness, or have direct antibacterial activity. Such natural compounds may offer sustainable, effective options against biofilm-related infections.</p><p>Peppermint, from the Lamiaceae family, has anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, antiviral, and immunomodulatory properties. With increasing <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> resistance to antibiotics, peppermint extract is a potential alternative, as its bioactive compounds might reduce resistance and inhibit biofilms (<xref rid="A160772REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="A160772REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Further studies are needed to identify the active compounds and their mechanisms.</p><sec><title>5.1. Antibiotic Susceptibility Testing</title><p>In this study, antibiotic susceptibility testing was performed to assess resistance patterns among <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. The results indicated that colistin was the only antibiotic to which all tested strains were sensitive, a finding that aligns with previous studies. For instance, Ghajavand et al. reported 92% sensitivity to colistin (<xref rid="A160772REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), while Smolyakov et al. observed 100% sensitivity to both colistin and ampicillin-sulbactam (<xref rid="A160772REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). However, our study revealed a 56% resistance rate to ampicillin-sulbactam, indicating an alarming increase in antibiotic resistance over time. These findings emphasize the need for continuous monitoring of resistance trends and the exploration of alternative treatments.</p></sec><sec><title>5.2. Antimicrobial Activity of Peppermint Extract</title><p>The agar well diffusion method demonstrated that peppermint extract effectively inhibited <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> growth, reinforcing its potential as a natural antimicrobial agent. These findings align with previous research, such as Pramila et al., who reported significant antimicrobial activity of peppermint due to its bioactive compounds (<xref rid="A160772REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Similarly, Jeyakumar et al. found that peppermint extract exhibited concentration-dependent antibacterial effects, demonstrating its efficacy against multidrug-resistant bacterial strains (<xref rid="A160772REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>5.3. Minimum Inhibitory Concentration and Minimum Bactericidal Concentration Analysis</title><p>The MIC and MBC of peppermint extract and ciprofloxacin were assessed to determine their bacteriostatic and bactericidal effects. Peppermint extract showed MIC values between 1.5 and 6 mg/mL, while ciprofloxacin had a MIC of 2048 mg/mL, indicating high antibiotic resistance. The MBC values matched the MICs, demonstrating peppermint extract’s strong bactericidal activity against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Similar findings were reported by Hatami Pirghibi et al., who observed peppermint extract inhibiting Pseudomonas aeruginosa at similar concentrations (<xref rid="A160772REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Additionally, peppermint extract’s potent antimicrobial effects against gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria are attributed to bioactive compounds like menthol and flavonoids, supporting its potential as a natural alternative against resistant strains (<xref rid="A160772REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="A160772REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>5.4. Biofilm Inhibition Assay</title><p>Biofilm formation is a major contributor to antibiotic resistance in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, making its inhibition a key target for alternative treatments. Our study found that in the control group, 88% of strains formed strong biofilms, whereas treatment with peppermint extract at 2MIC concentration reduced strong biofilm formation to 20%, with 64% of strains exhibiting weak biofilm formation. This suggests that peppermint extract has a strong inhibitory effect on biofilm formation, which is crucial for limiting <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> persistence in clinical settings. These findings align with previous research by Ranjbar and Farahani, who found that 70.6% of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains formed strong biofilms (<xref rid="A160772REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Additionally, Sandas et al. demonstrated that plant-based extracts, including peppermint, effectively inhibited biofilm formation, supporting our observations (<xref rid="A160772REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>5.5. Synergistic Effect of Peppermint Extract and Ciprofloxacin</title><p>The combination of peppermint extract with ciprofloxacin was assessed for possible synergistic effects, but no significant interaction was observed. This result differs from previous findings, such as Rosato et al.’s study, where plant extracts demonstrated synergistic activity with antibiotics like gentamicin (<xref rid="A160772REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The absence of synergy in our study suggests that while peppermint extract is effective on its own, its combination with ciprofloxacin may not enhance antibacterial efficacy against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Future research should investigate other antibiotic combinations to determine potential synergistic effects with peppermint extract.</p></sec><sec><title>5.6. Genetic Basis for Biofilm Formation</title><p>Our study found that all tested <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates possessed both <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PgaA</italic> genes, confirming their genetic capacity for biofilm formation. This aligns with the 88% of isolates showing strong biofilm formation phenotypically. Similar results were reported by Xiang et al., who linked <italic toggle="yes">AbaI</italic> expression to biofilm formation in drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (<xref rid="A160772REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), and Choi et al., who showed the <italic toggle="yes">PgaABCD</italic> locus is vital for producing poly-β-1-6-N-acetylglucosamine, a key biofilm matrix component (<xref rid="A160772REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Although we detected these genes, future studies should use quantitative RT-PCR to assess if peppermint extract modulates their expression, which could clarify the molecular basis of its anti-biofilm effects and how natural compounds disrupt biofilm formation genetically.</p></sec><sec><title>5.7. Conclusions</title><p>This study provides strong evidence that peppermint extract exhibits inhibitory effects on <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> growth and biofilm formation, making it a potential alternative therapy for biofilm-related infections. Given the increasing resistance of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> to conventional antibiotics, exploring plant-based antimicrobials represents a valuable strategy for future clinical applications. Further studies should focus on identifying the bioactive compounds responsible for these effects, understanding their mechanisms of action, and assessing their potential synergistic interactions with existing antibiotics.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="A160772REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="1.Villers D, Espaze E, Coste-Burel M, Giauffret F, Ninin E, Nicolas F, et al. Nosocomial Acinetobacter baumannii infections: microbiological and clinical epidemiology. Ann Intern Med. 1998;129(3):182-9. [PubMed ID:9696725]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espaze</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coste-Burel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giauffret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ninin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial Acinetobacter baumannii infections: microbiological and clinical epidemiology.</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med.</source><year>1998</year><volume>129</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-129-3-199808010-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9696725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Mendes SG, Combo SI, Allain T, Domingues S, Buret AG, Da Silva GJ. Co-regulation of biofilm formation and antimicrobial resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii: from mechanisms to therapeutic strategies. Europ J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2023;42(12):1405-23. [PubMed ID:37897520]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Combo</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allain</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domingues</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buret</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-regulation of biofilm formation and antimicrobial resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii: from mechanisms to therapeutic strategies.</article-title><source>Europ J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis.</source><year>2023</year><volume>42</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-023-04677-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37897520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10651561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Qi L, Li H, Zhang C, Liang B, Li J, Wang L, et al. Relationship between Antibiotic Resistance, Biofilm Formation, and Biofilm-Specific Resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii. Front Microbiol. 2016;7 [PubMed ID:27148178]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Relationship between Antibiotic Resistance, Biofilm Formation, and Biofilm-Specific Resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii.</article-title><source>Front Microbiol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7 </volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4828443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Mohamed EA, Raafat MM, Samir Mohamed R, Ali AEE. Acinetobacter baumannii biofilm and its potential therapeutic targets. Future J Pharm Sci. 2023;9(1):82. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raafat</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samir Mohamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>AEE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acinetobacter baumannii biofilm and its potential therapeutic targets.</article-title><source>Future J Pharm Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43094-023-00525-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Trebosc V, Gartenmann S, Totzl M, Lucchini V, Schellhorn B, Pieren M, et al. Dissecting Colistin Resistance Mechanisms in Extensively Drug-Resistant Acinetobacter baumannii Clinical Isolates. mBio. 2019;10(4). [PubMed ID:31311879]. [PubMed Central ID:PMC6635527]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trebosc</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gartenmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Totzl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucchini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schellhorn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Dissecting Colistin Resistance Mechanisms in Extensively Drug-Resistant Acinetobacter baumannii Clinical Isolates.</article-title><source>mBio.</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01083-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31311879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6635527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Fabricant DS, Farnsworth NR. The value of plants used in traditional medicine for drug discovery. Environ Health Perspect. 2001;109 Suppl 1(Suppl 1):69-75. [PubMed ID:11250806]. [PubMed Central ID:PMC1240543]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabricant</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farnsworth</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The value of plants used in traditional medicine for drug discovery.</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect.</source><year>2001</year><volume>109 Suppl 1</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.01109s169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11250806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1240543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Lai PK, Roy J. Antimicrobial and chemopreventive properties of herbs and spices. Curr Med Chem. 2004;11(11):1451-60. [PubMed ID:15180577]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and chemopreventive properties of herbs and spices.</article-title><source>Curr Med Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0929867043365107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15180577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Xinlong H, Feng L, Fenglai Y, Donglin J, Peng Z, Jie Z, et al. Biofilm Formation Caused by Clinical Acinetobacter baumannii Isolates Is Associated with Overexpression of the AdeFGH Efflux Pump. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2015;59(8):4817-25. [PubMed ID:26033730 ]. [PubMed Central ID:PMC4505227]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xinlong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenglai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donglin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Biofilm Formation Caused by Clinical Acinetobacter baumannii Isolates Is Associated with Overexpression of the AdeFGH Efflux Pump.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source><year>2015</year><volume>59</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>4817</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aac.00877-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26033730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4505227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Taherpour AA, Khaef S, Yari A, Nikeafshar S, Fathi M, Ghambari S. Chemical composition analysis of the essential oil of Mentha piperita L. from Kermanshah, Iran by hydrodistillation and HS/SPME methods. J Analytical Sci Technol. 2017;8(1):11. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taherpour</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaef</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikeafshar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghambari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition analysis of the essential oil of Mentha piperita L. from Kermanshah, Iran by hydrodistillation and HS/SPME methods.</article-title><source>J Analytical Sci Technol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40543-017-0122-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="book" xlink:title="Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute. Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing, 35th ed. Wayne, Pennsylvania: Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute; 2025. [Cited:2025]. Available from."><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab></person-group><source>Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing, 35th ed.</source><year>2025</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2025</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Wayne, Pennsylvania</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Natsheh IY, Elkhader MT, Al-Bakheit AaA, Alsaleh MM, El-Eswed BI, Hosein NF, et al. Inhibition of Acinetobacter baumannii Biofilm Formation Using Different Treatments of Silica Nanoparticles. Antibiotics. 2023;12(9):1365. [PubMed ID:37760662 ]. [PubMed Central ID:PMC10525453]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Natsheh</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhader</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Bakheit</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaleh</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Eswed</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosein</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of Acinetobacter baumannii Biofilm Formation Using Different Treatments of Silica Nanoparticles.</article-title><source>Antibiotics.</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1365</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12091365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37760662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10525453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Stepanović S, Vuković D, Hola V, Bonaventura GD, Djukić S, Ćirković I, et al. Quantification of biofilm in microtiter plates: overview of testing conditions and practical recommendations for assessment of biofilm production by staphylococci. APMIS. 2007;115(8):891-9. [PubMed ID:17696944]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanović</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuković</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hola</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonaventura</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Djukić</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ćirković</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Quantification of biofilm in microtiter plates: overview of testing conditions and practical recommendations for assessment of biofilm production by staphylococci.</article-title><source>APMIS.</source><year>2007</year><volume>115</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0463.2007.apm_630.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17696944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Xiong L, Yi F, Yu Q, Huang X, Ao K, Wang Y, et al. Transcriptomic analysis reveals the regulatory role of quorum sensing in the Acinetobacter baumannii ATCC 19606 via RNA-seq. BMC Microbiol. 2022;22(1):198. [PubMed ID:35971084 ]. [PubMed Central ID:PMC9380347]. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis reveals the regulatory role of quorum sensing in the Acinetobacter baumannii ATCC 19606 via RNA-seq.</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>198</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-022-02612-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35971084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9380347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Rosato A, Carocci A, Catalano A, Clodoveo ML, Franchini C, Corbo F, et al. Elucidation of the synergistic action of Mentha Piperita essential oil with common antimicrobials. PloS one. 2018;13(8):e0200902. [PubMed ID:30067803 ]. [PubMed Central ID:PMC6070247]."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carocci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clodoveo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franchini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Elucidation of the synergistic action of Mentha Piperita essential oil with common antimicrobials.</article-title><source>PloS one.</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e0200902</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30067803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0200902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6070247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Karicheri R, Antony B. Antibacterial and antibiofilm activities of peppermint (Mentha piperita Linn) and menthol mint (Mentha arvensis Linn) essential oils on Aggregatibacter Actinomycetemcomitans isolated from orodental infections. Eur J Pharm Med Res. 2016;3:577-81."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karicheri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antony</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antibiofilm activities of peppermint (Mentha piperita Linn) and menthol mint (Mentha arvensis Linn) essential oils on Aggregatibacter Actinomycetemcomitans isolated from orodental infections.</article-title><source>Eur J Pharm Med Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Ghajavand H, Havaei A, Nasr-Esfahani B, Fazeli H, Moghim S. Frequency of Multi-Drug Resistance Acinetobacter Baumannii Isolates in Intensive Care Units (ICU) of Isfahan Hospitals, Iran, via Molecular Method and Their Antimicrobial Resistance Patterns. J Isfahan Med Sch. 2014;32(295):1175-85."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghajavand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Havaei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasr-Esfahani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazeli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moghim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequency of Multi-Drug Resistance Acinetobacter Baumannii Isolates in Intensive Care Units (ICU) of Isfahan Hospitals, Iran, via Molecular Method and Their Antimicrobial Resistance Patterns.</article-title><source>J Isfahan Med Sch.</source><year>2014</year><volume>32</volume><issue>295</issue><fpage>1175</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Smolyakov R, Borer A, Riesenberg K, Schlaeffer F, Alkan M, Porath A, et al. Nosocomial multi-drug resistant Acinetobacter baumannii bloodstream infection: risk factors and outcome with ampicillin-sulbactam treatment. J Hosp Infect. 2003;54(1):32-8. [PubMed ID:12767844]."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolyakov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riesenberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlaeffer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial multi-drug resistant Acinetobacter baumannii bloodstream infection: risk factors and outcome with ampicillin-sulbactam treatment.</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect.</source><year>2003</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12767844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0195-6701(03)00046-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Pramila DM, Xavier R, Marimuthu K, Kathiresan S, Khoo ML, Senthilkumar M, et al. Phytochemical analysis and antimicrobial potential of methanolic leaf extract of peppermint (Mentha piperita: Lamiaceae). J Med Plants Res. 2012;6(2):331-5."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pramila</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marimuthu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kathiresan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical analysis and antimicrobial potential of methanolic leaf extract of peppermint (Mentha piperita: Lamiaceae).</article-title><source>J Med Plants Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Jeyakumar E, Lawrence R, Pal T. Comparative evaluation in the efficacy of peppermint (Mentha piperita) oil with standards antibiotics against selected bacterial pathogens. Asian Pacific J Tropical Biomed. 2011;1(2, Supplement):S253-S7. ."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeyakumar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative evaluation in the efficacy of peppermint (Mentha piperita) oil with standards antibiotics against selected bacterial pathogens.</article-title><source>Asian Pacific J Tropical Biomed.</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2, Supplement</issue><fpage>S253</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2221-1691(11)60165-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Hatami Pirghibi T, Chehri K, Abiri R, Karimi I. Effect of hydro-alcoholic extracts of Rosmarinus officinalis L., Mentha piperita L., and Zataria multiflora Boiss on biofilm formation of Pseudomonas. Res Med. 2021;45(3):11-7."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatami Pirghibi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chehri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abiri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of hydro-alcoholic extracts of Rosmarinus officinalis L., Mentha piperita L., and Zataria multiflora Boiss on biofilm formation of Pseudomonas.</article-title><source>Res Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>45</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Singh R, Shushni MAM, Belkheir A. Antibacterial and antioxidant activities of Mentha piperita L. Arabian J Chem. 2015;8(3):322-8."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shushni</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belkheir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antioxidant activities of Mentha piperita L.</article-title><source>Arabian J Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Ranjbar R, Farahani A. Study of genetic diversity, biofilm formation, and detection of Carbapenemase, MBL, ESBL, and tetracycline resistance genes in multidrug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii isolated from burn wound infections in Iran. Antimicrob Resistance Infect Control. 2019;8:1-11. [PubMed ID:31719975 ]. [PubMed Central ID:PMC6836547]."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranjbar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farahani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of genetic diversity, biofilm formation, and detection of Carbapenemase, MBL, ESBL, and tetracycline resistance genes in multidrug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii isolated from burn wound infections in Iran.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Resistance Infect Control.</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31719975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13756-019-0612-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6836547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Sandasi M, Leonard CM, Viljoen AM. The in vitro antibiofilm activity of selected culinary herbs and medicinal plants against Listeria monocytogenes. Letters Appl Microbiol. 2010;50(1):30-5. [PubMed ID:19874481]."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandasi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viljoen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The in vitro antibiofilm activity of selected culinary herbs and medicinal plants against Listeria monocytogenes.</article-title><source>Letters Appl Microbiol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19874481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2009.02747.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Rosato A, Vitali C, De Laurentis N, Armenise D, Milillo MA. Antibacterial effect of some essential oils administered alone or in combination with Norfloxacin. Phytomedicine. 2007;14(11):727-32. [PubMed ID:17303397]."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitali</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Laurentis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armenise</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milillo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial effect of some essential oils administered alone or in combination with Norfloxacin.</article-title><source>Phytomedicine.</source><year>2007</year><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17303397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phymed.2007.01.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Xiang J, Sun Z, Yang XG, Huan JN. Changes in expression of gene aba I in biofilm of Acinetobacter baumannii strains isolated from burn patients. Chinese J Burns. 2012;28(2):101-5."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huan</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in expression of gene aba I in biofilm of Acinetobacter baumannii strains isolated from burn patients.</article-title><source>Chinese J Burns.</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22781320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A160772REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" publication-type="journal" publication-format="print" xlink:title="Choi AH, Slamti L, Avci FY, Pier GB, Maira-Litrán T. The pgaABCD locus of Acinetobacter baumannii encodes the production of poly-β-1-6-N-acetylglucosamine, which is critical for biofilm formation. J Bacteriol. 2009;191(19):5953-63. [PubMed ID:19633088 ]."><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slamti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pier</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maira-Litrán</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pgaABCD locus of Acinetobacter baumannii encodes the production of poly-β-1-6-N-acetylglucosamine, which is critical for biofilm formation.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>191</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>5953</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.00647-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2747904</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec><title>Authors' Contribution: </title><p>Study concept and design: Z. M. F. and Y. E.; Analysis an interpretation of data: Z. M. F., Y. E., and S. E.; Drafting of the manuscript: Sh. A. and N. I. M.; Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content: Z. M. F., Y. E., Sh. A., N. I. M., and S. E.; Statistical analysis: Z. M. F. and S. E.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of Interests Statement: </title><p>The authors declared no conflict of interests.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability: </title><p>The dataset presented in the study is available on request from the corresponding author during submission or after publication.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical Approval: </title><p>This study is approved under the ethical approval code of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ethics.research.ac.ir/ProposalCertificateEn.php?id=389493" ext-link-type="uri">IR.IAU.SRB.REC.1402.156</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding/Support: </title><p>This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>