<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Genom</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microb Genom</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3160</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">microgen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mgen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbial Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2057-5858</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Microbiology Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12444785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12444785.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12444785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12444785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40961326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.001500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">001500</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pathogens and Epidemiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dominance of high-risk clones ST2 and ST571 and the diversity of resistance islands in clinical Acinetobacter baumannii isolates from Hanoi, Vietnam</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nghiem</surname><given-names initials="MN">Minh Ngoc</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>nnminh.vncg@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names initials="DP">Dung Phuong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><email>nmduc.vncg@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names initials="VTT">Van Thi Thu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>ndhieu.vncg@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names initials="HT">Hop Thi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>tran.vncg@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names initials="DT">Diem Thi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>nbtram.vncg@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6746-9573</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Vo</surname><given-names initials="TTB">Thuy Thi Bich</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><email>thuytbvo.igr@gmail.com</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Institute of Biology</institution>, <institution>Vietnam Academy of Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">18 Hoang Quoc Viet, Nghia Do, Hanoi 100000</addr-line>, <country>Vietnam</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>VNU University of Science</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">334 Nguyen Trai, Hanoi 100000</addr-line>, <country>Vietnam</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Vietnam Medical Military University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">160 Phung Hung, Hanoi 100000</addr-line>, <country>Vietnam</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest regarding the publication of this article.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Thuy Thi Bich Vo, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="thuytbvo.igr@gmail.com">thuytbvo.igr@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn><p><bold>Supplement:</bold> All supporting data, code and protocols have been provided within the article or through supplementary data files. A supplementary table is available with the online version of this article.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">495975</issue-id><elocation-id>001500</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-19 10:25:44.163"><day>19</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="mgen-11-01500.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="mgen-11-9-01500.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> poses a significant threat to hospital environments worldwide, including Vietnam. In this study, we conducted whole-genome sequencing on 30 clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates from Hanoi to explore their genomic diversity, antibiotic resistance determinants, virulence factors and mobile genetic elements. Phylogenetic analyses, utilizing both SNP-based and multilocus sequence typing-based approaches, revealed that the isolates clustered into various sequence types (STs). Among these, ST2 and ST571 emerged as the dominant high-risk clones. The ST2 isolates exhibited a wide range of resistance genes, such as <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">mph(E</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">msr(E</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic>. Additionally, they contained mobile genetic elements, including plasmids and AbaR-type resistance islands, which promote horizontal gene transfer. Virulence gene analysis showed the presence of several key determinants like <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">adeFGH</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bfmRS</italic> and quorum sensing regulators <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, underscoring the strains’ potential for persistent colonization and infection. These findings highlight the marked genomic diversity and robust resistance profiles of Vietnamese <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. The predominance of ST2 and ST571, corresponding to global clones GC2 and GC1, respectively, along with frequent co-occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic>, suggests region-specific features distinct from those reported in other parts of Southeast Asia. This underscores the need for improved surveillance and targeted infection control strategies.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>antibiotic resistance genes</kwd><kwd>mobile genetic elements</kwd><kwd>multidrug resistance</kwd><kwd>virulence genes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100007224</institution-id></institution-wrap>
<institution>National Foundation for Science and Technology Development</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>106.04-2020.08</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ngoc Nghiem</surname><given-names>Minh</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Impact Statement</title></caption><p>This study highlights the genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains isolated from clinical samples in Hanoi, Vietnam. The findings indicate that these strains not only harbour multiple antibiotic resistance genes but also possess mobile genetic elements that facilitate the spread of resistance. Additionally, the presence of virulence factors suggests a potential survival advantage in the hospital environment. The analysis reveals a high prevalence of two specific sequence types, ST2 and ST571, underscoring the urgent need for enhanced surveillance and targeted infection control measures to effectively address the growing threat of multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in Vietnam.</p></boxed-text><sec id="s1"><title>Data Summary</title><p>All sequencing data and supplementary materials have been deposited under BioProject accession number PRJNA1233432 and are available at the NCBI/SRA database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/PRJNA1233432" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/PRJNA1233432</ext-link>).</p><p>The whole-genome sequencing quality assessment of 30 <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> strains in this study is listed in Table S1 (available in the online Supplementary Material).</p></sec><sec sec-type="intro" id="s2"><title>Introduction</title><p>Multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>) is a pathogen frequently encountered in hospitals, posing a significant threat to public health, particularly in intensive care units. This bacterium is known to cause severe infections such as ventilator-associated pneumonia, septicaemia, meningitis and urinary tract infections, and it is responsible for cross-contamination in healthcare settings [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The spread of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> has been reported globally, with occurrences noted in Europe, Asia-Pacific and North America [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In Vietnam, <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> species have been found in various environments, especially within hospitals, where they serve as reservoirs for antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Many strains of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> exhibit resistance to multiple classes of antibiotics, including beta-lactams, aminoglycosides, tetracyclines and fluoroquinolones. These resistant strains typically carry ARGs on mobile genetic elements (MGEs) such as plasmids, transposons and integrons, which facilitate horizontal gene transfer (HGT) between bacteria [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Key resistance genes include bla<sub>OXA-23</sub>, encoding a class D carbapenemase; armA, a 16S rRNA methyltransferase conferring aminoglycoside resistance; and the msr(E)-mph(E) pair, mediating macrolide resistance through efflux and drug modification [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">oqxA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">oqxB</italic> encode multidrug efflux pumps, while <italic toggle="yes">floR</italic> confers phenicol resistance [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Plasmids, one of the key MGEs, are extrachromosomal DNA molecules capable of autonomous replication. Certain plasmids, such as AC716 identified in this study, can carry numerous resistance genes and facilitate the horizontal spread of multidrug resistance (MDR) across bacterial populations [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Resistance islands (RIs) are large chromosomal regions acquired through HGT, carrying clusters of resistance genes embedded within mobile elements such as transposons and integrons. Notable examples include AbaR-type islands (e.g. AbaR3 and AbaR4b), which are frequently found in global clone 2 strains and contribute to carbapenem resistance [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. RIs, which contain transposons, integrons and ARGs, play a crucial role in the transmission of resistance traits, particularly among global clonal lineages. The majority of multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains belong to global clones 1 and 2. These global clones correspond to sequence types (STs) ST1 and ST2, respectively, defined using multilocus sequence typing (MLST) based on seven conserved housekeeping genes. ST2 is also referred to as global clone 2 (GC2) and ST1 as GC1 – both are epidemic lineages linked to MDR and hospital outbreaks [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Although several studies have characterized ARGs and virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>, research focusing on the genomic features of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains in Vietnam remains limited. Previous epidemiological studies on <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> in Vietnam [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] have provided insights into the clinical aspects and prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>, but a comprehensive genomic analysis is still lacking. The distribution of ARGs, virulence factors and MGEs in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains remains poorly understood in Vietnam. These gaps highlight the urgent need for further research to investigate the genomic features of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains isolated from hospitals in Vietnam.</p><p>This study hypothesizes that <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains isolated from clinical samples in Hanoi, Vietnam, possess a distinct genomic profile compared to globally distributed clones (e.g. GC1 and GC2) and previously reported Vietnamese isolates. Such differences may stem from regional antibiotic usage practices and hospital-specific selection pressures, which have been shown to influence the genomic structure and resistance profiles of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> populations in various settings [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"> 10</xref>].</p><p>A recent multicentre genomic study conducted across six hospitals in northern, central and southern Vietnam between 2017 and 2019 identified ST2 and ST571 as the most prevalent STs among carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These findings suggest that high-risk clones had already been circulating across the country prior to our investigation.</p><p>Recent findings suggest that resistance and virulence genes may co-occur within the same genome or mobile element, potentially enhancing bacterial adaptability in hospital settings [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Exploring such convergence could improve our understanding of how multidrug-resistant pathogens evolve and persist. In this context, the present study focuses on <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates collected between January and December 2022 from clinical samples at Military Hospital 103 and Military Central Hospital 108 in Hanoi, Vietnam. We hypothesize that these recent isolates may exhibit genomic features distinct from globally distributed clones (e.g. GC1/ST1 and GC2/ST2) and from earlier Vietnamese collections. Such differences could reflect regional antibiotic practices and hospital-specific selection pressures, which are known to influence the genomic structure and resistance profiles of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>.</p><p>Therefore, our primary objective is to perform whole-genome sequencing (WGS) to investigate the resistance determinants, virulence factors and MGEs of these isolates. The results will be compared with global and regional data to identify any novel genomic features that may be unique to the Vietnamese context. This work aims to support more effective surveillance and infection control strategies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Sample collection and bacterial identification</title><p>Thirty strains of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> were isolated from clinical samples, including blood, urine, sputum, wound fluid, bronchial fluid and abdominal fluid. These samples were collected from patients at the Microbiology Departments of Military Hospital 103, Military Central Hospital 108, Vietnam, between January and December 2022. Medical microbiology specialists at these hospitals identified and confirmed the bacterial samples. The <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains were tested for antibiotic susceptibility using the Phoenix BD Line 58 automated bacterial identification and susceptibility testing system.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>DNA extraction, library preparation and WGS</title><p>Bacterial DNA was extracted according to the protocol described by Sambrook and Russell (2006) [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. DNA libraries were prepared using the Illumina TruSeq DNA PCR-Free Kit following the manufacturer’s instructions. WGS was performed using the NexSeq 500 platform (Illumina). The quality of the raw sequencing data was assessed using Galaxy, an open-source bioinformatic platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://usegalaxy.org.au" ext-link-type="uri">https://usegalaxy.org.au</ext-link>), developed by the University of Melbourne, Australia. The raw data were cleaned by removing low-quality reads (e.g. reads shorter than 200 bases or containing homopolymers) using the appropriate Galaxy tools. The high-quality data were then subjected to <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> genome assembly using SPAdes v3.15.2 available within the Galaxy platform. The quality of the assembled genomes was assessed based on total genome size, maximum contig length and N50 index using Galaxy’s QUAST integration. Genome annotation was performed using the Prokka tool within Galaxy.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Bioinformatic analysis</title><p>MLST was performed using the PubMLST platform (2018) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmlst.org/organisms/acinetobacter-baumannii" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmlst.org/organisms/acinetobacter-baumannii</ext-link>) based on the Pasteur method to identify the STs of the strains. The seven housekeeping genes used for MLST analysis were <italic toggle="yes">cpn60</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">fusA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">pyrG</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">rplB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic>. ARGs were annotated using ABRIcate v1.0.1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/tseemann/abricate" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/tseemann/abricate</ext-link>) and the ResFinder database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cge.food.dtu.dk/services/ResFinder/" ext-link-type="uri">https://cge.food.dtu.dk/services/ResFinder/</ext-link>). Virulence genes were identified from the VFDB database using Galaxy’s VFanalyzer tool. Plasmids in the assembled genomes were detected using MOB-suite v3.0.3 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/phac-nml/mob-suite" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/phac-nml/mob-suite</ext-link>). The presence of recombinase integrons was identified using IntegronFinder v2.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/gem-pasteur/Integron_Finder" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/gem-pasteur/Integron_Finder</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Phylogenetic analysis and classification</title><p>The genomes of the 30 <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains were compared with reference genomes belonging to the same or closely related STs, including ACICU, BJAB0868, BJAB07104 and BJAB0715 using Roary v3.13.0 within Galaxy. Core genes were defined as those present in at least 99% of the samples and showing at least 95% similarity in <sc>aa</sc> sequence. Short-read sequencing data from the 30 samples were mapped to the reference genome of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> ATCC17978, and SNPs were analysed using Snippy v4.6.0, also available through the Galaxy interface.</p><p>A phylogenetic tree was constructed using the maximum likelihood method with RaxML v8.2.12 integrated into Galaxy. This analysis employed the GTRGAMMA model and included 250 bootstrap replicates. The tree was built from three datasets: core genome, core SNP and whole-genome core sites, where ‘core sites’ were defined as positions that appeared in all samples, including both SNPs and invariant sites. The phylogenetic tree was visualized using iTOL, which is also accessible through Galaxy.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s4"><title>Results</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>WGS quality assessment</title><p>The whole genomes of 30 <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains were successfully sequenced with high-quality results. The recovery rate ranged from 97% to 99% compared with the pre-purified sequences. The guanine-cytosine content in the samples averaged 40 mol%, both before and after purification, indicating stable genome properties. The number of contigs varied from 76 to 1761, and the total genome length was between ~3.8 million bp and over 4.5 million bp. This aligns with the genome sizes of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains documented in the NCBI database, where the N50 index varied from 4,823 to 164,357 bp (see Table S1).</p><p>The core genome-based phylogenetic tree (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>) demonstrated a clear clustering of isolates into distinct STs. Notably, strains E13BL and E45BL were grouped within the ST193 clade. The ST571 clade included multiple strains, such as E6BR, E8BR and N24BE. The ST575 clade consisted of strains E30UR and E16BL, while the ST119 clade contained N34BE. Additionally, the ST25 clade was delineated by the clustering of S101PH and N22BL, and the ST2 group showed multiple sub-branches, indicating a notable level of genetic diversity within that lineage.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Classification tree based on the core genome (<bold>a</bold>), core SNP (<bold>b</bold>) and whole-genome core site (<bold>c</bold>).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="mgen-11-01500-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>In contrast, the core SNP-based tree (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>) and the whole-genome core site-based tree (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref>), which incorporates both SNPs and invariant sites, generally produced clustering patterns consistent with the core genome tree, although some variations were noted. A notable difference was observed in the placement of strain E31AS. In the core genome tree (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>), E31AS was positioned in a distinct clade, whereas in the core SNP-based tree (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>), it remained isolated. In the whole-genome core site-based tree (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref>), E31AS grouped with N34BE within ST119.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>MLST typing and ARG profiles</title><p>MLST analysis successfully identified STs for 28 out of 30 bacterial isolates, revealing 11 distinct STs. Among them, ST2 was the most prevalent, accounting for 11/30 strains (39.29%), followed by ST571 with 6/30 strains (21.43%). Notably, two strains, E13BL and E31AS, isolated from blood and sterile fluids, did not match any known STs in the database, indicating that they may represent potential novel STs.</p><p>A total of 43 ARGs were detected across the isolates (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). The most frequently found genes included <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> (24/30), <italic toggle="yes">mph(E</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">msr(E</italic>) (22/30) and <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic> (20/30), conferring resistance to beta-lactams, macrolides and aminoglycosides. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">strB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">strA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-66</sub> were present in 18/30 isolates. <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>ADC- 25</sub> was also found in 29/30 strains; however, as a chromosomally encoded housekeeping gene, its presence alone may not imply resistance. Although <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-51-like</sub> genes are typically intrinsic to <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>, they were only detected in one strain in this dataset. This may be due to annotation artefacts or assembly limitations, as short-read sequencing sometimes fails to capture complete chromosomal elements. Less common resistance genes, such as <italic toggle="yes">aac(3)-IIa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aac(3)-IId</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aac(6′)-Ian aac(6′)-Ib-cr</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>CARB-2</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>PER-1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>NDM-1</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-58</sub>, were detected sporadically among different isolates, suggesting variations in resistance mechanisms. Tetracycline resistance was linked to the presence of <italic toggle="yes">tet(B</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">tet(39),</italic> while sulphonamide resistance was associated with <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic> (11 strains) and <italic toggle="yes">sul2</italic> (13 strains). Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">ARR-3</italic> was identified in isolates resistant to rifamycins, while <italic toggle="yes">oqxA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">oqxB</italic> were linked to MDR, and <italic toggle="yes">clmA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">floR</italic> conferred resistance to phenicol antibiotics.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Distribution of ARGs in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="mgen-11-01500-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Most <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates exhibited MDR, possessing genes that conferred resistance to at least three antibiotic classes. The E43PH strain (ST16) and S101PH and N22BL strains (ST25) were found to carry up to 16 resistance genes, indicating broad-spectrum resistance. Notably, the E43PH strain was the only one harbouring <italic toggle="yes">aac(6′)-Ib-cr</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aac(6′)-Ib3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>CARB-2</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-70</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>NDM-1</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">floR</italic>. The E18BR, E24PH and E25PH strains (ST2) possessed 14 resistance genes, underscoring the high resistance potential within this lineage.</p><p>These results indicate that the SNP-based approach yields a higher-resolution phylogenetic tree, enabling a more detailed differentiation among closely related bacterial isolates compared with the MLST-based methods. Concerning the ST distribution of ARGs in the 30 strains, we observed that all ST2 strains contained the <italic toggle="yes">strB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">strA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>ADC-25</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-66</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">tet(B</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">mph(E</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">msr(E</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic> genes (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). ST2 strains carry a varying number of ARGs, ranging from 9 to 14 genes. Two isolates, S-101PH and N-22BL, belonging to ST25, exhibited identical ARGs. A total of five out of six strains from ST571 had identical ARGs, except for the E-6BR isolate, which lacked the <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic> gene. Two unidentified STs of E-13BL and E-31AS strains had significantly fewer resistance genes than the others; however, the E-31AS strain was the only one that carried the <italic toggle="yes">oqxA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">oqxB</italic> genes.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Distribution of ARGs according to STs.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="mgen-11-01500-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Virulence genes</title><p>A total of 48 virulence genes were identified across the strains, categorized into adherence, biofilm formation, immune evasion, iron uptake, regulation and serum resistance (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). All 12 strains harboured mutations in all 48 genes. The genes <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">adeFGH</italic> efflux pump, PNAG, phospholipase D/C, lipopolysaccharide, <italic toggle="yes">bfmRS</italic> and pbpG were found in every strain. Additionally, 21 out of 30 strains carried both <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes, which are associated with quorum sensing regulation. However, the <italic toggle="yes">csu</italic>A/B/C/D/E genes that encode Csu pili and the <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic> gene were absent in strains E-16BL and E-30UR.</p><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Distribution of virulence genes in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="mgen-11-01500-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>MGE related to ARGs: plasmids and RIs</title><p>A total of 36 plasmids were identified across 30 strains, with 10 of these plasmids detected in at least 5 strains (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Among them, 19 plasmids were found to carry ARGs, predominantly <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA</sub> genes. The AE272 plasmid was the most frequently observed, present in 24 strains, but interestingly, it did not contain any ARGs. In contrast, the AC716 plasmid, which was found in four strains, harboured 12 ARGs. The resistance genes encoded in these plasmids primarily conferred resistance to beta-lactams and aminoglycosides, although resistance genes for sulphonamide, tetracycline and phenicol were also identified (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). WGS revealed the presence of 15 RIs. The strains N-20BL, E-25PH, E-24PH, E-18BR and E-11UR had the highest number of RIs, with each carrying 13. Strains S-101PH, N-22BL (ST25) and E-9PH, E-33PH (ST2) harboured 12 RIs each. In contrast, strains E-13BL and E-31AS (unassigned STs), E-45BL (ST193) and N-34BE (ST119) lacked any detectable RIs. Additionally, the transposons Tn6166 and Tn6167 were found in 14 strains, primarily belonging to ST2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=10), ST571 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=3) and ST16 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=1). An RI structurally similar to AbaR4, lacking a full Tn6022 core and carrying IS26 insertions, was found in 24 isolates (mainly ST2), while a structure resembling AbaR3 was identified in the ST16 strain E-43PH.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Details of predicted plasmids from MOB-suite</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARG (in all isolates containing plasmids)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE272</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE271</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-91_1, <italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-120_1, <italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-67_1, <italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-66_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC163</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD096</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mph(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">msr(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic>_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE689</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC715</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1, <italic toggle="yes">aph(3')-</italic>VIb_1, <italic toggle="yes">sul2</italic>_2, <italic toggle="yes">tet(B)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">aph(6)-</italic>Id_1, <italic toggle="yes">aph(3'')-</italic>Ib_2, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>_5, <italic toggle="yes">ant(3'')-</italic>Ia_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AH171</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC237</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>_5, <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic>_1, <italic toggle="yes">msr(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">mph(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">blaTEM</italic>-1D_1, <italic toggle="yes">ant(3'')-</italic>Ia_1, <italic toggle="yes">aph(3')-</italic>Ia_7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF972</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB082</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC716</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mph(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">msr(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic>_1, <italic toggle="yes">aac(6')-</italic>Ian_1, <italic toggle="yes">aac(3)-</italic>IIa_1, <italic toggle="yes">aph(3''</italic>)-Ib_2, <italic toggle="yes">aph(6)-</italic>Id_1, <italic toggle="yes">ARR</italic>-3_4, <italic toggle="yes">cmlA1</italic>_1, <italic toggle="yes">blaPER</italic>-7_1, <italic toggle="yes">tet(B</italic>)_1, <italic toggle="yes">sul1</italic>_5, <italic toggle="yes">sul2</italic>_2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB413</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB702</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ant(2''</italic>)-Ia_13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB114</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">floR</italic>_2, <italic toggle="yes">sul2</italic>_2, <italic toggle="yes">msr(E</italic>)_1, <italic toggle="yes">mph(E</italic>)_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB355</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tet(39</italic>)_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB880</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AG457</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">aac(3</italic>)-IIa_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE373</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">aph(3')-</italic>VI_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC861</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">aph(6</italic>)-Id_1, <italic toggle="yes">mph(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">msr(E)_</italic>1, <italic toggle="yes">aac(3)-</italic>IId_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">novel_12a6c3e2aa896865d52105c3a512fa08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">novel_207dfe76ce26e19a7b48fd531546ec09</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">novel_3bc7128461026ecd275d380a6d6c4e2e</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">novel_bbdf6f0e1a3b520c977560c2d8e4694e</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">novel_f19e0bb1c1d87ddd7be8c2c69cf27e78</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">blaOXA</italic>-23_1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA665</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB338</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB408</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB412</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB826</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB872</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE187</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE688</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">novel_5c056d5ca175dc725a432bbade889fd8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">novel_7fb9056a1ed08de2b69dda1c3b6330f6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Distribution of plasmids and RIs in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="mgen-11-01500-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Co-occurrence and co-localization of resistance and virulence genes</title><p>To explore the relationship between ARGs and virulence factors, we examined their distribution across the 30 <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates. A notable pattern was observed between the carbapenem resistance gene <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> (present in 24/30 isolates) and the quorum sensing regulator <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> (21/30), which frequently co-occurred within the same strains. Similarly, the aminoglycoside resistance gene <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic> (20/30) often appeared in isolates carrying <italic toggle="yes">bfmRS</italic>, a key transcriptional regulator found universally in this dataset. In contrast, widely distributed genes such as <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>ADC-25</sub> (29/30) and <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> did not show any specific co-distribution pattern.</p><p>In terms of physical linkage, plasmid and RI analysis revealed that the AC716 plasmid (found in four isolates) carried both <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, suggesting potential co-localization of resistance and regulatory functions. The AbaR4b RI, present in 24 isolates, frequently carried <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> along with <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> (18/30), pointing to a mechanism for joint dissemination of resistance and quorum sensing traits. In contrast, the AE272 plasmid, though prevalent (24/30), lacked both resistance and virulence genes, highlighting the functional diversity of mobile elements within the <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> genome.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5"><title>Discussion</title><p>The results from WGS revealed marked genetic diversity among the 30 <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> strains studied, with ST distribution showing a predominance of ST2 and ST571. ST2 is widely recognized as a high-risk clonal lineage associated with MDR and global dissemination [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In our study, ST2 accounted for 39.29% of the strains, which aligns with previous research highlighting its clinical importance in nosocomial infections [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Similarly, ST571 made up 21.43% of the strains and has been increasingly reported in hospital outbreaks, particularly in cases involving carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The high prevalence of these STs suggests that they are well adapted to withstand antimicrobial pressures and have a strong ability to persist in healthcare environments.</p><p>A key observation in this study was the correlation between ST and antibiotic resistance profiles. All ST2 isolates contained a core set of resistance genes, including <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-66</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">strB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">strA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tet(B</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">mph(E</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">msr(E</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic>. These genes confer resistance to beta-lactams, aminoglycosides, tetracyclines and macrolides. The high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub>, a significant carbapenemase gene, is particularly concerning, as it is a major contributor to carbapenem resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> globally [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The co-occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">mph(E</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">msr(E</italic>) in multiple strains suggests that macrolide resistance may be more widespread than previously recognized. A study analysing azithromycin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> isolates from various animal sources found that the <italic toggle="yes">msr(E)-mph(E</italic>) gene pair was present in all animal groups examined, indicating a broad distribution of these resistance determinants [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Interestingly, the two unclassified STs (E-13BL and E-31AS) showed notably fewer resistance genes, with E-31AS uniquely harbouring <italic toggle="yes">oqxA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">oqxB</italic> genes, which contribute to MDR through efflux mechanisms [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>In addition to individual resistance genes, the presence of RIs and plasmids highlights the role of HGT in the development of antimicrobial resistance. Our study identified 36 plasmids, 19 of which carry resistance genes, including several variants of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA</sub>. The AC716 plasmid was detected in 4 strains and contained 12 resistance genes, emphasizing the role of plasmid-mediated dissemination in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> resistance evolution [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Additionally, the detection of AbaR4b in 24 isolates supports earlier research, showing that AbaR-type RIs are characteristic of MDR <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. While our findings confirm the importance of these genetic elements in acquiring resistance, more functional studies are needed to understand their specific contributions to observable resistance.</p><p>Virulence analysis showed that a wide range of virulence genes are present across all strains, including <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">adeFGH</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bfmRS</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pbpG</italic>. These genes are essential for processes such as adherence, biofilm formation and immune evasion [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Importantly, quorum sensing regulators <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> were detected in 21 out of 30 isolates, suggesting a potential role in regulating virulence and biofilm development. The absence of csuA/B/C/D/E and bap in the E-16BL and E-30UR strains suggests possible changes in their ability to form biofilms, which may affect colonization and persistence [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>The co-occurrence of resistance genes (<italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">armA</italic>) and virulence regulators (<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bfmRS</italic>) in ST2 and ST571 strains suggests a convergent adaptation strategy favouring both antimicrobial survival and enhanced colonization. This convergence has been observed in global high-risk clones and is increasingly recognized as a factor driving clinical persistence of <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>The identification of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> on the same plasmid (AC716), and of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> with <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> on the AbaR4b RI, suggests the potential for co-transfer of resistance and virulence genes via MGEs. The regulatory systems <italic toggle="yes">abaI/abaR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bfmRS</italic> are known to control biofilm formation, quorum sensing and virulence expression, which may increase fitness under hospital conditions [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>Interestingly, MGEs such as AE272, although widely distributed, did not carry either resistance or virulence genes, highlighting the heterogeneity of MGEs in <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>. While short-read sequencing limits the confirmation of physical linkage, the frequent co-occurrence of resistance and virulence determinants in MGE-positive strains suggests a need for long-read genome analysis. Understanding how MGEs shape the spread of pathogenic traits is essential for infection control and antibiotic stewardship strategies.</p><p>The predominance of ST2 and ST571 in our isolates aligns with global reports, where ST2 is widely recognized as a dominant multidrug-resistant clone in Asia and Europe [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"> 15</xref>]. ST571 has also been increasingly reported in Southeast Asia [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Based on MLST analysis, ST571 is a double-locus variant of ST2, differing at only two housekeeping loci. This close relationship suggests that both STs may share core resistance and virulence features, while exhibiting minor genomic variations. Although both ST2 and ST571 were dominant in our dataset, phylogenetic analysis revealed that they form distinct clades with different RI structures and gene content. ST2 is a well-characterized international clone, whereas ST571 appears to be more geographically restricted and less extensively studied.</p><p>Notably, the co-localization of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-23</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> on plasmid AC716 and the widespread presence of AbaR4b suggest possible local adaptations of global clones. While similar MGEs have been observed globally, recent studies also highlight the acquisition of <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>NDM</sub> and novel RIs in ST2 strains from other regions, indicating ongoing evolution under antibiotic pressure [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s6"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study demonstrates that clinical <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> isolates from Hanoi display significant genetic diversity, with ST2 and ST571 being the predominant high-risk clones. These strains carry multiple ARGs and MGEs that facilitate the spread of resistance, along with key virulence factors that enhance their survival in hospital settings. Our findings underscore the urgent need for improved surveillance and targeted infection control measures to address the threat posed by multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic> in Vietnam.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="ST1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.001500</object-id><label>Uncited Table S1.</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mgen-11-01500-s001.xlsx" id="d67e1356" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This research was funded by the Vietnam National Foundation for Science and Technology Development (NAFOSTED) under grant no. 106.04-2020.08.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Author contributions:</bold> All the authors contributed to the study conception and design. Material preparation, data collection and analysis were performed by D.P.B., V.T.T.H., H.T.T., D.T.N. and T.T.B.V. The first draft of the manuscript was written by M.N.N., and all the authors commented on previous versions of the manuscript. All the authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethical statement:</bold> This study was approved by the institutional review board of the Institute of Genome Research (IGR), Vietnam Academy of Science and Technology (VAST), based on the contract number 31/2020/106/HĐTN. All the studies were also conducted and designed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki or other comparable ethical standards. Informed consent was not required by our IRB from all patients included in this study. This research did not affect the patients’ health or privacy. The bacteria were stored and not specifically isolated as part of this study.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>
<italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>
</term><def><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ARG</term><def><p>antibiotic resistance gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HGT</term><def><p>horizontal gene transfer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDR</term><def><p>multidrug resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MGE</term><def><p>mobile genetic element</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MLST</term><def><p>multilocus sequence typing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RI</term><def><p>resistance island</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ST</term><def><p>sequence type</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WGS</term><def><p>whole-genome sequencing</p></def></def-item></def-list></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoub Moubareck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hammoudi Halat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Insights into <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: a review of microbiological, virulence, and resistance traits in a threatening nosocomial pathogen</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics</italic>
</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9030119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32178356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7148516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Castanheira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gales</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Global epidemiology and mechanisms of resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>-calcoaceticus complex</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>S166</fpage><lpage>S178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciad109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37125466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10150277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Toan</surname><given-names>NQ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phuong</surname><given-names>NTK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sy</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nghien</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the effectiveness of some interventions to reduce hospitalacquired infections in intensive care units, 108 military central hospital</article-title><source>J 108-Clin Med Pham</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.52389/ydls.v0i0.2296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kyriakidis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vasileiou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pana</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tragiannidis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> antibiotic resistance mechanisms</article-title><source>Pathogens</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>373</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens10030373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33808905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8003822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ovsepian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leekitcharoenphon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Seyfarth</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mordhorst</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Azithromycin resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> from food-producing animals and meat in Europe</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2024</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1657</fpage><lpage>1667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkae161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38775752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11215539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Bacterial multidrug efflux pumps at the frontline of antimicrobial resistance: an overview</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>520</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11040520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35453271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9032748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z-Q</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> coordinates central metabolism, plasmid dissemination, and virulence by sensing nutrient availability</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e0227623</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mbio.02276-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37855599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10746170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Spread of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> global clone 2 in Asia and AbaR-type resistance islands</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2013</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>5239</fpage><lpage>5246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00633-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23939892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3811275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Emergence, molecular mechanisms and global spread of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Microb Genom</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6861865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31599224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Diep</surname><given-names>DTH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ngoc</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vinh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dung</surname><given-names>TTN</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The clinical features and genomic epidemiology of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections at a tertiary hospital in Vietnam</article-title><source>J Glob Antimicrob Resist</source><year>2023</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgar.2023.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37120145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10275762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thi</surname><given-names>NNP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thi</surname><given-names>BVT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and antibiotic resistance assessment of Acinetobacter baumannii isolates from respiratory specimens collected at Can Tho General Hospital</article-title><source>J App Biol Biotech</source><year>2024</year><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7324/JABB.2024.146101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huy</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Đac</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cuong</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Genomic epidemiology and resistant genes of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> clinical strains in Vietnamese hospitals</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><year>2024</year><volume>73</volume><elocation-id>001922</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.001922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39475466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11524319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>AFA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Agamy</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zafer</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Genetic configuration of genomic resistance islands in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> clinical isolates from Egypt</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>878912</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.878912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35935207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9353178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Purification of nucleic acids by extraction with phenol: chloroform</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Protoc</source><year>2006</year><volume>2006</volume><elocation-id>db</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/pdb.prot4455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22485786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Nosocomial surveillance of multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: a genomic epidemiological study</article-title><source>Microbiol Spectr</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e0220723</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.02207-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38197661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10846281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Genovese</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>La Fauci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>D’Amato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Squeri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anzalone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Molecular epidemiology of antimicrobial resistant microorganisms in the 21th century: a review of the literature</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Acta Biomed</italic>
</source><year>2020</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23750/abm.v91i2.9176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32420962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7569612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hennon</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Uncovering the mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> virulence</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29249812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6571207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eijkelkamp</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stroeher</surname><given-names>UH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of surface-exposed virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genom</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1020</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-1020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4256060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25422040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Šeputienė</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Povilonis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sužiedėlienė</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Novel variants of AbaR resistance islands with a common backbone in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates of European Clone II</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2012</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1969</fpage><lpage>1973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.05678-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22290980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3318354</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>