<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">44</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcmicr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2180</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12701606</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12701606.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12701606</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12701606</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41390371</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-025-04507-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4507</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Deciphering the efficacy of staphyloxanthin-encapsulated niosomal nanovesicles to attenuate biofilm formation, quorum sensing, and meropenem persistence in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nosair</surname><given-names initials="AM">Ahmed M.</given-names></name><address><email>ahmed.nosir@pharm.tanta.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelaziz</surname><given-names initials="AA">Ahmed A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abo-Kamar</surname><given-names initials="AM">Amal M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Madboly</surname><given-names initials="LA">Lamiaa A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5954-7842</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Farghali</surname><given-names initials="MH">Mahmoud H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/016jp5b92</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412258.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9477 7793</institution-id><institution>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Tanta University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tanta, 31527 Egypt </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478510</issue-id><elocation-id>791</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-12-15 18:25:13.670"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12866_2025_Article_4507.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is the primary cause of persistent opportunistic infections in healthcare settings, recognized as a global priority due to its resistance to antibiotic therapy. Quorum sensing and biofilm formation are the key factors driving the pathogenesis and drug resistance of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Nanostructures demonstrated encouraging promise in enhancing the therapeutic efficacy and overcoming treatment failure. Therefore, the efficacy of staphyloxanthin (STX)-encapsulated niosomes was evaluated both in vitro and in vivo.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">The formulated niosomal nanovesicles displayed a spherical shape at the nanoscale (177.8 nm), featuring a slow-release rate (39.6%) and appropriate entrapment efficiency (92.7%). Our results demonstrated that STX exhibited strong antibacterial activity, with MIC values up to 16 µg/mL against multidrug-resistant isolates (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24). The in vitro findings revealed that the encapsulation of STX within niosomal nanovesicles demonstrated superior therapeutic efficacy compared to the free solution. This improvement was reflected by a significant reduction in biofilm formation (68–88%), motility (66.66–94.45%), and siderophore production (48.75–79.5%), as well as marked disruption of the mature biofilm by 82%. The anti-quorum sensing activity of STX was further confirmed the attenuation of biofilm and virulence, as evidenced by downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> expression (1.42-fold reduction) and molecular docking simulations. It is noteworthy that the biological findings revealed a significant eradication of meropenem-induced persister cells after the addition of niosomal dispersion. The preclinical investigations prove the efficacy of STX in improving survival rates through reducing the bacterial burden (2-fold reduction) and lethal inflammatory consequences in a mouse model of pneumonia.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">our results suggested that STX may serve as a promising alternative for combating <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilms and persister cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12866-025-04507-1.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Acinetobacter baumannii</kwd><kwd>Staphyloxanthin</kwd><kwd>Niosomes</kwd><kwd>Biofilm</kwd><kwd>Quorum sensing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Tanta University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par4">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is an opportunistic human pathogen that predominantly leads to nosocomial infections in individuals with compromised immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It is commonly associated with diseases such as ventilator-associated pneumonia, wound infections, meningitis, endocarditis, bacteraemia, as well as infections of the respiratory and urinary tracts. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is one of the most frequently found infections in intensive care neonatal and burn units [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA) has classified it as a pathogen among “ESKAPE” bacteria owing to its resistance to standard antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The World Health Organization (WHO) report categorizes this issue as critical within the hierarchy of multidrug-resistant (MDR) bacteria, posing an extreme threat to human health. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> resistance to multiple antibiotics is experiencing a significant increase on a global scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The development of drug resistance occurs through a variety of mechanisms, involving efflux pumps, secretion systems, alterations to the outer membrane, biofilm formation, and quorum sensing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The two-component AbaI/AbaR system, a homologue of the LuxI/LuxR system seen in other Gram-negative bacteria, comprises up <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>’s quorum sensing system. The two-component regulatory system initiates a series of reactions that subsequently modify the expression of various genes regulated by quorum sensing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Antibiotic resistance and the pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> are primarily driven by biofilm formation, a significant factor among the diverse mechanisms of virulence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">Biofilms constitute a bacterial community embedded within a matrix of extracellular polysaccharides, proteins, and DNA, adhering to biotic and abiotic surfaces. These structures augment the capacity of bacteria to induce infectious diseases, adhere tenaciously to biological surfaces, circumvent the host’s innate immune defenses, and foster antibiotic resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Additionally, patients with prosthetic medical equipment are particularly vulnerable to the serious health issues associated with chronic biofilms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In addition to its multi-drug resistance, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> demonstrates multidrug tolerance, a phenomenon facilitated by persister cells that withstand high concentrations of antibiotics and subsequently contribute to the persistence of chronic infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. This situation underscores the urgent necessity for the advancement of novel antimicrobial treatments.</p><p id="Par6">Staphyloxanthin (STX) is a prominent pigment produced from Staphylococcus aureus and belongs to a particular class of apocarotenoid triterpenoid pigments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The oxidative cleavage of C40 isoprenoids yields apocarotenoids in both plants and microbes. While other processes are employed in the non-enzymatic synthesis of apocarotenoids, carotenoid cleavage dioxygenases (CCDs) are crucial in the enzymatic generation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Most of carotenoids’ biological activity is thought to be due to their propensity to produce reactive oxygen species (ROS), which in turn cause oxidative stress, inhibit ion-membrane interactions, and change the cellular permeability through active solute transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Recently, a plethora of research has explored the carotenoids and their possible applications in the battle against parasitic and bacterial infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">A novel approach to enhance the therapeutic effects of a drug involves administration in the form of nanostructures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Nano-carriers, including niosomes, have been extensively utilized to improve the therapeutic efficacy of drugs and facilitate their delivery. Niosomes are bilayered structures that are composed of biocompatible materials, specifically non-ionic surfactants and cholesterol, which function as lipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. These nanovesicles are extremely biocompatible and water-soluble, with the ability to transport both hydrophobic and hydrophilic agents. Preventing chemical deterioration and the adverse effects of unfavorable environmental conditions, this method of drug delivery substantially enhances the physical stability of the pharmaceutical compound [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Regarding the aforementioned scenario, this study relies on the evaluation of STX, both free solution and niosomes, in combating <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p><p id="Par8">In this study, the antibacterial activity of STX against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was evaluated both in vitro and in vivo as a drug solution and niosomal dispersion. Furthermore, STX activity was assessed for attenuation of biofilm formation, quorum sensing, virulence, and meropenem persistence.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Materials</title><p id="Par9">The STX pigment was extracted from <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> A2 (accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="PP197164">PP197164</ext-link>). Our previous research addressed the laboratory extraction, purification, chemical validation, and safety profile of STX on normal Vero cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Sorbitan monostearate (Span 60), cholesterol, and dialysis membrane (Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO, USA) were procured from the Pharmaceutical Technology Department of the Faculty of Pharmacy at Tanta University, Egypt.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Bacterial isolates and susceptibility pattern determination</title><p id="Par10">Thirty <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were retrieved from microbiological laboratories in the Tanta University Hospitals. The isolation of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was performed using macConkey agar (HiMedia Laboratories Pvt. Limited, Mumbai, India). Following their recovery, the isolated colonies were presumed to be <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> using an assortment of standard biochemical techniques and Gram staining analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The isolates were subsequently streaked on HiCrome™ agar (HiMedia Laboratories Pvt. Limited, Mumbai, India), and the light purple colonies were picked up for confirmation by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS). For subsequent investigations, the bacterial isolates were kept at −80 °C in tryptic soy broth with 40% (v/v) glycerol. The assessment of antimicrobial susceptibility for the isolated <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was performed using the Kirby-Bauer disc diffusion method on Mueller Hinton agar (MHA) plates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], according to Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI), 2020 guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 19,606 served as a quality control strain.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Preparation of niosomal formulation encapsulating staphyloxanthin</title><p id="Par11">The composition of the niosomal formulation listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> was utilized following the previously reported investigation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The hydration technique, as previously described, was employed to create niosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In essence, cholesterol and span 60 (surfactant) were melted on a water bath at 55 °C. A clear liquid was produced by dissolving STX in 5 mL of ethanol and then adding the solution to the melted components while combining. By progressively incorporating 5 mL of water during the mixing process, a homogeneous mixture was achieved. Proniosomal creamy gel was generated through continuous mixing during chilling. To prepare the surfactant nanovesicles, proniosomes were hydrated. This was achieved by employing continuous mixture to develop homogenous niosomal dispersion, with the remaining water being incrementally incorporated. By overnight incubation at room temperature, the niosomal dispersion was permitted to endure swelling and hydration. Bath sonication was employed to reduce the size of the prepared distended vesicles for a duration of 45 min upon cooling with ice crystals. STX-loaded niosomes were generated at a final concentration of 3 mg/mL in triplicate (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3).</p><p id="Par12">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Composition of Niosomal formulation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Formulation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amount or volume</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Span 60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2 g</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cholesterol</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3 g</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethanol</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 mL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Staphyloxanthin</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.075 g</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Distilled water</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Up to 25 mL</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Characterization of the formulated niosomes</title><p id="Par13">The morphology and size of the produced niosomal formulation were evaluated using transmission electron microscopy (TEM; JEOL – JSM1400 PLUS, Tokyo, Japan) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Niosomes were diluted 1:200 in HPLC-filtered distilled water. A single niosomal dispersion droplet dried on a carbon grid. The grid was then stained with saturated uranyl acetate dissolved in 70% ethanol for 5 min and lead citrate for 2 min. The sample was carefully placed in the holder for TEM. Photomicrographs were obtained by carefully calibrating magnification. Moreover, vesicles’ size and zeta potential were ascertained using Zetasizer Nano-ZS (Malvern Instruments, UK) at 25 °C. A appropriate scattering intensity was achieved by diluting 1 mL of the vesicular dispersion (1:200) with HPLC-filtered distilled water before examination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The measurements were carried out in triplicate (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Entrapment efficiency and drug content</title><p id="Par14">The niosomes’ encapsulation effectiveness was assessed after the free STX pigment was separated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The nanovesicles were centrifuged for 90 min at 12,000x g and the liquid phase supernatant was carefully separated from the solid residue pellet. Measurements of absorbance at 456 nm determined the supernatant’s unentrapped STX content. According to the equation, the entrapment effectiveness EE% was obtained by subtracting the free STX content from the total STX employed in vesical formulation: <inline-formula id="IEq1"><tex-math id="d33e426">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\;\text{EE}\%\;=\;\lbrack(\text{A}\;-\;\text{B})/\text{A}\rbrack\;\times\;100\%$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par15">A: Initial STX content in vesical formulation. B: unentrapped STX in supernatant.</p><p id="Par16">The loading efficiency (LE) was STX encapsulated per lipid. As indicated in the calculation, this better showed the niosomes’ ability to load STX compared to the formulation’s total lipid:<inline-formula id="IEq2"><tex-math id="d33e434">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text{Actual encapsulated medication}/\text{formulation lipid}\:=\:\text{LE}\;(\text{mg}/\text{g})$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>In-vitro drug release</title><p id="Par17">STX release from encapsulated nanovesicles was monitored in-vitro using the dialysis membrane technique [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The dialysis membrane was a cellulose acetate membrane with a molecular weight cut-off of 10,500 Da (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany). The donor compartment was loaded with 2 mL of niosomes and submerged in 70 mL of ethanol: PBS (50:50) at pH 7.4. The sink condition was maintained by using this receptor fluid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The system ran at 37 °C with 50 rpm agitation. The blank for UV analysis was a 3 mg/mL solution of STX, identical to the release media employed in the experiment. The blank provides a baseline for the UV-visible spectrophotometer, ensuring reliable drug release measurements without interference from the release medium. Spectrophotometry at 456 nm was used to analyze samples taken at various intervals (60, 120, 180, 240, 300, 360, 420, 480, 600, and 1440 min). The rate of STX release over time was used to determine the drug release kinetics. The measurements were carried out in triplicate (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Stability of niosomes</title><p id="Par18">Monitoring niosomes over a predetermined period of time in terms of particular properties is one way to verify their stability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In short, the size and EE% of 1 mL of STX-nisomes were assessed. The requirements were monitored for a month at two different temperatures: 4 and 25 °C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Determination of Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC)</title><p id="Par19">According to the CLSI 2020 standard methodology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], the broth micro-dilution test was employed in order to examine the antibacterial activity. Different dilutions of free STX and niosomes containing STX (2–1024 µg/mL) were tested for MIC values using Mueller-Hinton (MH) broth against challenging exponentially grown tested bacteria with final density of 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL. The microplates were scrutinized after an overnight incubation at 37 °C, with the turbidity of the broth serving as an indicator for the growth of the microorganism under investigation. The MIC value was defined at the lowest concentration with no discernible growth. To determine the minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC), 10 µL of clear wells were spot-spotted onto LB agar plates and incubated at 37 <sup>◦</sup>C for 24 h. MBC was detected with no growth at the lowest concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Biofilm formation</title><p id="Par20">The capacity of MDR <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24) to promote the formation of biofilm was examined using the crystal violet assay as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. In essence, 96-well microtitration plates with tryptic soy broth (TSB) media and 1% glucose were used to cultivate the bacterial isolates for 24 h at 37 °C. After discarding the cultures, phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) was used to wash the plates twice. After 15 min of 0.1% crystal violet staining the ensuing biofilm, the leftover stain was washed off with PBS. Using a microtiter reader (SunriseTM, TECAN, Switzerland), the stained-biofilm was solubilized by 33% (vol/vol) glacial acetic acid and measured by absorbance at 595 nm. After biofilm quantification, strong biofilm-producing isolates were selected for further investigation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Effect on growth kinetics</title><p id="Par21">After inoculating strong biofilm-producing isolates (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8) into double-strength LB broth (with an optical density of 600 nm = 0.3), 100 µL was dispensed into each well of a microtiter plate. Subsequently, 100 µL of STX at concentrations of 0, 0.25, 0.5, and 0.75 MIC was aspirated with a micropipette, and the mixture was thoroughly combined. A microplate reader (Sunrise™, TECAN, Switzerland) measured optical densities at 630 nm at intervals of 0, 2, 4, 6, and 12 h. The impact of STX-niosomes on the growth of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolate<italic toggle="yes">s</italic> was illustrated by plotting the observed optical densities over time (h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Biofilm inhibition assay</title><p id="Par22">The impact of free STX and niosomes on biofilm formation were evaluated as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Briefly, overnight cultures of the tested isolated were diluted to 0.5 McFarland (1.5 × 10<sup>8</sup> CFU mL<sup>− 1</sup>) and incubated with the treatments (0.5 MIC) for 24 h at 37 °C. Biofilm biomass was quantified using crystal violet staining. Lastly, the percentage of biofilm inhibition was determined by applying the following formula: (%) = [(Control OD<sub>570</sub>nm - Treated OD<sub>570</sub>nm)/Control OD<sub>570</sub>nm] × 100.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Air–liquid interface biofilm formation assay</title><p id="Par23">To evaluate the impact of STX on ring biofilm formation at the air–liquid interface, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were grown for 24 h at 37 °C in glass tubes with 2 mL of TSB supplemented with or without STX treatment (0.5 MIC). The tubes were rinsed three times with PBS after incubation and then stained with a 0.4% crystal violet solution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Assessment of pellicle formation</title><p id="Par24">The methodology for testing pellicle formation was adapted from earlier approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In summary, overnight bacterial cultures were diluted 1:100 in 5 ml TSB and incubated in glass tubes at 37 °C for 72 h under static condition. The pellicle material was quantified by introducing 1 ml of ethanol into the tube, extracting the floating pellicles, and resuspending them in PBS. A spectrophotometer (SunriseTM, TECAN, Switzerland) was employed to quantify OD<sub>600</sub> values.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Microbial Adhesion to Hydrocarbon assay (MATH)</title><p id="Par25">The MATH test was employed to evaluate the impact of STX on the cell surface hydrophobicity (CSH) of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, as previously mentioned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Briefly, bacterial isolated were inoculated in TSB without and with treatment (0.5 MIC) and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. The cells were centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min. Following three rinses with 1 PBS, the absorbance of the cell solution was measured at 600 nm. Subsequently, 1 mL of toluene was incorporated into the cell suspension and vortexed for 10 min. The solution was allowed to undergo phase separation. Subsequent to the removal of the organic phase, the optical density (OD) of the cell suspension was assessed at 600 nm. The hydrophobicity index was derived from CSH use the formula:</p><p id="Par26">Hydrophobicity index = (1 - OD600 after vortexing/OD600 before vortexing)) x 100.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Quantification of exopolysaccharide (EPS)</title><p id="Par27">The impact of STX on the production of EPS was previously evaluated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In brief, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were incubated in LB broth with and without treatment (0.5 MIC). Following a 24-h incubation period at 37 °C, the particles were suspended in PBS and subsequently centrifuged at 8000 × g for 10 min. The supernatant was centrifuged after being combined with an equal volume of ethyl alcohol. Finally, the EPS solution (1 mL) was meticulously combined with cold 5% phenol (1 mL) and concentrated sulphuric acid (5 mL). The optical density of the resultant red color at 490 nm was measured to determine the percentage of reduction in EPS following STX treatment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Biofilm disruption assay</title><p id="Par28">The biofilm-eradicating efficacy of STX was evaluated by inducing a biofilm of strong biofilm-producing isolates in a 96-well polystyrene microtiter plate for 48 h. The adhered phase was subsequently rinsed twice with PBS after the planktonic cells were removed. The remaining adhered cells were subsequently treated with 200 µL of tryptic soya broth (TSB) medium alone or treatment (MIC) for 24 h at 37 <sup>◦</sup>C. Total biomass and biofilm-adhered cell viability were measured. Biofilms were scraped and resuspended in PBS to count colony-forming unit (CFU). Following serial dilution, 100 µL of each dilution was plated on LB agar and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. Subsequently, the crystal violet staining assay was employed to quantify the total biomass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. To verify the eradication activity, STX’s ability to destroy the mature biofilm was further evaluated on glass surfaces. In a 6-well plate, biofilms were formed on coverslips. Following treatment, biofilms were visualized using a compound bright field microscope (Labomed, California, America) at a magnification of ×40 after being stained with crystal violet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Confocal Laser Scanning Microscopy (CLSM)</title><p id="Par29">The biofilm eradication activity of STX on the established biofilm was visualized under a CLSM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The biofilm was induced into an 8-well µ--Slide (ibidi, Martinsried, Germany) after 48 h. The Live/Dead fluorescent dye (Invitrogen) was used to stain the wells following the treatment. Subsequently, biofilms were examined under CLSM at ×20 magnification (DMi8; Leica Microsystems). Dead cells were labelled with propidium iodide (red fluorescent), while viable cells were labelled with acridine orange (green fluorescent).</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Motility assay</title><p id="Par30">The impact of STX treatments (free and niosomes) on the motility of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii isolates</italic> was assessed through swarming and twitching motility assays [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. To perform the swarming motility, 0.5% MHA plates were prepared with and without STX treatments at concentrations of 0.5 MIC. Subsequently, 5 µL of overnight culture was introduced to the central region of the agar plates and incubated at 37 °C for 72 h. The motility zone was assessed following incubation. To test twitching motility, a sterile toothpick was used to pierce the overnight culture on a 1% MHA plate from the middle to the bottom. The plate was then incubated at 37 °C for 72 h. Plates were rinsed with PBS and stained with 0.4% crystal violet solution after the agar was properly eliminated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Siderophore estimation assay</title><p id="Par31">The impact of STX treatments (free and niosomes) on the extent of siderophores secreted by bacterial isolates was assessed by the universal Chrom Azurol S (CAS) assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In a nutshell, the bacterial cultures were incubated at 37 °C for 24 h in 5 mL of TSB with and without treatment at a concentration of 0.5 MIC. Following incubation, 1 mL of the bacterial cultures was centrifuged at 4900x g for 20 min. In triplicate, 100 µL of the siderophore-containing supernatant was transferred to 96-well microtitration plates, which already contained 100 µL of CAS-hexadecyl trimethyl ammonium bromide (CAS-HDTMA) solution. A blank and positive control were established in wells that contained only fresh medium and 15 mM EDTA, respectively. The plates were incubated for 30 min in the dark. Lastly, the plate reader was employed to measure the absorbance at a wavelength of 630 nm. According to the following equation, the siderophore content is then calculated.</p><p id="Par32">% siderophore units = ((A<sub>r</sub> - A<sub>s</sub>)/A<sub>r</sub>) x 100.</p><p id="Par33">In this equation, A<sub>r</sub> represents the reference absorbance (blank), while A<sub>s</sub> denotes the absorbance of the supernatant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p id="Par34">The protocol provided by Roche Diagnostic GmbH (Germany) was followed to extract total RNA from bacterial pellets. Using absorbance measurements with samples having a 260/280 nm ratio in the 1.8–2.8 range, the RNA yield and purity were evaluated. Following the directions given by the supplier of the kit (Thermo-Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), the cDNA synthesis was carried out. To determine gene transcript levels using the oligonucleotides listed in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, a qRT-PCR was performed using a Rotor-Gene Q apparatus (Qiagen, USA). The 16 S rRNA gene, serving as a housekeeping gene, underwent 30 cycles consisting of denaturation at 94 °C for 30 s, annealing at 60 °C for 30 s, extension at 72 °C for 30 s, followed by a final extension at 72 °C for 5 min. The cycling parameters were established at 94 °C for a duration of 3 min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Expression data were obtained from three independent biological replicates (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3), each measured in triplicate (technical replicates). 16 S rRNA was validated as a stable housekeeping gene under the tested conditions and used for normalization. Relative expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> were calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method.</p><p id="Par35">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Primer sequence involved in real-time PCR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primer name</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primer sequence</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amplicon size (bp)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Efficiency (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 S rRNA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>F: 5’-TAGTCCATGCCGTAAACGATGT-3’</p><p>R: 5’-TTGAGTTTTAGTCTTGCGACCG-3’</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>F: 5’-CCACACAACCCTATTTACTCGC-3’</p><p>R: 5’- GGCGGTTTTGAAAAATCTACGG − 3’</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Molecular Docking</title><p id="Par36">Molecular docking research were carried out using the Molecular Operating Environment (MOE, 2019.0102). The MMFF94x force field was used to automatically calculate the partial charges once all MOE minimizations were completed up to a gradient of 0.05 kcal mol − 1 Å−1. The protein chains that were going to be used in the molecular docking simulations were prepared for them by removing all residues and adding polar hydrogens using the protonate 3D procedure in MOE with its default parameters. This created protonation states that worked well in the simulations. In order to construct docking poses, the Triangle Matcher placement method and the London-dG scoring function were employed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Anti-persister assay</title><p id="Par37">The persister assay was conducted as previously outlined, with minor modifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Biphasic time-kill curves under antibiotic stress were first determined by challenging the isolates A1, A3, A7, and A8 (initial inoculum size of OD600 = 0.5) with meropenem at concentrations of 5X MIC over an 8-h incubation period. For the persister assay, cells were grown to exponential phase (OD600 = 0.5), and 1 mL of the culture was exposed to meropenem (5X MIC) at 37 °C. After incubation with shaking at 185 rpm for 4 h, the samples were washed twice with PBS and subsequently distributed on LB agar using serial dilution. The colony-forming unit (CFU) for surviving persister populations was ascertained. The harvested persister cells were re-grown in LB broth overnight and then treated with 5X meropenem, as mentioned earlier. This cycle was reiterated thrice. To confirm that the surviving colonies were persister cells, one colony was re-inoculated into new LB broth and tested for antibiotic sensitivity to ensure that the MIC was not altered. The impact of STX (both free form and niosomes) on persister cells formation was assessed by applying 5X MIC of STX treatments in late exponential phase bacterial cultures in presence of meropenem (0.5 MIC). After, a 6-h incubation period, the CFU for surviving persister populations was enumerated, and survival rates after treatments were determined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">To test the efficacy of STX in accelerating cell death of pre-formed persister cells, STX (5X MIC) was added to <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> late exponential phase cells treated with 5X MIC meropenem for 6 h. The survival rate of pre-formed persister cells was examined after STX treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Respiratory infection model</title><p id="Par39">This study employed a total of 24 male Swiss albino mice weighing an average of 25 g, obtained from the Faculty of Pharmacy at Tanta University. We obtained an informed consent from Faculty of Pharmacy at Tanta University to use the animals, and the Research Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Pharmacy at Tanta University (approval code, TP/RE/6/25 p-002) approved this study and the procedures in accordance with ARRIVE guidelines. Mice were given unfettered access to water and a regular pellet diet. In order to produce transitory neutropenia in mice, cyclophosphamide (300 mg/kg body weight) was injected intraperitoneally at days − 4 and − 1 before infection, after a one-week adaption period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Thiopental was administered via intraperitoneal injection at a volume of 0.08–0.1 mL, corresponding to a dosage of 40 mg/kg body weight. After light anesthesia, intranasal administration of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (final concentration of 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL in sterile PBS) established a respiratory infection. Animals were then categorized into four separate groups. Group I functioned as a negative control: uninfected and untreated. Group II functioned as a positive control, undergoing infection without intervention. Group III: infected and administered STX pigment dissolved in 1% DMSO at 6 h post infection. Group IV: infected and administered the STX niosomal formulation at 6 h post infection. Over the course of 7 days, survival rates, clinical symptoms, and disease progression were monitored. From 0 to 3, the subsequent clinical indications were assessed: Healthy, normal mice at the 0th stage. There was a significant noise response and motility in Stage (1) Weight loss, whiter ears, and moderate noise and motility reaction are all evidence of Stage (2) In the third stage, death and cyanosis occurred, concomitant with minor disturbance response and movement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Bacteriological and histopathological examination</title><p id="Par40">Lung tissues were aseptically collected for further analysis following the euthanasia (by cervical dislocation under light anesthesia) of three randomly selected animals from each group 48 h post-infection. A tissue homogenizer was employed to weigh and homogenize the right lungs in sterile PBS. Lung homogenates were diluted and subsequently plated onto LB agar to quantify the viable bacterial count. In contrast, 10% neutral buffered formalin was utilized to preserve the excised left lungs. Hematoxylin-eosin (H&amp;E) staining was utilized on the paraffin-embedded tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. A grading system was implemented to compare the lesions in the untreated and treated groups of mice, taking into consideration the most prominent observable aspects of the lungs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par41">GraphPad Prism version 5 was employed to conduct the statistical analysis. Data were given as mean ± SD, with significance considered at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. To compare more than two groups, ANOVA test was employed, and pairwise comparisons were made using the Tukey’s post hoc test. Student’s t-test was performed to compare the two groups.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec29"><title>Bacterial isolated and antibiotic susceptibility</title><p id="Par42">The isolation of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains revealed that the highest frequencies were found in endotracheal fluids (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9, 30%), sputum (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, 27%), and wound samples (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7, 23.3%). In contrast, urine samples (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4, 13.3%) and blood samples (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2, 6.6%) exhibited relatively lower frequencies. The respiratory tract emerges as the predominant site for infection by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, exhibiting an isolation frequency exceeding 50%, with contributions of 30% from endotracheal fluid and 27% from sputum. A panel of sixteen antibiotics spanning nine distinct categories were employed to assess the antibiotic susceptibility of the identified isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). According to Magiorakos et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], the majority of the isolates exhibited multi-drug resistance (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24, 80%), with at least one agent demonstrating resistance across at least three distinct categories. It is important to highlight that all isolates exhibit sensitivity to colistin, with the CLSI breakpoint for colistin resistance set at 2 µg/mL.<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Antibiotic susceptibility profile of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates utilized in the present investigation.Bacteria were categorized as sensitive (white box), intermediate (grey box), or resistant (black box) in accordance with CLSI criteria</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="MO1" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Tab3_HTML.jpg"/><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">A</italic> Aminoglycosides, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> Antipseudomonal carbapenems, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> Antipseudomonal fluoroquinolones, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> Antipseudomonal penicillins + β-lactamase inhibitors, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> Extended-spectrum cephalosporins, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic> Folate pathway inhibitors, <italic toggle="yes">G</italic> Penicillins + β-lactamase inhibitors, <italic toggle="yes">H</italic> Polymyxins, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> Tetracyclines</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Niosomal formulation exhibited acceptable nanoscale morphology, in vitro release, and stability profile</title><p id="Par43">The evaluation of the morphology, zeta potential, and particle size of the niosomal formulation was conducted using TEM and DLS. Representative TEM micrographs of the formulated niosomes are depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A. The micrographs depict spherical particles exhibiting diameters within the nanoscale range. The DLS measurement provided further validation of the vesicle size, confirming that it was within the nanoscale range, with an average size of 177.8 nm (supplementary material Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The polydispersity index value recorded at 0.383 suggests that the niosomes produced exhibited a uniform vesicle size. The findings revealed that the zeta potential of the synthesized niosomes is a notable negative value of −35.23 ± 1.26 (supplementary material Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), highlighting the robustness and stability of the niosomal vesicles. The encapsulation efficiency of STX within niosomal vesicles is documented at 92.7%. The assessment of drug loading involved quantifying the amount of drug encapsulated per gram of lipid. The results demonstrated that 185.4 mg of STX was integrated per gram of lipid in the formulation.</p><p id="Par44">The release profile of STX was observed to be affected by the cholesterol and surfactant content within the niosomes. The findings depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B demonstrated that the release of STX encapsulated in niosomal nanovesicles has a slower release than free solution. After 24 h, the niosomal vesicles exhibited a release percentage of 39.6 + 2.51%, in contrast to the free form (95.3 + 4.72%). Over a 30-day period, the stability of niosomes was evaluated under storage conditions of ambient temperature and refrigeration (4 °C). Our study’s findings demonstrated that niosomes kept in a refrigerator at 4 °C exhibited greater stability, with no discernible sedimentation or creaming over the storage period, and the niosomal suspension retained its initial particle size and EE%. On the other hand, the niosomes stored at the temperature of 25 °C showed comparable changes in their initial particle size (836.2 nm; supplementary material Fig. S2) and EE% (85.3%).</p><p id="Par45">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Characterization of the formulated niosomes. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative TEM micrographs of niosomes showing spherical vesicles within the nanoscale range. (<bold>B</bold>) The in-vitro release profile of STX at 37 °C in free form and niosomes (2 mL donor volume; sink conditions). Data was expressed as mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Killing activity and growth Inhibition</title><p id="Par46">Using the broth microdilution method, the antimicrobial activity of STX against isolates of MDR <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was investigated. The observed MIC values of the tested agents exhibited variability contingent upon the examined isolates. The findings presented in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> indicated that the MIC values ranged from 32 to 128 µg/mL, with a significant proportion of the isolates (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19, 80%) demonstrating a MIC value of 64 µg/mL. The encapsulation of STX within niosomes led to a significant decrease in the MIC values. The boost in efficiency was clearly observable across all isolates, with reductions ranging from 2 to 8 folds. There was no discernible growth when treated bacteria were sub-cultured on LB agar plates, suggesting that the tested agent has a bactericidal mode of action.<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Biofilm-forming capacities and STX susceptibility (free and niosomes) of MDR <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bacterial isolates</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Biofilm formation</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Free STX</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">STX-niosomes</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC (µg/mL)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBC (µg/mL)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIC (µg/mL)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBC (µg/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 19,606</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">SBP</italic> strong-biofilm producer, <italic toggle="yes">MBP</italic> moderate-biofilm producer, <italic toggle="yes">WBP</italic> weak-biofilm producer</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par47"><italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates experiencing strong biofilm production capacity (Table 4), as determined by the crystal violet method, were chosen to assess the efficacy of the tested agents against both planktonic cells and biofilm. Firstly, the growth of planktonic cells was challenged with different concentrations (0.25, 0.5, and 0.75 MIC). The dose-dependent growth inhibition was investigated by comparing the spectrophotometric OD values over a 12-h period. The growth curves demonstrate that STX at a concentration of 0.75 MIC substantially impeded the growth of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> planktonic cells under shaking conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Nevertheless, other concentrations exhibited minimal impact on the growth. Consequently, these concentrations may serve as an approach for regulating biofilm formation while preserving the viability of the planktonic cells. These findings indicated that STX’s antibiofilm activity was not a consequence of its killing activity, suggesting that it may be less vulnerable to the emergence of drug resilience.</p><p id="Par48">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Growth curve of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8) cultured with and without 0.75, 0.5, and 0.25 MICs of STX at 2-h intervals. The average of three sample replicates produced the results</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1312" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Staphyloxanthin impedes microbial adhesion and biofilm formation</title><p id="Par49">The formation of biofilms is profoundly influenced by cell surface hydrophobicity (CSH), which is a metric that estimates a cell’s affinity for hydrophobic environs. The cell adherence to hydrophobic substratum was evaluated by MATH assay. The findings illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A indicated that the untreated hydrophobic cells exhibit a heightened resemblance for non-polar solvent (toluene). Following treatment, the affinity of cells for the solvent diminished by 29.44–56.87% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), with the most notable enhancement occurring in the case of nanovesicles, which exhibited a substantial decrease in hydrophobicity indices of 65.75–76.8% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The impact on exopolysaccharide production, the key part of the biofilm matrix, was assessed using the phenol–sulfuric acid method. The dark red shade of the supernatant and the OD values showed that the untreated cells produced a significant amount of exopolysaccharide after incubation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B; supplementary material S3). Treatment with STX significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) reduced the production of exopolysaccharide by 43.2–59.5%, with the highest reduction observed in the case of the niosomal formulation (64.9–86.4%).</p><p id="Par50">Taking into the account the overall biofilm biomass, the crystal violet OD values of all examined isolates exhibiting associated biofilms experienced a significant reduction (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) of 43% to 58% upon treatment with STX solution. Administration of niosomal dispersion significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) enhanced the efficacy of STX, resulting in an attenuation of the biofilm formation by 68–88% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C; supplementary material S3). Considering the colonization of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> on the upper surfaces of stagnant media and biofilm creation at air-liquid interfaces, the inhibitory effect on pellicle and ring biofilm formation was evaluated. After a span of 24-h incubation, the liquid’s surface commenced to form a fine pellicle, and then a dense and opaque pellicle had completely covered the whole surface of the liquid by the close of the third day (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>H). Treatment with tested agents resulted in a significant reduction (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) of pellicle formation by 50–69% (STX) and 78–92% (niosomes), as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D. The findings revealed that STX (free and nanovesicles) markedly reduced the ring biofilm formation (crystal violet staining) in all tested <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates (supplementary material S3).</p><p id="Par51">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Effect on cellular adhesion and biofilm formation of strong biofilm producing <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. (<bold>A</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage of cell surface hydrophobicity after treatment. (<bold>B</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage of exopolysaccharide formation after treatment. (<bold>C</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage of biofilm biomass after treatment. (<bold>D</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage of pellicle formation after treatment. Statistical significance is denoted by the letters, at <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 (one-way ANOVA). Letter a indicates statistical significance compared to control. Letter b indicates statistical significance compared to treatment (free STX). Data expressed as mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1391" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Encapsulation of staphyloxanthin effectively disrupt the mature biofilm</title><p id="Par52">The potential efficacy of free STX and its formulation for biofilm disruption was evaluated against strong biofilm-producing isolates (Table 4). Concerning the total biofilm biomass, STX treatment of 48-h pre-established biofilm significantly decreased the total attached biomass, as indicated by crystal violet OD values, for all tested isolates, with reductions of 51% for the solution and 82% for the niosomes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). Regarding the viability of biofilm-adhered cells, the cell count (CFU/mL) was considerably (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) reduced by 55.66–61.5% after a 24-h treatment with STX solution. Encapsulation of STX within niosoma nanovesicles significantly enhanced efficacy and reduced the biofilm viability by 68–93% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). Furthermore, the notable decrease in mature biofilms was investigated and illustrated using a bright field microscope, as depicted in (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C).<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Encapsulation of STX effectively eliminated the 48-h mature biofilms produced by various <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. (<bold>A</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage of the total biomass of attached biofilm after treatment. (<bold>B</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage of the viability of biofilm-adhered cells after treatment. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative images the preformed biofilm under bright field microscope (×40) with and without treatment. Statistical significance is denoted by the letters, at <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 (one-way ANOVA). Letter a indicates statistical significance compared to control. Letter b indicates statistical significance compared to treatment (free STX). Data expressed as mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1435" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par53">The analysis of biofilms was further conducted through confocal microscopy to deepen the comprehension of the influence of STX (free and niosomes) on the structural elements of the biofilm. The fluorescence intensity indicated the percentage of LIVE/DEAD-stained cells with the biofilm matrix. Following 24 h of treatment, there was a notable decline in the viability of biofilm-embedded cells, with reductions of 56.8% (STX solution) and 79.1% (niosomes), as evidenced by the pronounced intensity of red fluorescence observed through propidium iodide staining (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Moreover, 3D-dimensional analysis indicated that the 48-h pre-established biofilm displayed a well-organized and substantial biofilm structure. Treatment administration for 24 h disturbed the preformed biofilm and significantly reduced (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) the biofilm’s thickness by 50% (STX solution) and 75% (niosomes), as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.</p><p id="Par54">.</p><p id="Par55">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>CLSM examination of the biofilm viability and thickness after and before STX encapsulation. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative images demonstrating the LIVE/DEAD-stained cells and 3D biofilm thickness with and without treatment. (<bold>B</bold>) Bar chart indicates fluorescence intensity represented in arbitrary units. (<bold>C</bold>) Bar chart indicates the 3D analysis of biofilm biomass thickness. Statistical significance is denoted by the asterisks, at <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 (one-way ANOVA). Three distinct areas of the preformed biofilm were used to measure the fluorescence intensity and biofilm thickness (z-stack)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1470" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Virulence attenuation after staphyloxanthin treatment</title><p id="Par56">The impact of STX (free and niosomes) on the virulence determinants of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates, including surface-associated motility, twitching motility, and iron acquisition activity, was evaluated. Using a semi-solid medium (0.5% MHA), an anti-surface motility assessment was carried out. The bacterial cells were treated with the STX solution at a sub-growth-inhibitory concentration (1/2 MIC), resulting in a notable decrease in surface motility of up to 47.29–63.07% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The encasement within niosomal nanovesicles demonstrated markedly improved performance compared to the free solution, exhibiting a reduction in surface motility of up to 66.66 to 94.45% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>; supplementary material S4). The twitching motility was evaluated utilizing a semi-solid medium (1% MHA). Following crystal violet staining, the dispersion from the inoculation site (toothpick stabbing) was notably reduced (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) by 27.02–56.75% with the application of STX solution. The results illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B indicated that the boosted diminution of dispersion (72.97–91.89%) is associated with the administration of niosomes.</p><p id="Par57">It is worth noting that <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is able to adjust to an iron deficiency by producing and secreting siderophores, which are iron chelators. Therefore, a sub-growth-inhibitory concentration (1/2 MIC) of STX was evaluated for siderophore inhibition. After the addition of the CAS-HDTMA solution, the untreated cells exhibited a notable production of siderophores, as evidenced by the recorded OD values and the appearance of a pinkish-red color, a hallmark for the production of hydroxamate-type siderophores (supplementary material S4). The results displayed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C revealed that the percentage of siderophore units was significantly reduced (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) after treatment by 26.68–44.06% (STX solution) and 48.75–79.5% (niosomes).</p><p id="Par58">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Attenuation of the virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates following treatment. (<bold>A</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage in swarming motility. (<bold>B</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage in twitching motility. (<bold>C</bold>) Bar chart indicates the reduction percentage in siderophore units. Statistical significance is denoted by the letters, at <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 (one-way ANOVA). Letter a indicates statistical significance compared to control. Letter b indicates statistical significance compared to treatment (free STX). Data expressed as mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1530" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Impact of staphyloxanthin on quorum sensing attentuation</title><p id="Par59">In <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene is a prerequisite for the two-component AbaI/AbaR quorum sensing system. Hence, qRT-PCR was employed to examine the effect of STX on the quorum sensing in the tested <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates by assessing the expression levels of the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene after STX treatment at a concentration of 0.5 MIC. The results displayed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> indicated that the expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene were significantly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) by different extents in all examined isolates after STX treatment, with reduction percentages of 20.3%−68.5% (free STX) and 48%−79% (niosomes).<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The impact of STX treatments (free and niosomes) on gene expression level of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>. Statistical significance is denoted by the letters, at <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 (one-way ANOVA). Letter a indicates statistical significance compared to control. Letter b indicates statistical significance compared to treatment (free STX). Data expressed as mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1574" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par60">The interaction between STX and the autoinducer synthase enzyme (AbaI protein) was subsequently examined to gain deeper insights into the plausible mechanism through which STX exerts its anti-quorum sensing activity. A molecular docking study was conducted using the “molecular operating environment (MOE) version 2019.0102” to elucidate the binding modes of the purified STX pigment with the the crystal structure of AbaI protein (PDB code: 1KZF). The results indicated that STX exhibited a significant docking score (−9.4302 kcal/mol) and was appropriately positioned within the active site of the AbaI protein. STX established a strong complex with the AgrA protein’s through hydrogen bonding interaction with Arg31 amino acid, as depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>. The docking analysis was elaborated upon to explore the binding modalities between STX and AbaR (AlphaFold DB model; UniProtKB: A0A013UP), a receptor protein for N-acyl-homoserine lactones (AHL). The results illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> indicated that STX was oriented effectively, forming a strong binding score (−8.9635 kcal/mol) through hydrogen bonding interaction with Lys51 within the active site of the AbaR protein. Ultimately, our findings suggested that STX may serve as a quorum sensing inhibitor through binding and interacting with the two-component AbaI/AbaR system, thereby inhibiting the expression of quorum sensing genes and other genes regulated by quorum sensing associated with virulence factors such as motility and biofilm formation.</p><p id="Par61">
<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Molecular docking analysis demonstrating the docking and minimization of the STX residue in the binding pocket of quorum sensing proteins in both 2D and 3D. (<bold>A</bold>) AbaI (PDB code: 1KZF) and (<bold>B</bold>) AbaR (AlphaFold DB model; UniProtKB: A0A013UP)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1598" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec36"><title>Staphyloxanthin nanovesicles effectively eradicate the meropenem-induced persistence</title><p id="Par62">In the late exponential phase, bacterial cultures exhibited the formation of persister cells when confronted with meropenem stress at a concentration of 5X MIC for the tested <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates A1 (MIC = 8 µg/mL), A2 (MIC = 8 µg/mL), A7 (MIC = 16 µg/mL), and A8 (MIC = 16 µg/mL). After 24-h incubation, the time-dependent assay demonstrated that the maximum persister rates were 0.92% for isolate A3 and 0.58% for isolate A7, while the minimum levels were 0.089% for isolate A1 and 0.008% for isolate A8. This pattern was characterized by a typical biphasic killing curve, showcasing an abrupt drop in vulnerable cells followed by a plateau representing the subpopulation of the surviving persisters. The inflection points of the plot were recorded following a 4-h exposure to 5X MIC of meropenem (supplementary material Fig. S5). The culture derived from persister cells exhibited the same sensitivity to meropenem as the parent culture, with no observed change in MIC.</p><p id="Par63">The impact of meropenem exposure in conjunction with STX treatments (both free and niosomal) on persister formation was examined. Upon exposure of the cells in the late exponential phase to free STX, the formation of persister cells was significantly reduced by 28.4 ± 2.1% (A7), 32.4 ± 2.1% (A3), 44.44 ± 1% (A8), and 51.72 ± 3% (A1). The results displyed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>A indicated that he combination of the niosomal formulation of STX with 5X meropenem was the most effective (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in reducing the survival rates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> persistence compared to the free form of STX. In addition, the persister cells that survived were collected after 6 h, which was adequate for obtaining persister cells according to time-dependent assays, and were subsequently tested for STX eradication. The death rate of the pre-formed persister cells was accelerated after STX treatment by 23.5–48.2% in the all examined <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. Intriguingly, no persister cells were detected when STX niosomal nanovesicle was applied in case of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> A1 and A8, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>B.</p><p id="Par64">
<fig id="Fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Effect of STX treatments on meropenem persistence against late exponential phase cells of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. (<bold>A</bold>) Survival rates of persister cells formation after exposure of meropenem (5X MIC) in conjunction with STX treatments for 6 h. (<bold>B</bold>) Survival rates of the pre-formed persister cells after treatments with STX (free and niosomes) for 6 h (ND = not detected). Statistical significance is denoted by the asterisks, at * <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05, ** <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.01, *** <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.001 (one-way ANOVA). Data expressed as mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1659" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig9_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec37"><title>In vivo assessment of the therapeutic efficacy of staphyloxanthin formulation</title><p id="Par65">In the current study, we established a respiratory infection model to evaluate the therapeutic efficacy of STX (free and niosomes) in vivo. Consequently, we challenged different groups of neutropenic mice with <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> A8 isolate (final inoculum size of 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mouse). The groups that received treatment (both free STX and niosomes) exhibited a markedly enhanced resistance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) to <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> A8 respiratory infection, as evidenced by the clinical manifestations observed in the mice. Throughout the period of the observation, the animals administered the free-STX treatment displayed stage 2 clinical manifestations, as evidenced by the findings illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A (moderate sensitivity to auditory stimuli and alterations in motility, a paler appearance than previously noted, along with a slight reduction in weight). Fortunately, there was a significant improvement in clinical symptoms (reduced weight loss and normal ear color, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the group that received the niosomal formulation of STX, as evaluated by a lower clinical signs score (&gt; 1). In contrast, the respiratory infection induced by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> A8 resulted in a marked deterioration of the clinical signs noted in the untreated group, culminating in an exacerbation of the disease progression to a deadly outcome (stage 3, characterized by cyanosis and mortality; Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A).</p><p id="Par66">The results from the Kaplan-Meier survival curve (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>B) corroborated these observations. At the conclusion of the seven-day monitoring period, the treatment with STX (free and niosomes) had successfully rescued the entire treated mice. The survival rate of the untreated group, in contrast, was markedly diminished at 80% by the day four of the experiment, and this decline persisted, ultimately reaching 40% by days six and seven (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>B). The enhanced clinical outcomes and boosted survival rates stated substantiate the curative potential of STX in vivo in combating the induced lethal infection of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. The killing capacity of STX was further evaluated through an evaluation of the bacterial load in lung homogenates. In the untreated group, the lung samples showed a bacterial burden of 7.9 ± 0.1 (mean log (CFU/g)) after 48 h of inoculation. Mice receiving STX solution showed a significant reduction (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) of bacterial counts to 4.027 ± 0.5021 log units. The best improvement in lowering bacterial load (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) was observed in case of administration of niosomal nanovesicles (2.533 ± 0.3215 log units), as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>C.</p><p id="Par67">
<fig id="Fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>In vivo therapeutic efficacy of STX (free and niosomes) against respiratory infection of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> A8. (<bold>A</bold>) Bar chart demonstrating the average illness score during the infection study. (<bold>B</bold>) Kaplan-Meier survival curve demonstrating the mortality rate of mice before and after treatment. (<bold>C</bold>) Bar chart demonstrating the bacterial burden in lung homogenates of mice before and after treatment. Statistical significance is denoted by the asterisks, at * <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05, ** <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.01, *** <italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.001 (one-way ANOVA). Data expressed as mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1744" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig10_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec38"><title>Niosomal formulation of staphyloxanthin alleviates pulmonary destruction and inflammation triggered by lung infection</title><p id="Par68">The efficacy of STX (free and niosomes) in protecting the lungs from a deadly respiratory infection was assessed by histologically examining the lung tissues to identify pathological alterations. As expected, the normal control’s H&amp;E-stained lung tissues showed no structural damage or inflammation, along with appropriately sized alveoli and bronchioles (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>A). The untreated infected group displayed patches of destructed emphysematous alveoli and extensive congested surrounding blood vessels, which were clear signs of inflammation. There was extensive bronchial and interstitial inflammation in the pulmonary alveoli. Furthermore, inflammatory cell infiltration was observed, primarily consisting of macrophages with a limited count of neutrophils (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>B-D). The infected group treated with STX solution exhibited histopathological findings of multifocal interstitial inflammation primarily consisting of macrophages, alongside mild peribronchial inflammation, characterized by spots of mild congestion and alveolar emphysema (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>E&amp;F). Encapsulation of STX within nanovesicles, on the other hand, showed matured granulation tissue that was well-formed, enriched with freshly generated capillaries, and showed elevated fibroblast recruitment. Additionally, lung tissue displayed moderate fibrosis, an average-sized bronchiole with minimal inflammation, and alveoli of average size connected by thick fibrous septa (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>G&amp;H).<fig id="Fig11" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Histopathological findings of H&amp;E-stained lung tissue sections of infected mice and treated with different treatments after 6 h of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> A8 inoculation. (<bold>A</bold>; 100x) photomicrographs of lungs sections from normal control group (GI) showing no structural damage and inflammation with normal bronchiole surrounded by normal sized alveoli. (<bold>B</bold>; 100x), (<bold>C</bold>; 400x) and (<bold>D</bold>; 400x) photomicrographs of lungs sections from infected untreated group (GII) showing interstitial inflammation (black arrows) and perivascular inflammation (blue arrow) separated by congested alveoli (red arrows) with areas of destructed emphysematous alveoli (*). (<bold>E</bold>; 100x) and (<bold>F</bold>; 400x) photomicrographs of STX-treated group (GIII) lungs sections showing multifocal interstitial inflammation mainly macrophages (black arrows), mild peribronchial inflammation (blue arrow), areas of mild congestion (red arrow) and mild alveolar emphysema (*). (<bold>G</bold>; 100x) and (<bold>H</bold>; 400x) photomicrographs of niosomes-treated group (GIV) lungs sections showing weak interstitial inflammation (black arrows)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1797" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_Fig11_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par69">Semi-quantitative histological metrics ranging from minimal-to-widespread appearance were also used to evaluate the effectiveness of STX and indicate the severity of the pathological findings. It was demonstrated that mice treated with STX formulation exhibited improved histology scores over the untreated group (GI) and the group treated with unencapsulated STX. Results in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> unequivocally indicated that STX treatment reduced the bacterial infection-induced congestion and degradation of the alveoli, as well as the inflammation of the interstitial and bronchial tissues in the lungs.</p><p id="Par70">
<table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Semi-quantitative assessment of histological parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Histological parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Infected group</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">STX-treated group</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Niosomes-treated group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alveolar congestion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inflammation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fibroblasts proliferation (fibrosis)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Emphysema</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Angiogenesis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Granulation tissue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Collagen deposition</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Absence -, Mild +, Moderate ++, Severe +++, Widespread ++++</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec39"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par71">
<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is an opportunistic pathogen of considerable healthcare magnitude, held accountable for various resilient nosocomial infections globally, especially in patients with serious illnesses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is a highly concerning bacterium that conveys noteworthy health threats owing to the scarcity of effective treatment options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Consequently, exploring innovative strategies for their management is a necessity for minimizing elevated mortality rates stemming from therapeutic inadequacies. The astounding biological and antimicrobial attributes of natural pigments such as carotenoids and apocarotenoids render them fascinating candidates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. However, the potential efficacy of carotenoids may be hindered by poor solubility and bioavailability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. To overcome this challenge, a novel approach through the delivery of STX in the form of nanovesicles was formulated for augmenting the therapeutic efficacy as a promising antibacterial agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par72">This was accomplished through the encapsulation of STX within niosomes for enhanced therapeutic efficacy in combating <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> planktonic cells and biofilms. Niosomes, which are vesicular carriers composed of cholesterol and non-ionic surfactants, encapsulated STX, thereby facilitating its attainment of the intended effect. The encapsulation of hydrophilic and lipophilic medications utilizing niosomes is indeed achievable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The intriguing possibility of niosomes to enhance biological activity in the realm of pathogen defense warrants deeper exploration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. It was suggested that these carriers could improve the drug’s ability to penetrate the pathogen membrane, demonstrate an enhanced antibacterial effect, and minimize its detrimental impact on healthy cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The data provided strong support for our decision to utilize niosomes as the delivery mechanism. This study primarily involved the administration of cholesterol through niosomes produced with span 60 serving as the main surfactant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Drug retention and entrapment may be enhanced by adding cholesterol as a stabilizing factor to the membrane. The prepared vesicles displayed a spherical morphology, as expected. The measured dimensions of the vesicles varied between 100 and 200 nm within the nanoscale range. The reported data exhibits a consensus regarding both morphology and size values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. It is essential to emphasize that the properties of the drug and the particular category of lipid are fundamental factors influencing the efficacy of drug entrapment, especially concerning lipophilic drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The recorded drug loading and entrapment efficiency is underscored by evidence indicating that STX, due to its lipophilic nature, predominantly resides within the lipid core of the vesicle. The observed entrapment efficiency and release profile align with the values reported by other researchers, indicating they fall within the appropriate range [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].</p><p id="Par73">This report represents, to our knowledge, the first examination of the impact of STX in the fight against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. This involved a thorough analysis of the effects of free and niosomes-encapsulated STX on planktonic cells and biofilms. Our study indicates that STX exhibited significant antibacterial activity against all tested <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates, as evidenced by the recorded MIC values (Table 4). The notable antibacterial efficacy of STX can be fundamentally attributed to its inherent chemical composition of carotenoids. In summary, the biological potential of carotenoids is largely linked to their role in generating reactive oxygen species, which subsequently leads to oxidative stress and modifications in cell permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. One plausible mechanism by which pro-oxidative features increase antibacterial potential was proposed by Black et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. This mechanism entails disrupting with the pathogens’ ability to generate energy, bind to their membrane glycoprotein, and decouple oxidative phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Moreover, the antibacterial activity was increased by niosomal encapsulation of STX, as evidenced by a lower MIC when compared to the comparable STX solution (Table 4). The tendency of vesicular systems to adsorb to the bacterial cell membrane has been the central theme of numerous studies elucidating the mechanism behind enhanced antibacterial efficacy following encapsulation within niosomes as vesicular carriers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Fusion of vesicles to the bacterial surface was proposed in other reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The adsorption or fusion process can render the bacterial cell wall more permeable, facilitating an increased influx of medication into the bacterial cells. Even in biofilm-forming bacteria, it is thought that these effects reduce bacterial resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. The documented findings observed across various bacterial strains are consistent with the magnitude of enhancement in antibacterial activity complying with niosomal encapsulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Consistent with our research, the co-delivery of curcuminrosemary loaded niosomes showed higher antimicrobial activity with lower MIC values and successfully inhibited the growth of the pathogenic bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Another recent study reported that niosomes encapsulating carvacrol displayed up to 4-fold higher antibacterial activity against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, compared to free drug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>].</p><p id="Par74">In addition to its effects on planktonic cells, STX demonstrated notable efficacy in inhibiting biofilm formation as well as disrupting pre-established biofilms. Biofilm production is regarded as one of the most critical virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. The process of biofilm formation commences with the adhesion of microbes to abiotic and biotic surfaces, such as endotracheal tubes and medically relevant surfaces. After the initial adhesion, bacteria will proliferate and aggregate to form microcolonies. The completely formed biofilm undergoes maturation and maintenance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. This investigation revealed that STX successfully inhibited biofilm formation at multiple stages, including initial adhesion (cell surface hydrophobicity), biofilm matrix (exopolysaccharide and crystal violet assay), and mature biofilm (light and confocal microscopy), especially in the context of niosomal encapsulation. The encouraging potential of niosome-encapsulated natural products in the management of biofilm-forming bacteria has been demonstrated in a multitude of research studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Our study aligns with recent research reporting the potential efficacy of β-carotene extracted from <italic toggle="yes">Azanza garckeana</italic> in combating respiratory infections caused by <italic toggle="yes">A.</italic> baumannii and other ESKAPE pathogens by inhibiting biofilm formation and eradicating mature biofilms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].</p><p id="Par75">An intriguing approach for attenuating the pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> involves targeting the quorum sensing network. The two-component AbaI/AbaR system, a homologue of the LuxI/LuxR system seen in other Gram-negative bacteria, comprises up <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>’s quorum sensing system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. The enzyme autoinducer synthase, known as AbaI, is encoded by the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene, which plays a crucial role in the synthesis of N-acyl-homoserine lactone (AHL). With the accumulation of AHL, the receptor protein AbaR, encoded by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, initiates a series of reactions that subsequently modify the expression of various genes regulated by quorum sensing. This includes genes associated with virulence factors such as biofilm formation, motility, and iron acquisition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Blocking the expression of the autoinducer synthase encoding gene (<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>) leads to quorum quenching and downregulation of virulence genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Our investigation revealed that STX effectively suppressed the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene across all examined <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates. The quorum quenching activity of STX has been proven through an observed attenuation in bacterial motility and siderophore production at sub-inhibitory concentrations, preserving the viability. Additionally, the computational analysis revealed the anti-quorum sensing activity of STX through binding with the two-component proteins (AbaI and AbaR) of the quorum sensing system. Consistent with our research, the ethanolic extract of <italic toggle="yes">Azadirachta indica</italic> showed its potent quorum quenching activity by downregulating the expression of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene, which subsequently leading to a decrease in the motility and iron acquisition of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Additionally, Pumirat et al. observed that <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> mutations showed notable changes in protein expression, particularly in proteins associated with virulence, antibiotic resistance, and membrane structure, between mutant and wild-type strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].</p><p id="Par76">Nevertheless, high persister emergence rates in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> under antibiotic stress have been documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. A subpopulation of bacteria termed persister cells demonstrates resilience to antibiotic treatment, potentially leading to therapeutic failure and recurrence, particularly in recalcitrance of chronic infections, upon cessation of antibiotic pressure. The eradication of persisters is crucial for managing antibiotic tolerance and for developing new strategies to enhance treatment efficacy and reduce patient stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. This study demonstrates that the encapsulation of STX within niosomal nanovesicles significantly inhibited the formation of persisters in the presence of meropenem and effectively eradicated the pre-formed persistence. Our study aligns with previous research indicating that thymol was utilized either alone or in conjunction with meropenem for anti-persister activity against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Another instance is curcumin, which reinstated the sensitivity of colistin-persisted <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> owing to its pro-oxidant properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par77">To further confirm the efficacy of STX against <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infection, we evaluated the impact of STX on respiratory infections induced by antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates, which are frequently identified in immunocompromised patients with pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Upon elaboration, we observed a statistically significant improvement in clinical outcomes among the treated groups, evidenced by higher survival rates, reduced bacterial burden, and decreased inflammation in lung tissues. Our study aligns with another report indicating that intranasal administration of <italic toggle="yes">Scutellaria barbata</italic> extract resulted in 100% survival of infected mice with <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and demonstrated improved resolution of alveolar, peribronchial, and perivascular inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. However, to date, there is no published data reporting the antivirulence and antibiofilm potentials of STX in either drug solution or niosomal dispersion.</p></sec><sec id="Sec40"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par78">Encapsulation of STX in niosomal nanovesicles presents a novel anti-virulence strategy against multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, effectively disrupting quorum sensing and the survival of persister cells. The in vivo efficacy underscores clinical promise; however, comprehensive safety studies, delivery optimization, and validation in advanced preclinical models are required before translation into clinical application.</p></sec><sec id="Sec41" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12866_2025_4507_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to the study conception and design. Material preparation, data collection and analysis were performed by A. N. The first draft of the manuscript was written by A. N. and all authors commented on previous versions of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB). The authors affirm that no financial resources, grants, or additional assistance were obtained in the course of preparing this manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All the data supporting the research results are available in this the article.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par79">We obtained an informed consent from Faculty of Pharmacy at Tanta University to use the animals, and the Research Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Pharmacy at Tanta University (approval code, TP/RE/6/25 p-002) approved the care and use of animals in this study and the procedures in accordance with ARRIVE guidelines. This study is devoid of any involvement with human participants, human data, or human tissue. The clinical isolates were sourced from microbiological laboratories within the Tanta University hospitals, ensuring no access to patient data or personal contact with patients, and we obtained them as unnamed bacteria on agar media. Therefore, humans did not directly participate, and obtaining informed consent to participate was waived for this study by the ethics committee of the Faculty of Pharmacy at Tanta University. However, our study complies with Helsinki’s Ethical Principles for Medical Research.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par80">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuatzin-Flores</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chávez-Bravo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, a multidrug-resistant opportunistic pathogen in new habitats: a systematic review</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>644</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12040644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38674589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11051781</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Ahuatzin-Flores OE, Torres E, Chávez-Bravo E. <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, a multidrug-resistant opportunistic pathogen in new habitats: a systematic review. Microorganisms. 2024;12(4):644.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38674589</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/microorganisms12040644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11051781</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rangel K, De-Simone S. <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii-</italic>the rise of a resistant pathogen: the rise of a resistant pathogen. BoD–Books on Demand; 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unveiling the secrets of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: resistance, current treatments, and future innovations</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>6814</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25136814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38999924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11241693</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Marino A, et al. Unveiling the secrets of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: resistance, current treatments, and future innovations. Int J Mol Sci. 2024;25(13):6814.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38999924</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms25136814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11241693</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiofilm and antivirulence efficacy of myrtenol enhances the antibiotic susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21975</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-79128-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33319862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7738676</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Selvaraj A, et al. Antibiofilm and antivirulence efficacy of myrtenol enhances the antibiotic susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Sci Rep. 2020;10(1):21975.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33319862</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-020-79128-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7738676</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gedefie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilm formation and its role in disease pathogenesis: a review</article-title><source>Infect Drug Resist</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S332051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34531666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8439624</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Gedefie A, et al. <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilm formation and its role in disease pathogenesis: a review. Infect Drug Resist. 2021. 10.2147/IDR.S332051.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34531666</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/IDR.S332051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8439624</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Convergence of biofilm formation and antibiotic resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infection</article-title><source>Front Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>793615</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.793615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8987773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402433</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Roy S, et al. Convergence of biofilm formation and antibiotic resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infection. Front Med. 2022;9:793615.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2022.793615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8987773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402433</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almatroudi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biofilm resilience: molecular mechanisms driving antibiotic resistance in clinical contexts</article-title><source>Biology</source><year>2025</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>165</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology14020165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40001933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11852148</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Almatroudi A. Biofilm resilience: molecular mechanisms driving antibiotic resistance in clinical contexts. Biology. 2025;14(2):165.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40001933</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biology14020165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11852148</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deciphering meropenem persistence in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> facilitates discovery of anti-persister activity of thymol</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2025</year><volume>69</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e01381</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aac.01381-24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39976427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11963602</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Hussain A, et al. Deciphering meropenem persistence in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> facilitates discovery of anti-persister activity of thymol. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2025;69(4):e01381–24.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39976427</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/aac.01381-24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11963602</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barretto</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vootla</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro anticancer activity of Staphyloxanthin pigment extracted from <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus gallinarum</italic> KX912244, a gut microbe of <italic toggle="yes">Bombyx mori</italic></article-title><source>Indian J Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>58</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12088-018-0718-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29651173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5891481</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Barretto DA, Vootla SK. In vitro anticancer activity of Staphyloxanthin pigment extracted from <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus gallinarum</italic> KX912244, a gut microbe of <italic toggle="yes">Bombyx mori</italic>. Indian J Microbiol. 2018;58(2):146–58.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29651173</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12088-018-0718-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5891481</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Citrus carotenoid extracts promote ROS accumulation and induce oxidative stress to exert anti-proliferative and pro-apoptotic effects in MDA-MB-231 cells</article-title><source>Antioxidants</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox13030264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38539798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10967589</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Wei J, et al. Citrus carotenoid extracts promote ROS accumulation and induce oxidative stress to exert anti-proliferative and pro-apoptotic effects in MDA-MB-231 cells. Antioxidants. 2024;13(3):264.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38539798</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox13030264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10967589</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation and identification of carotenoid-producing yeast and evaluation of antimalarial activity of the extracted carotenoid (s) against <italic toggle="yes">P. falciparum</italic></article-title><source>Biol Futura</source><year>2021</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42977-021-00081-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34554551</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Sinha S, et al. Isolation and identification of carotenoid-producing yeast and evaluation of antimalarial activity of the extracted carotenoid (s) against <italic toggle="yes">P. falciparum</italic>. Biol Futura. 2021;72:325–37.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s42977-021-00081-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34554551</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The protective role of carotenoids in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title><source>J Funct Foods</source><year>2025</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>106685</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2025.106685</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Sui J, et al. The protective role of carotenoids in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies. J Funct Foods. 2025;125:106685.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Advances in carotenoid based delivery systems for alleviating inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Food Rev Int</source><year>2024</year><volume>40</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2427</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/87559129.2023.2273928</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Zhang Y, et al. Advances in carotenoid based delivery systems for alleviating inflammatory bowel disease. Food Rev Int. 2024;40(9):2427–47.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manzari-Tavakoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrating natural compounds and nanoparticle‐based drug delivery systems: a novel strategy for enhanced efficacy and selectivity in cancer therapy</article-title><source>Cancer Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e7010</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cam4.7010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38491817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10943377</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Manzari-Tavakoli A, et al. Integrating natural compounds and nanoparticle‐based drug delivery systems: a novel strategy for enhanced efficacy and selectivity in cancer therapy. Cancer Med. 2024;13(5):e7010.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38491817</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cam4.7010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10943377</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formulation and characterization of BBR loaded niosomes using saponin as a nonionic biosurfactant investigating synergistic effects to enhance antibacterial activity</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5231</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-87950-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39939626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11822194</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Shiri S, et al. Formulation and characterization of BBR loaded niosomes using saponin as a nonionic biosurfactant investigating synergistic effects to enhance antibacterial activity. Sci Rep. 2025;15(1):5231.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39939626</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-025-87950-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11822194</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abo Kamer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surfactant nanovesicles for augmented antibacterial activity against carbapenemase resistant Enterobacteriaceae and extended spectrum beta-lactamases producing bacteria: in vitro and in vivo evaluation</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>73</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-023-02812-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36927445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10018850</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Abo Kamer AM, et al. Surfactant nanovesicles for augmented antibacterial activity against carbapenemase resistant Enterobacteriaceae and extended spectrum beta-lactamases producing bacteria: in vitro and in vivo evaluation. BMC Microbiol. 2023;23(1):73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36927445</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12866-023-02812-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10018850</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nosair AM, Abdelaziz AA, Abo-Kamer AM et al. Nutritional optimization for bioprocess production of Staphyloxanthin from <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> with response surface methodology: promising anticancer scaffold targeting EGFR Inhibition. Microb Cell Fact. 2025; 24 (1): 99.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12934-025-02717-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12054202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40329373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lal B et al. Specimen Collection, Processing, Culture, and Biochemical Identification of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter spp. Acinetobacter baumannii: Methods and Protocols</italic>. 2019: pp. 1–15.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-4939-9118-1_1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30798539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLSI performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing</article-title><source>CLSI Supplements M</source><year>2020</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Wayne P. CLSI performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing. CLSI Supplements M. 2020;100:20–30.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marei</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arafa</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Maghraby</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eudragit S100 coated surfactant vesicles for boosted oral bioavailability of Ticagrelor</article-title><source>J Drug Deliv Sci Technol</source><year>2024</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>106234</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jddst.2024.106234</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Marei HF, Arafa MF, El Maghraby GM. Eudragit S100 coated surfactant vesicles for boosted oral bioavailability of Ticagrelor. J Drug Deliv Sci Technol. 2024;101:106234.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preparation, characterization, and in vivo activity of <italic toggle="yes">Gossypium hirsutum</italic> niosomes against cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania major</italic> in a murine model: parasite burden, gene expression, and histopathological profiling</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>2024</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>108859</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2024.108859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39505195</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Sharifi I, et al. Preparation, characterization, and in vivo activity of <italic toggle="yes">Gossypium hirsutum</italic> niosomes against cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania major</italic> in a murine model: parasite burden, gene expression, and histopathological profiling. Exp Parasitol. 2024;267:108859.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39505195</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.exppara.2024.108859</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan coated nanostructured lipid carriers for enhanced in vivo efficacy of albendazole against <italic toggle="yes">Trichinella spiralis</italic></article-title><source>Carbohydr Polym</source><year>2020</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>115826</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2019.115826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31952620</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Eid RK, et al. Chitosan coated nanostructured lipid carriers for enhanced in vivo efficacy of albendazole against <italic toggle="yes">Trichinella spiralis</italic>. Carbohydr Polym. 2020;232:115826.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31952620</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.carbpol.2019.115826</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formulation, preparation of niosome loaded zinc oxide nanoparticles and biological activities</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16692</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-67509-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39030347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11271597</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Rezaei H, et al. Formulation, preparation of niosome loaded zinc oxide nanoparticles and biological activities. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):16692.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39030347</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-67509-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11271597</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morteza-Semnani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preparation and in-vitro evaluation of ketoconazole-loaded niosome (ketosome) for drug delivery to cutaneous candidiasis</article-title><source>Pharm Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.34172/PS.2022.34</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Morteza-Semnani K, et al. Preparation and in-vitro evaluation of ketoconazole-loaded niosome (ketosome) for drug delivery to cutaneous candidiasis. Pharm Sci. 2022;29(2):208–18.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Curcumin niosomes (curcusomes) as an alternative to conventional vehicles: a potential for efficient dermal delivery</article-title><source>J Drug Deliv Sci Technol</source><year>2020</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>102035</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jddst.2020.102035</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Akbari J, et al. Curcumin niosomes (curcusomes) as an alternative to conventional vehicles: a potential for efficient dermal delivery. J Drug Deliv Sci Technol. 2020;60:102035.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamer</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial, antibiofilm, and anti-quorum sensing activities of pyocyanin against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>: in vitro and in vivo study</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-023-02861-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37095436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10124065</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Kamer AMA, et al. Antibacterial, antibiofilm, and anti-quorum sensing activities of pyocyanin against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>: in vitro and in vivo study. BMC Microbiol. 2023;23(1):116.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37095436</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12866-023-02861-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10124065</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Madboly</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization and genomic analysis of novel bacteriophage NK20 to revert colistin resistance and combat pandrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> in a rat respiratory infection model</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>322</volume><fpage>121639</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2023.121639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37001805</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Al-Madboly LA, et al. Characterization and genomic analysis of novel bacteriophage NK20 to revert colistin resistance and combat pandrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> in a rat respiratory infection model. Life Sci. 2023;322:121639.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37001805</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lfs.2023.121639</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raorane</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiofilm and antivirulence efficacies of flavonoids and curcumin against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>990</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31134028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6517519</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Raorane CJ, et al. Antibiofilm and antivirulence efficacies of flavonoids and curcumin against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Front Microbiol. 2019;10:990.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31134028</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6517519</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elshaer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaldam</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaaban</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ketoprofen, piroxicam and indomethacin-suppressed quorum sensing and virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>133</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2182</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.15609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35503000</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Elshaer SL, Shaldam MA, Shaaban MI. Ketoprofen, piroxicam and indomethacin-suppressed quorum sensing and virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. J Appl Microbiol. 2022;133(4):2182–97.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35503000</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jam.15609</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muriana</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A microplate growth inhibition assay for screening bacteriocins against <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> to differentiate their mode-of-action</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1178</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom5021178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26111195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4496717</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Vijayakumar PP, Muriana PM. A microplate growth inhibition assay for screening bacteriocins against <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> to differentiate their mode-of-action. Biomolecules. 2015;5(2):1178–94.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26111195</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biom5021178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4496717</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganić</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cinnamon essential oil and its emulsion as efficient antibiofilm agents to combat <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>989667</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.989667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36299724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9589355</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Ganić T, et al. Cinnamon essential oil and its emulsion as efficient antibiofilm agents to combat <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:989667.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36299724</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2022.989667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9589355</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nait Chabane</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of pellicles formed by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> at the air-liquid interface</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e111660</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0111660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25360550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4216135</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Nait Chabane Y, et al. Characterisation of pellicles formed by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> at the air-liquid interface. PLoS One. 2014;9(10):e111660.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25360550</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0111660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4216135</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasath</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Palmitic acid inhibits the virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic>: biofilms, cell surface hydrophobicity, ergosterol biosynthesis, and enzymatic activity</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>864</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7226919</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Prasath KG, et al. Palmitic acid inhibits the virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic>: biofilms, cell surface hydrophobicity, ergosterol biosynthesis, and enzymatic activity. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:864.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457728</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7226919</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamer</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of newly isolated bacteriophage to control multi-drug resistant <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> colonizing incision wounds in a rat model: in vitro and in vivo approach</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>121085</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2022.121085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36265569</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Kamer AMA, et al. Characterization of newly isolated bacteriophage to control multi-drug resistant <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> colonizing incision wounds in a rat model: in vitro and in vivo approach. Life Sci. 2022;310:121085.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36265569</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lfs.2022.121085</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelaziz</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring the potential efficacy of phage therapy for biocontrol of foodborne pathogenic extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in Gastrointestinal tract of rat model</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>121362</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2022.121362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36610637</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Abdelaziz AA, et al. Exploring the potential efficacy of phage therapy for biocontrol of foodborne pathogenic extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in Gastrointestinal tract of rat model. Life Sci. 2023;315:121362.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36610637</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lfs.2022.121362</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly virulent and multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> sequence type 58 from a sausage in Germany</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1006</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11081006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35892394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9331442</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Eger E, et al. Highly virulent and multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> sequence type 58 from a sausage in Germany. Antibiotics. 2022;11(8):1006.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35892394</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics11081006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9331442</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>PAA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection and validation of reference genes suitable for gene expression analysis by reverse transcription quantitative real-time PCR in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3830</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-51499-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38360762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10869792</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">de Oliveira PAA, et al. Selection and validation of reference genes suitable for gene expression analysis by reverse transcription quantitative real-time PCR in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):3830.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38360762</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-51499-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10869792</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CRISPR-Cas in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> contributes to antibiotic susceptibility by targeting endogenous AbaI</article-title><source>Microbiol Spectr</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e00829</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.00829-22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35938813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9430643</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Wang Y, et al. CRISPR-Cas in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> contributes to antibiotic susceptibility by targeting endogenous AbaI. Microbiol Spectr. 2022;10(4):e00829–22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35938813</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/spectrum.00829-22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9430643</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capalash</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin alleviates persistence of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> against colistin</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11029</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-29291-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30038318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6056455</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Kaur A, Sharma P, Capalash N. Curcumin alleviates persistence of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> against colistin. Sci Rep. 2018;8(1):11029.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30038318</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-018-29291-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6056455</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eradication of persister cells of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> through combination of colistin and amikacin antibiotics</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2019</year><volume>74</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkz034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30759206</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Chung ES, Ko KS. Eradication of persister cells of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> through combination of colistin and amikacin antibiotics. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2019;74(5):1277–83.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30759206</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jac/dkz034</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro and in vivo activity of combinations of polymyxin B with other antimicrobials against carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Infect Drug Resist</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S334200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34764660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8577563</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Zhang H, et al. In vitro and in vivo activity of combinations of polymyxin B with other antimicrobials against carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Infect Drug Resist. 2021. 10.2147/IDR.S334200.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34764660</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/IDR.S334200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8577563</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergamini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mouse pneumonia model by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> multidrug resistant strains: comparison between intranasal inoculation, intratracheal instillation and oropharyngeal aspiration techniques</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0260627</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0260627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34855837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8638993</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Bergamini G, et al. Mouse pneumonia model by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> multidrug resistant strains: comparison between intranasal inoculation, intratracheal instillation and oropharyngeal aspiration techniques. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(12):e0260627.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34855837</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0260627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8638993</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magiorakos</surname><given-names>A-P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: an international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03570.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793988</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Magiorakos A-P, et al. Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: an international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2012;18(3):268–81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793988</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03570.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypervirulent <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (hvAB): the convergence of virulence and multidrug resistance</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2025</year><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>551</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics14060551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40558141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12190087</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Wu N, Ma X, Ni W. Hypervirulent <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (hvAB): the convergence of virulence and multidrug resistance. Antibiotics. 2025;14(6):551.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40558141</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics14060551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12190087</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molteni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>La Motta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valoppi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving the bioaccessibility and bioavailability of carotenoids by means of nanostructured delivery systems: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Antioxidants</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>p1931</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox11101931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9598319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36290651</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Molteni C, La Motta C, Valoppi F. Improving the bioaccessibility and bioavailability of carotenoids by means of nanostructured delivery systems: a comprehensive review. Antioxidants. 2022;11(10):p1931.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox11101931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9598319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36290651</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izhar</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drug delivery through niosomes: a comprehensive review with therapeutic applications</article-title><source>J Cluster Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2257</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10876-023-02423-w</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Izhar MP, et al. Drug delivery through niosomes: a comprehensive review with therapeutic applications. J Cluster Sci. 2023;34(5):2257–73.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nanocarriers for the delivery of antibiotics into cells against intracellular bacterial infection</article-title><source>Biomater Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D2BM01489K</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36503914</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Wang C, et al. Nanocarriers for the delivery of antibiotics into cells against intracellular bacterial infection. Biomater Sci. 2023;11(2):432–44.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36503914</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/d2bm01489k</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overcoming resistance: chitosan-modified liposomes as targeted drug carriers in the fight against multidrug resistant bacteria-a review</article-title><source>Int J Biol Macromol</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39182895</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Singh I, et al. Overcoming resistance: chitosan-modified liposomes as targeted drug carriers in the fight against multidrug resistant bacteria-a review. Int J Biol Macromol. 2024. 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135022.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39182895</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135022</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shiri S et al. Exploring the use of saponin as a biosurfactant for formulating Niosomal carriers to regulate the release of Berberine. J Dispers Sci Technol. 2025: pp. 1–11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cakir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimizing niosomal formulations for enhanced cellular applications: a comparative case study with L-α‐lecithin liposomes</article-title><source>Adv Pharmacol Pharm Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>2024</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9933465</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2024/9933465</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Cakir N, et al. Optimizing niosomal formulations for enhanced cellular applications: a comparative case study with L-α‐lecithin liposomes. Adv Pharmacol Pharm Sci. 2024;2024(1):9933465.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan hydrochloride coated and nonionic surfactant modified niosomes: a better way for oral administration of semaglutide</article-title><source>Biomed Mater</source><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-605X/adb2cf</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39908666</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Wang B, et al. Chitosan hydrochloride coated and nonionic surfactant modified niosomes: a better way for oral administration of semaglutide. Biomed Mater. 2025. 10.1088/1748-605X/adb2cf.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39908666</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1088/1748-605X/adb2cf</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kianinejad N, et al. Preparation and characterization of niosomes for the delivery of a lipophilic model drug: comparative stability study with liposomes against phospholipase-A2. J Liposome Res. 2024(2). 10.1080/08982104.2024.2410748.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08982104.2024.2410748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39363444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maghraby</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Olive oil and flaxseed oil incorporating niosomes for enhanced in vivo anti-diabetic efficacy of Canagliflozin</article-title><source>Drug Dev Ind Pharm</source><year>2024</year><volume>50</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03639045.2024.2409167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39319618</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Saad G, El GM, Maghraby, Sultan AA. Olive oil and flaxseed oil incorporating niosomes for enhanced in vivo anti-diabetic efficacy of Canagliflozin. Drug Dev Ind Pharm. 2024;50(9):801–9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39319618</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03639045.2024.2409167</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Farhana A et al. Antioxidant and Prooxidant Functions of Carotenoids in Human Health: Trigger Factors, Mechanism and Application, in Recent Advances in Phytochemical Research. 2025, IntechOpen.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The benefits and risks of certain dietary carotenoids that exhibit both anti-and pro-oxidative mechanisms—a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Antioxidants</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox9030264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32210038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7139534</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Black HS, et al. The benefits and risks of certain dietary carotenoids that exhibit both anti-and pro-oxidative mechanisms—a comprehensive review. Antioxidants. 2020;9(3):264.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32210038</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox9030264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7139534</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rifampicin niosome: preparations, characterizations and antibacterial activity against <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> isolated from acne</article-title><source>Dhaka Univ J Pharm Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3329/dujps.v14i1.23744</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Begum K, et al. Rifampicin niosome: preparations, characterizations and antibacterial activity against <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> isolated from acne. Dhaka Univ J Pharm Sci. 2015;14(1):117–23.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghafelehbashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preparation, physicochemical properties, in vitro evaluation and release behavior of cephalexin-loaded niosomes</article-title><source>Int J Pharm</source><year>2019</year><volume>569</volume><fpage>118580</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2019.118580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31374239</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Ghafelehbashi R, et al. Preparation, physicochemical properties, in vitro evaluation and release behavior of cephalexin-loaded niosomes. Int J Pharm. 2019;569:118580.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31374239</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2019.118580</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaleghian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In silico design and mechanistic study of niosome-encapsulated Curcumin against multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilms</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1277533</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1277533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38098658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10720333</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Khaleghian M, et al. In silico design and mechanistic study of niosome-encapsulated Curcumin against multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilms. Front Microbiol. 2023;14:1277533.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38098658</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1277533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10720333</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmati</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antibiofilm potentials of vancomycin-loaded niosomal drug delivery system against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) infections</article-title><source>BMC Biotechnol</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12896-024-00874-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38978013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11229259</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Hemmati J, et al. Antibacterial and antibiofilm potentials of vancomycin-loaded niosomal drug delivery system against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) infections. BMC Biotechnol. 2024;24(1):47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38978013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12896-024-00874-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11229259</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mehdipour E, Iranbakhsh A, Mirzaie A. Formulation, characterization and co-delivery of Curcuminrosemary loaded niosomes to enhance antimicrobial activity against <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains. Nanomed J. 2025; 12(2): 313.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhtiari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced antimicrobial effects of carvacrol against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains using niosome formulations</article-title><source>Rev Argent Microbiol</source><year>2025</year><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39843290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ram.2024.10.001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Bakhtiari R, et al. Enhanced antimicrobial effects of carvacrol against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains using niosome formulations. Rev Argent Microbiol. 2025;57(1):39–48.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39843290</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ram.2024.10.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naseef Pathoor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Understanding the biofilm development of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and novel strategies to combat infection</article-title><source>APMIS</source><year>2024</year><volume>132</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apm.13399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38444124</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Naseef Pathoor N, et al. Understanding the biofilm development of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and novel strategies to combat infection. APMIS. 2024;132(5):317–35.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38444124</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/apm.13399</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shamkani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced anti-biofilm activity of the minocycline-and-gallium-nitrate using niosome wrapping against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in C57/BL6 mouse pneumonia model</article-title><source>Int Immunopharmacol</source><year>2023</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>109551</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2022.109551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36621329</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Shamkani F, et al. Enhanced anti-biofilm activity of the minocycline-and-gallium-nitrate using niosome wrapping against <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in C57/BL6 mouse pneumonia model. Int Immunopharmacol. 2023;115:109551.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36621329</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2022.109551</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paseban</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preparation and optimization of niosome encapsulated meropenem for significant antibacterial and anti-biofilm activity against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e35651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39211930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11357772</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Paseban K, et al. Preparation and optimization of niosome encapsulated meropenem for significant antibacterial and anti-biofilm activity against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates. Heliyon. 2024. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e35651.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39211930</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e35651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11357772</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dakwa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mozirandi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukanganyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of <italic toggle="yes">Azanza garckeana</italic> extracts (Malvaceae) in vitro and their potential use in respiratory infections</article-title><source>Microb Pathog</source><year>2025</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>107170</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.107170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39613234</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Dakwa R, Mozirandi W, Mukanganyama S. Antibacterial activity of <italic toggle="yes">Azanza garckeana</italic> extracts (Malvaceae) in vitro and their potential use in respiratory infections. Microb Pathog. 2025;198:107170.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39613234</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.micpath.2024.107170</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>SKK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of quorum sensing, biofilm formation, and iron acquisition as key virulence mechanisms in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and the corresponding anti-virulence strategies</article-title><source>Microbiol Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>127032</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2022.127032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35483311</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Law SKK, Tan HS. The role of quorum sensing, biofilm formation, and iron acquisition as key virulence mechanisms in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and the corresponding anti-virulence strategies. Microbiol Res. 2022;260:127032.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35483311</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.micres.2022.127032</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The abaI/abaR quorum sensing system effects on pathogenicity in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>679241</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.679241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34322102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8312687</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Sun X, et al. The abaI/abaR quorum sensing system effects on pathogenicity in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Front Microbiol. 2021;12:679241.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34322102</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2021.679241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8312687</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Namasivayam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In Silico and in vitro analysis of quorum quenching active phytochemicals from the ethanolic extract of medicinal plants against quorum sensing mediated virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Indian J Biochem Biophys (IJBB)</source><year>2019</year><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Namasivayam S, et al. In Silico and in vitro analysis of quorum quenching active phytochemicals from the ethanolic extract of medicinal plants against quorum sensing mediated virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Indian J Biochem Biophys (IJBB). 2019;56(4):276–86.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pumirat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of AbaI mutation on virulence, biofilm development, and antibiotic susceptibility in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21521</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-72740-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39277662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11401864</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Pumirat P, et al. Impact of AbaI mutation on virulence, biofilm development, and antibiotic susceptibility in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):21521.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39277662</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-72740-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11401864</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR70" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased OmpW and OmpA expression and higher virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> persister cells</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-023-02904-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37246220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10226259</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70" publication-type="journal">Schmitt BL, et al. Increased OmpW and OmpA expression and higher virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> persister cells. BMC Microbiol. 2023;23(1):157.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37246220</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12866-023-02904-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10226259</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunosuppression broadens evolutionary pathways to drug resistance and treatment failure during <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> pneumonia in mice</article-title><source>Nat Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-022-01126-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35618774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9159950</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Huo W, et al. Immunosuppression broadens evolutionary pathways to drug resistance and treatment failure during <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> pneumonia in mice. Nat Microbiol. 2022;7(6):796–809.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35618774</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41564-022-01126-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9159950</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using the Chinese herb scutellaria Barbata against extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections: in vitro and in vivo studies</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-018-2151-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29554903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5859712</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Tsai C-C, et al. Using the Chinese herb scutellaria Barbata against extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections: in vitro and in vivo studies. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2018;18:1–11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29554903</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12906-018-2151-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5859712</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>