<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Curr Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3814</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">phenaturepg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Current Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0343-8651</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0991</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer Nature - PMC COVID-19 Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8439540</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8439540.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8439540</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8439540</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34522977</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-021-02654-y</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2654</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mechanism Underlying the Role of LuxR Family Transcriptional Regulator <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> in Biofilm Formation by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="X">Xu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><address><email>13801789791@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412277.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 6738</institution-id><institution>Department of Burn, </institution><institution>Ruijin Hospital Affiliated to Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>78</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">390007</issue-id><fpage>3936</fpage><lpage>3944</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>09</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>09</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-08 18:25:15.470"><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2021</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="284_2021_Article_2654.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Our study attempted to explore the mechanism underlying the role of LuxR family transcriptional regulator <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> in biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii.</italic> The <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene was knocked out in ATCC 17978 strain using homologous recombination method. The growth curve and biofilm formation were measured in the wild type and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown strains. Transcriptome sequencing was performed in the wild type and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown strains following 8 h of culture. The growth curve in the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown strain was similar to that of the wild-type strain. Biofilm formation significantly declined in the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown strain at 8 and 48 h after culture. A total of 137 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were obtained including 20 downregulated DEGs and 117 upregulated DEGs. Genes with differential expression were closely related to viral procapsid maturation (GO:0046797), acetoin catabolism (GO:0045150), carbon metabolism (ko01200), and the glycolysis/gluconeogenesis (ko00010)-related pathways. The results of the eight verified expression DEGs were consistent with the results predicted by bioinformatics. <italic toggle="yes">AbaR</italic> gene knockdown significantly affected biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 strain. The glycolysis/gluconeogenesis pathways were significantly dysregulated and induced by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii.</italic></p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s00284-021-02654-y.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Shanghai Municipal Science and Technology Commission</institution></funding-source><award-id>16ZR1420800</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2"><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> is a Gram-negative coccobacillus which is troublesome pathogen in hospitalized patients globally. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> has emerged as a major challenge in infected patients because of its multiple drug resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, pp. 939–951]. Recent data show that <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is one of the top four most common pathogens isolated in the hospital environment between 2005 and 2017 in China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, pp. S128–S134]. In global intensive care units (ICUs), the infection rate of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. baumannii accounts for 20% of the total number of infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, pp. 25–36]. The resistance profile of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> spp. indicates that the resistance rate against the five commonly used antimicrobials, except amikacin, is increasing. The resistance rate of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> against carbapenems varied from 18 to 25% in different provinces of China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, pp. S128–S134]. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> can cause a variety of nosocomial infections, most of which involve the respiratory tract and some involve skin wound infections and bacteremia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. This is corroborated by the report that <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is an increasing threat in burn centers because of its high multidrug resistance based on clinical data obtained from a comprehensive hospital covering 2007–2013 and the CHINET (the surveillance system for bacterial epidemiology and resistance in China) data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, pp. 1718–1719].</p><p id="Par3">Considerable attention has been focused on exploring the mechanism of drug resistance in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in clinical settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. One of the major factors associated with bacterial resistance to antimicrobials is the ability to form biofilms. Previous studies have shown that strains that can form biofilms are more resistant to antibiotics than strains that cannot [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Recent evidence shows that biofilm formation is closely related to drug resistance and virulence in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, pp. 119–127]. It is reported that the biofilm-forming ability of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in a solid–liquid interface is approximately three times higher than that of other <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, pp. 1–4]. <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. baumannii can rapidly produce biofilms while forming antibiotic resistance, and the level of biofilm-specific resistance can vary according to the induction response of the biofilm population and the action mechanism of antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, p. 817]. Cold plasma technology, as a new tool for purification of biofilm-contaminated surfaces, has received more and more clinical attention. The increase in the amount of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. baumannii biofilm could reduce the antibacterial effect of cold plasma, thereby improving its tolerance to cold plasma exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, pp. 344–349]. The biofilm formation characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. baumannii are related to the expression of genes. The genes that have been reported to be associated with the formation of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>. baumannii biofilm include <italic toggle="yes">csu</italic> locus, <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">adeFGH</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic> encodes a fimbriae assembly system, and the formation of fimbriae is an important step in the formation of biofilm on non-living surfaces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, pp. 3473–3484]. <italic toggle="yes">Bap</italic> can support the development of mature biofilm structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, pp. 1036–1044]. The mutation of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> will cause the failure of the acyl-homoserine lactone signals to be generated and further damage the maturation of the biofilm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, pp. 951–957]. <italic toggle="yes">adeFGH</italic> is involved in the synthesis and transport of autoinducer molecules during the formation of biofilms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, pp. 4817–25]. <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> encodes a porin protein involved in the formation of biofilms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, pp. 3150–3160]. Previous reports have implicated the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilm formation and disruption of <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> expression is associated with a decline in biofilm formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, pp. 1802–1805; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, pp. 200–205; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, pp. 1339–1346]. Although there have been advances in exploring the mechanism underlying biofilm formation, the role of abaR at the transcriptome level has not been clarified completely.</p><p id="Par4">Therefore, in this study, we aimed to determine the role of <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilm formation through <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown and explore the mechanism regulated by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> expression using high-throughput transcriptional sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Bacterial Strains and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> Gene Knockouts</title><p id="Par5"><italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 strain was obtained from Shanghai Santa Biotechnology Co. Ltd., Shanghai, China. The ATCC 17978 strain was cultured in Luria–Bertani (LB) medium at 37 °C overnight. The <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown was performed using homologous recombination method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, pp. 3743–3751]. A recombinant DNA fragment (ΔabaR::Kn) consisting of kanamycin resistance gene (Kn) sequences (obtained from pKD4 plasmid using PCR) and the upper and lower homologous recombination arms for <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene (amplified from ATCC17978 genome using PCR) were obtained using splicing PCR technology. ΔabaR::Kn target fragments were amplified by transferring them into pUC19 vector and tested by PCR analysis. The primers used are listed in Supplementary Table 1. Next, ΔabaR::Kn sequences were linked to pCVD442 vector and transferred to <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> β2155 by electrotransformation. Conjugation between ATCC17978 strain and the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was performed and the knockdown ATCC17978 strains were selected for kanamycin resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, pp. 71–76].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Construction of Complementary Strains</title><p id="Par6">To complement the knockout mutant, the target gene <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> was amplified from the cDNA of ATCC17978 strain, and the amplification product was cloned into the vector pBAD33-TC<sup>R</sup> to construct a pBAD33-TC<sup>R</sup>-<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>. The vector pBAD33-TC<sup>R</sup> has the origin of replication ori amplified on the pWH1266 plasmid and the tetracycline resistance gene; so, this plasmid can be amplified in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Then, pBAD33-TC<sup>R</sup>-<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> was transformed to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> competent cells DH5α. The plasmids that were positive after tetracycline screening were sequenced. Then, the plasmids with correct sequencing results were transferred to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> β2163 competent cells and the positive clone <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> β2163-[pBAD33-TC<sup>R</sup>-<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>] was screened. Finally, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> β2163-[pBAD33-TC<sup>R</sup>-<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>] was transformed into knockdown ATCC17978 strains using electrotransformation method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, pp. 162–168] and the recombinant clones were screened out, followed by PCR verification, and PCR products are sequenced for sequence confirmation (Supplementary Fig. 1). The primers used in this section were listed in Supplementary Table 2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Growth Curve Analysis</title><p id="Par7">ATCC 17978 and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains at 1 × 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL were maintained in fresh LB media at 37 °C for consecutive 18 h. The optical density (OD) of cultured strains in each group was evaluated for each hour using a Microplate reader (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). There were three repeats in each group.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Biofilm Formation Analysis</title><p id="Par8">Next, 200 μL of strain cultures (1 × 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL) was seeded onto each well of a 96-well plate. After culturing for 8, 24, and 48 h, the cultures were washed thrice with 200 μL PBS. Next, the cultures were fixed in methanol for 15 min followed by staining with 0.2% crystal violet solution for 20 min. After washing, 200 μL of 33% glacial acetic acid was added to each well and then, OD values were measured using a Microplate reader.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>RNA Sequencing</title><p id="Par9">After culturing for 8 h, ATCC17978 and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains were collected for further analysis. Total RNA of the cultures in the two groups were isolated using mirVana miRNA isolation kit (Ambion) following the manufacturer’s protocols, separately [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, p. e72968]. Because the vast majority of RNA in bacteria is rRNA, rRNA was obtained using Ribo-Zero Magnetic Kit (MRZB12424, Illumina, CA, USA) and removed, following which the mRNAs were broken into fragments as templates for cDNA synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. An RNA library was constructed using PCR analysis. The quality and size of the DNA fragments were evaluated using Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer. The whole transcriptome was then sequenced based on the Illumina platform.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data Processing</title><p id="Par10">The raw data were downloaded and quality control was performed, using Trimmomatic software, including removing adaptor and low-quality reads. Clean reads were then mapped to reference genome using Rockhooper2 software. The gene expression level was measured based on the number of reads mapped to the genome and exome according to the reads per kilobase per million mapped reads (RPKM) method. The formula is provided in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>) as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{RPKM}}=\frac{{\text{Total}} \,{\text{exon}} \,{\text{reads}}}{{\text{Mapped}} \,{\text{reads}} \left({\text{millions}}\right)\times {\text{exon}} \,{\text{length}} \left({\text{KB}}\right)}.$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RPKM</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Total</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>exon</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>reads</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mapped</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>reads</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mtext>millions</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mtext>exon</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>length</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mtext>KB</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_Article_Equ1.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Differentially Expressed Gene Analysis</title><p id="Par11">The gene counts were normalized using DESeq software to produce the significant genes with differential expression between the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown ATCC 17978 and wild-type ATCC 17978 strains. The fold change (FC) of gene expression was calculated and negative binomial distribution test was applied to evaluate the significance of the differences in gene reads between two samples. The log|FC|&gt; 1.5 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; 0.05 were set as the cutoff values.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Function Enrichment Analysis</title><p id="Par12">The Gene Ontology (GO) project provides the possibility of biological function annotation of genes of interest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, pp. D322–D326]. The differentially expressed genes were subjected to GO function analysis and the significant <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were tested using the hypergeometric distribution test. GO terms with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt; 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Pathway Enrichment Analysis</title><p id="Par13">The Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.ad.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.ad.jp/kegg/</ext-link>) is a pathway-related database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, pp. 91–100]. KEGG pathway enrichment analysis was performed to explore the pathways involved in differentially expressed genes using the DAVID online tool. The enrichment <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were calculated using the hypergeometric distribution test. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; 0.05 was considered the cutoff value.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Real-Time Reverse Transcription-PCR Verification</title><p id="Par14">RT-PCR was carried out to determine the relative expression of some DEGs. Total RNA was isolated from wild-type strains, mutant strains, and complementary strains after 8 h of culture. The concentration of RNA was detected using NanoDrop 2000. RNA was reverse-transcribed to cDNA using TransScript All-in-One First-Strand cDNA Synthesis SuperMIX for qPCR kit. PerfectStartTM Green qPCR SuperMix kit and LightCycler® 480 system were used together to perform RT-PCR. All assays were performed in triplicate. The relative expression levels of RNAs were calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method. 16 s was set as internal control. The primer sequences are listed in Supplementary Table 3.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="Par15">The data for strain growth and biofilm formation are expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Multiple group comparison was performed using one-way ANOVA analysis and the difference between two groups was analyzed using the LSD test. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Deposit the RNA-Seq Data</title><p id="Par16">The raw sequencing data were deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Sequence ReadArchive (SRA) database under accession number PRJNA720897.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Effective <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> Gene Knockouts in ATCC 17978 Strain</title><p id="Par17">PCR analysis of a recombinant DNA fragment (ΔabaR::Kn) showed that the size of the target sequence was 3029 bp (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Next, the knockdown ATCC17978 strain was selected for kanamycin resistance. The PCR amplification of the target fragment was about 3300 bp, which indicated that the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene sequence was successfully replaced by ΔabaR::Kn target fragment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Size of the target fragments (ΔabaR::Kn) by PCR analysis (<bold>a</bold>) and the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown determined by PCR analysis (<bold>b</bold>). <bold>a</bold>: M, marker; 1, target (ΔabaR::Kn) fragment (size: 3029 bp). <bold>b</bold>: M, DL10000 marker; M2, DL2000 marker; 1, tested fragment after abaR gene knockdown (size: 3300 bp)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Growth Curve of ATCC 17978 Strain and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> Knockdown Strain</title><p id="Par18">The strain growth curve in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> showed that the OD values for the ATCC 17978 strain were slightly higher than the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strain at 2, 3, and 4 h of culture. No significant differences were observed in the OD values of the two strain groups from 5 to 12 h of culture. All strains entered the plateau stage after 14 h of culture. ATCC17978 entered the exponential growth stage during 3–4 h of culture in vitro and entered the plateau stage at 14 h, which was similar to the growth curve of the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strain.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Growth curve for ATCC 17978 strain after abaR gene knockdown, compared with wide-type strain. The OD value of strains after abaR gene knockdown was observed at 0–18 h of culture. There were three repeats in each group</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Biofilm Formation Analysis</title><p id="Par19">As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, biofilm formation by the ATCC 17978 strain increased in a time-dependent manner and peaked at 48 h of culture. However, there were no significant changes in the biofilm-forming ability of <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains during 0–8 h of culture. The biofilm-forming ability in the wild type and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains was similar at 0–4 h of culture. At 8, 24, and 48 h after strain culture, the OD value of ATCC 17978 was 0.63 ± 0.06, 0.522 ± 0.18, and 1.04 ± 0.32, respectively. After <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown, the OD value was 0.41 ± 0.20, 0.45 ± 0.11, and 0.57 ± 0.02 at 8, 24, and 48 h, respectively. There were significant differences in OD values at 8 and 48 h of culture between the groups (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt; 0.05), indicating that biofilm formation significantly declined in the ATCC 17978 strain after <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Biofilm formation of ATCC 17978 strain after <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown, compared with wide-type strain. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, compared with wide-type ATCC 17978 strain. There were three repeats in each group</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Identification of Differentially Expressed Genes</title><p id="Par20">With the cutoff value of log|FC|&gt; 1.5 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; 0.05, a total of 137 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were obtained between the wild type and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains, including 20 downregulated genes and 117 upregulated genes (Supplementary Table 4). The volcano plot of genes with differential expression is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>.<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Volcano plot for differentially expressed genes in <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strain, compared with wide-type strain. Red spots represent genes that were significantly upregulated. Green spots represent genes that were significantly downregulated. Gray spots represent genes that were not significantly different between the two groups (Color figure online)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Significant Biological Processes and Pathways for Differentially Expressed Genes</title><p id="Par21">GO analysis was performed for all the genes with differential expression. A total of 79 GO terms were enriched by differentially expressed genes, among which 58 GO terms were significantly enriched with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05. The differentially expressed genes were closely related to acetoin catabolic process (GO:0045150, BP), glycolytic process (GO:0006096, BP), tartrate dehydrogenase activity (GO:0009027, MF), and viral capsid (GO:0019028, CC). A total of 22 pathways were significantly enriched and the top 15 significant pathways are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The results showed that pathways such as glycolysis/gluconeogenesis (ko00010), pyruvate metabolism (ko00620), and glucagon signaling pathway (ko04922) were dysregulated in <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains compared with the wild-type ATCC 17978.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The top 15 significant GO term and pathways of differentially expressed genes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ID</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Term</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Category</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">GO function enrichment analysis</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0009027</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tartrate dehydrogenase activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_0849</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0046553</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sc>d</sc>-Malate dehydrogenase (decarboxylating) activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_0849</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0019028</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Viral capsid</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cellular_component</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1589; A1S_2022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0046797</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Viral procapsid maturation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Biological_process</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1590</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0016624</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oxidoreductase activity, acting on the aldehyde or oxo group of donors, disulfide as acceptor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1699</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0003886</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DNA(cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.37E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1146; A1S_2036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0099001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Viral genome ejection through host cell envelope, long flexible tail mechanism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Biological_process</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.37E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1589; A1S_2022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0045150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acetoin catabolic process</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Biological_process</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.37E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1699; A1S_1700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0004148</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.37E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1702; A1S_1703</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0009307</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DNA restriction-modification system</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Biological_process</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.52E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000109</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1146; A1S_2036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0019012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Virion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cellular_component</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.52E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000109</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1590; A1S_1595</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0006096</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glycolytic process</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Biological_process</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.67E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000241</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1701; A1S_1702; A1S_1703</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0015103</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inorganic anion transmembrane transporter activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000251</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000903</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_0669</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0003862</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3-isopropylmalate dehydrogenase activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000251</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000903</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_0849</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GO:0003992</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2-Acetyl-<sc>l</sc>-Ornithine:2-oxoglutarate 5-aminotransferase activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Molecular_function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000251</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000903</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1092</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Pathway enrichment analysis</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko00010</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Glycolysis/Gluconeogenesis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.95E-08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.06E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1699; A1S_1700; A1S_1701; A1S_1702; A1S_1703; A1S_2148</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko00620</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Pyruvate metabolism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.47E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.82E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1699; A1S_1700; A1S_1701; A1S_1702; A1S_1703; A1S_2148</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko00020</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Citrate cycle (TCA cycle)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.43E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1699; A1S_1700; A1S_1701; A1S_1702; A1S_1703</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko04922</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Glucagon signaling pathway</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.58E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1699; A1S_1700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko01200</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Carbon metabolism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.74E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1386; A1S_1699; A1S_1700; A1S_1701; A1S_1702; A1S_1703; A1S_2148</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko04066</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">HIF-1 signaling pathway</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.39E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1699; A1S_1700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko00630</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Glyoxylate and dicarboxylate metabolism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000373</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_0849; A1S_1386; A1S_1702; A1S_1703</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko00280</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Valine, leucine, and isoleucine degradation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000298</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000967</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1376; A1S_1702; A1S_1703</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko00785</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Lipoic acid metabolism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000578</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00167</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1698</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko00640</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Propanoate metabolism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00101</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002625</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1702; A1S_1703; A1S_2148</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko04011</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MAPK signaling pathway—yeast</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001147</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00271</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1386</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko04211</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Longevity regulating pathway</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001895</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004106</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1386</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko04068</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">FoxO signaling pathway</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002819</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005638</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1386</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko04213</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Longevity regulating pathway—multiple species</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003914</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.007268</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1386</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ko04212</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Longevity regulating pathway—worm</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.006598</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.011436</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A1S_1386</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>RT-PCR Detection</title><p id="Par22">The relative expression levels of four significantly up-regulated DEGs and four significantly down-regulated DEGs were detected by PT-PCR between wild-type ATCC17978 strains and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). As we predicted, compared in the wild-type ATCC17978 strains, the relative expression of A1S_3544, A1S_0849, A1S_3867, and A1S_3011 showed a significantly higher levels in the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The expression levels of A1S_3661, A1S_1709, A1S_2237, and A1S_2457 were significantly higher in the wild-type ATCC17978 strains than that in the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Relative expression of genes in wide-type ATCC 17978 strains and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown strains. ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, compared with wide-type ATCC 17978 strain. There were three repeats in each group. Error bar represents SD</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">We also detected the relative expression of A1S_0849 and A1S_2237 between wild-type ATCC17978 strains, <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains, and complementary strains (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The results revealed that there were no significant difference between ATCC17978 strains and complementary strains in the A1S_0849 and A1S_2237 expression. This indicates that our complementation experiment successfully restored gene expression to the wild-type level.<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Relative expression of genes in wide-type ATCC 17978 strains, <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown strains, and complemented strains. ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, compared with wide-type ATCC 17978 strain. There were three repeats in each group. Error bar represents SD</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24"><italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> has emerged as an important nosocomial pathogen mainly affecting patients with impaired host defences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, pp. 640–645]. Now, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is one of the most prevalent pathogens in burn-induced infections because of its multidrug-resistance, which can even induce bloodstream infections. <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is responsible for a vast array of infections, of which ventilator-associated pneumonia and bloodstream infections are the most common, and mortality rates can reach 35% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, pp. 292–301]. Multidrug resistance may complicate the treatment of serious infections. Biofilm-forming ability has been found to be the major factor affecting drug resistance by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, pp. 626–633]. Many gram-negative pathogens control their virulence through a quorum sensing (QS) system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, p. 163]. <italic toggle="yes">AbaR</italic> is one of the QS-related genes, which is reported to play a regulatory role in biofilm formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, pp. 15–27]. In this study, we aimed to explore the mechanism underlying the role of <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilm formation<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p><p id="Par25">We first determined the regulatory role of <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> biofilm formation by gene knockout. In <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii,</italic> abaR- and abaI-mediated QS plays a regulatory role in biofilm formation and surface motility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, pp. 1719–1728]. The <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene at a size of 717 bp is localized at 1255 bp of the downstream of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene. Additionally, we constructed an <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockout model in neurons using homologous recombination method. After <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene knockdown, the alternative target fragment in ATCC 17978 was determined to be 3300 bp using PCR analysis, which was similar to the size of ΔabaR::Kn target fragment, suggesting that the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene was successfully knocked out.</p><p id="Par26">Data of the growth curve analysis showed that after 4 h of culture, the growth of the wild-type ATCC 17978 entered the exponential growth phase and entered the plateau phase at 14 h after culture. The <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strain showed a similar growth curve, which indicates that no significant effect was observed in the growth of ATCC 17978 strain following <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown.</p><p id="Par27">A previous study suggested that the absorbance value of drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strain was similar to sensitive strains at all culture time points. Compared with the controls, the biofilm-forming ability of the ATCC 17978 strain exposed to <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Heptanoyl-<sc>l</sc>-Homoserine lactone significantly declined at 12 h of culture and that of strains exposed to <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-(3-Hydroxydodecanoyl)-<sc>dl</sc>-Homoserine lactone noticeably increased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, pp. 200–205]. Therefore, inhibition or activation of the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene can influence biofilm formation. Our data showed that biofilm-forming ability significantly increased in the wild-type ATCC 17978 strain compared with the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown ATCC 17978 strain at 8 h of culture, which was consistent with the previous findings. All these results suggest that <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown affected the biofilm-forming ability of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> without influencing strain growth.</p><p id="Par28">In addition, the mechanism of the declined biofilm-forming ability of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> induced by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown has not been clarified completely. Thus, we performed transcriptome sequencing to identify the changed gene expression profile caused by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown. Based on the results, a total of 137 genes were differentially expressed between the wild type and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains. GO analysis showed that viral procapsid maturation was closely related to the dysregulated expressed genes induced by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown. It is reported that viral procapsid maturation is a dynamic process for viral infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, pp. 423–439]. The virus capsid assembly and DNA packaging have been proposed to be the target for antiviral therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Thus, biofilm formation may share a similar group of involved genes with viral procapsid maturation and biofilm formation may be suggested as the target for antimicrobial treatment.</p><p id="Par29">A previous study suggested that the changes in gene expression were more obvious in the early stage of biofilm formation than the later stages. In our study, biofilm formation was significantly changed at 8 and 24 h of culture in <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains compared with the wild-type strains. Thus, we performed transcriptome sequencing for the strains cultured for 8 h. Previous evidence showed that carbohydrate and amino acid metabolism were the necessary pathways in biofilm formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, p. 13160]. Our study suggested that the DEGs in <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown strains, compared with the wild-type ATCC 17978, were significantly enriched in carbon metabolism and valine, leucine, and isoleucine degradation, which is consistent with previous reports and indicates that our findings are significant. Additionally, glycolysis and gluconeogenesis were the most significant pathways involved in the differentially expressed genes. A recent study reported that genes that play a regulatory role in gluconeogenesis are significantly upregulated in biofilm cells compared with free cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, p. 139]. It is reported that carbohydrates are the major composition of biofilms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Carbon sources play a necessary role in the survival, growth, and infection of strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, pp. 2034–2045]. Accumulating evidence shows that <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> can utilize glycolysis and gluconeogenesis alternatively for energy production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Glycolysis plays a necessary role in the morphogenesis and virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> species<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> The evidence for the significant role of glycolysis and gluconeogenesis pathways in <italic toggle="yes">A. Baumannii</italic> virulence has been rarely reported. Thus, we suspect that the dysregulation of the glycolysis and gluconeogenesis pathways was induced by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown in <italic toggle="yes">A. Baumannii.</italic></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par30">Although this study lacks certain mechanism experiments, our verification of DEGs through RT-PCR showed that our bioinformatics analysis has a certain degree of credibility. Of course, further research on the protein level of these DEGs is also necessary in the future. In summary, <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown significantly decreased the biofilm-forming ability of the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 strain without affecting its growth. Carbon metabolism-related pathways, especially the glycolysis and gluconeogenesis pathways, were significantly dysregulated by <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> knockdown in <italic toggle="yes">A. Baumannii.</italic></p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec24"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_MOESM1_ESM.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (TIF 17301 KB) Size of the empty vector and complementary strain by PCR. M, DL2000 marker; 1, PCR product of empty vector (size 207 bp); 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6, PCR product of complementary strain (size: 924 bp)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="284_2021_2654_MOESM2_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 (DOCX 27 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conception and design of the research: JX and XS; acquisition of data: JX and XS; analysis and interpretation of data: JX and XS; statistical analysis: JX and XS; obtaining funding: JX; drafting the manuscript: XS; revision of manuscript for important intellectual content: JX. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code Availability</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical Approval</title><p id="Par32">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent to Participate</title><p id="Par33">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for Publication</title><p id="Par34">Not applicable.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkshoorn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An increasing threat in hospitals: multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18007677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Current status and trends of antibacterial resistance in China</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>S128</fpage><lpage>S134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciy657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30423045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Litake</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: an emerging pathogenic threat to public health</article-title><source>World J Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5495/wjcid.v3.i3.25</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vázquez-López</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solano-Gálvez</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juárez Vignon-Whaley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> resistance: a real challenge for clinicians</article-title><source>Antibiotics (Basel)</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>205</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9040205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7235888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32340386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance for and susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> in a large hospital and burn center in Shanghai, China, 2007–2013</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1718</fpage><lpage>1719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2016.06.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27544791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trebosc</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gartenmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tötzl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissecting colistin resistance mechanisms in extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> clinical isolates</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01083-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31311879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6635527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biofilm formation in acinetobacter baumannii: genotype-phenotype correlation</article-title><source>Molecules (Basel, Switzerland)</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1849</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24101849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6572253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31091746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuotto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>New Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24858639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martí</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez-Baño</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catel-Ferreira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biofilm formation at the solid-liquid and air-liquid interfaces by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> species</article-title><source>BMC Res Notes</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-4-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21223561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3023692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shenkutie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>GK-h</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biofilm-induced antibiotic resistance in clinical <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>817</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9110817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7698371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33212840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilm biomass mediates tolerance to cold plasma</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/lam.13122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30706947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6446819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaras</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorsey</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edelmann</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Attachment to and biofilm formation on abiotic surfaces by <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: involvement of a novel chaperone-usher pili assembly system</article-title><source>Microbiology (Reading, England)</source><year>2003</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>3473</fpage><lpage>3484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.26541-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14663080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loehfelm</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luke</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campagnari</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of an <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilm-associated protein</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2008</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>1036</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01416-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2223572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piperaki</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzouvelekis</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miriagou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: in pursuit of an effective treatment</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2019</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2019.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30914347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biofilm formation caused by clinical <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates is associated with overexpression of the AdeFGH efflux pump</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2015</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>4817</fpage><lpage>4825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00877-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26033730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4505227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaras</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> 19606 OmpA protein plays a role in biofilm formation on abiotic surfaces and in the interaction of this pathogen with eukaryotic cells</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2009</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>3150</fpage><lpage>3160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00096-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19470746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2715673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disruption of biofilm formation by the human pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> using engineered quorum-quenching lactonases</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2014</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1802</fpage><lpage>1805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02410-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3957888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influences of abaR gene on biofilm formation of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Zhonghua Shao Shang Za Zhi</source><year>2017</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3760/cma.j.issn.1009-2587.2017.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28427132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AbaR is a LuxR type regulator essential for motility and the formation of biofilm and pellicle in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title><source>Genes Genomics</source><year>2020</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13258-020-01005-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33025548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arroyo</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The pmrCAB operon mediates polymyxin resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 and clinical isolates through phosphoethanolamine modification of lipid A</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2011</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>3743</fpage><lpage>3751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00256-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21646482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3147623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chhetri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An improved method for high-level soluble expression and purification of recombinant amyloid-beta peptide for in vitro studies</article-title><source>Protein Expr Purif</source><year>2015</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pep.2015.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26118700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel IS26-mediated hybrid plasmid harbouring tet(X4) in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J Global Antimicrobial Resistance</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgar.2020.03.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32247809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rumbo-Feal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gayoso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole transcriptome analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> assessed by RNA-sequencing reveals different mRNA expression profiles in biofilm compared to planktonic cells</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e72968</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24023660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3758355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Culviner</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guegler</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laub</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple, cost-effective, and robust method for rRNA depletion in RNA-sequencing studies</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00010-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7175087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Consortium GO</collab></person-group><article-title>The gene ontology (GO) project in 2006</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D322</fpage><lpage>D326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkj021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1347384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>The KEGG database. Novartis Foundation Symposium</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12539951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>CJ-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>C-F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emergence of carbapenem-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> ST787 in clinical isolates from blood in a tertiary teaching hospital in Northern Taiwan</article-title><source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source><year>2017</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>640</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmii.2016.08.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28711441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visca</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Towner</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: evolution of a global pathogen</article-title><source>Pathogens Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2049-632X.12125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nor A’shimi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alattraqchi</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd Rani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biocide susceptibilities and biofilm-forming capacities of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> clinical isolates from Malaysia</article-title><source>J Infect Dev Ctries</source><year>2019</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3855/jidc.11455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32065820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vadakkan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayanand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemapriya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing inimical activity of <italic toggle="yes">Tribulus terrestris</italic> against gram negative bacterial pathogens by signalling interference</article-title><source>3 Biotech</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-019-1695-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6443769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30944810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saipriya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swathi</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnakar</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quorum-sensing system in <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: a potential target for new drug development</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.14330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31102552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stacy</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Attenuation of quorum sensing in the pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> using non-native N-Acyl homoserine lactones</article-title><source>ACS Chem Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1719</fpage><lpage>1728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cb300351x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22853441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3477293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heymann</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossmann</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Procapsid assembly, maturation, nuclear exit: dynamic steps in the production of infectious herpesvirions</article-title><source>Viral molecular machines</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-4614-0980-9_19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3475206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22297525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Capsid-targeted viral inactivation: a novel tactic for inhibiting replication in viral infections</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>258</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v8090258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5035972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27657114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The biology of <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title><source>Microbiol Spectr</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.GPP3-0051-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6615571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30657107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Que</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolomics deciphered metabolic reprogramming required for biofilm formation</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>13160</fpage><lpage>13166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-49603-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31511592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6739361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Involvement of glycolysis/gluconeogenesis and signaling regulatory pathways in <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> biofilms during fermentation</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>139</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25755652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4337339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alarcón</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monnappa</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Self-adaptation of pseudomonas fluorescens biofilms to hydrodynamic stress</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.588884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33510716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7835673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selective carbon sources influence the end products of microbial nitrate respiration</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2020</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2034</fpage><lpage>2045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41396-020-0666-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32372050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7368043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabana</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouweini</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> biofilms to drugs and the host immune system</article-title><source>Jundishapur J Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5812/jjm.37385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28138373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5240163</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>