<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1523</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">idr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">idr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7699449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7699449.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7699449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7699449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33262621</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S276970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">276970</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Contribution of the AbaI/AbaR Quorum Sensing System to Resistance and Virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> Clinical Strains</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Tang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Tang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinlei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhaohui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Pathogen Biology, <institution>The Key Laboratory of Zoonosis, Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Basic Medical Sciences, Jilin University</institution>, <addr-line>Changchun</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jilin</addr-line>
<addr-line>130021</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Neurosurgery, <institution>The Second Hospital of Jilin University</institution>, <addr-line>Changchun</addr-line>, <addr-line>China</addr-line>
<addr-line>130041</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Clinical Laboratory, <institution>The Second Hospital of Jilin University</institution>, <addr-line>Changchun</addr-line>
<addr-line>130041</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Zhaohui Ni Email nich@jlu.edu.cn</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">349618</issue-id><fpage>4273</fpage><lpage>4281</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-03-31 00:25:15.183"><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 Tang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tang et al.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="idr-13-4273.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Background</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>) is one of the most important pathogens that cause serious nosocomial infections worldwide. However, there are few reports on the virulence of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates, and little is known about the mechanism regulating virulence and drug resistance. The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of drug resistance and virulence profiles and explore features related to quorum sensing (QS).</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p>A total of 80 clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were collected from Jilin province of China from 2012 to 2017. We investigated these clinical isolates with respect to biofilm formation, surface motility, adherence, invasion into A549 human alveolar epithelial cells, and virulence to <italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic>. We also explored the prevalence of the AbaI/AbaR QS system and its correlation with bacterial virulence and drug resistance.</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>The resistance rates of the isolates to 17 commonly used antibiotics were higher than 50%, and 75% of the isolates were multi-drug resistant. Approximately 95% (76/80) of the isolates showed the ability to form biofilms, of which 38 showed strong biofilm formation ability (+++). Only 5 strains showed strong surface-related motility. A high level of variability was found in adherence and invasion into A549 epithelial cells, and 16 isolates showed strong virulence to <italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> (none survived after 6 days of infection). Of the 61 isolates carrying <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes, 24 were found to produce N-acyl homoserine lactones (AHLs) detectable by biosensor bacteria. Correlation analysis revealed that <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes positively correlated with bacterial resistance rates. All strains showing obvious surface-related motility carried <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes and produced AHLs. The isolates with detectable QS systems also showed stronger invasiveness into A549 cells and pathogenicity toward <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> than the QS-deficient isolates.</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our study demonstrates that the AbaI/AbaR QS system was widely distributed among the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates, was necessary for surface-related motility, and significantly correlated with drug resistance, invasion into epithelial cells, and virulence to <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></kwd><kwd>drug resistance</kwd><kwd>virulence</kwd><kwd>quorum sensing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>the National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>the Education Department of Jilin Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Jilin Province Science and Technology Department</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Department of Finance of Jilin Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was partially supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81601817), the Education Department of Jilin Province (JJKH20170820KJ), Jilin Province Science and Technology Department (20200201510JC) and grants from Department of Finance of Jilin Province(SWKYZ002).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="5"/><ref-count count="36"/><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>) is a clinically important, opportunistic pathogen that causes a wide range of clinical infections. Lately, many difficult-to-treat nosocomial infections caused by multidrug-resistant (MDR), extensive- or pan-drug-resistant (PDR) <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> have been reported throughout the world, which often lead to morbidity due to the development of antimicrobial drug resistance and the expression of virulence genes.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref> QS is a mechanism by which bacteria coordinate their group behavior by sensing their population density.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Small diffusible molecules termed autoinducers are produced constantly, including oligopeptides in Gram-positive bacteria and N acyl-homoserine lactones (AHLs) in some Gram-negative bacteria.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> At a certain threshold concentration, the binding of the autoinducers and the cognate receptors will induce a cascade of reactions and modulate the expression of QS target genes in the organism.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> It has been shown that the QS phenomenon exists widely in bacteria and links to various biological activities including motility, conjugation, biofilm formation, production of virulence factors, and pathogenic processes.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The QS system of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> has recently been reported to consist of AbaI/AbaR, a two-component system.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> The <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene encodes the autoinducer synthases which catalyze the synthesis of AHL signals. The most predominant AHLs produced by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> is 3-hydroxy-C12-homoserine lactones.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene encodes the receptor protein which binds to AHLs and behaves as transcriptional regulatory factors. Current studies showed that the mutation of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene could result in a greatly reduction of biofilm formation.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Some strategies that inhibit quorum sensing also strongly inhibited <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> motility and biofilm formation.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> However, up to date, little is known about the association between the QS system and the resistance and virulence of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates. The objectives of this study were to determine the presence of the AbaI/AbaR QS system in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates and its effects on antimicrobial resistance and virulence-associated features. This will help to understand the potential roles of the QS system of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> in the regulation of various biological activities and to develop alternative strategies targeting the QS network to combat the infections caused by this notorious pathogen.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Bacterial Strains and Culture Conditions</title><p>Eighty clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were collected from six hospitals representing three provinces in northeastern China extending from January 2012 until December 2017. The isolates were obtained from various departments including Respiration, Neurosurgery, Pediatrics, Intensive Care Units, and Emergencies. All clinical isolates were identified to the species level using the Vitek-2 system (bioMérieux, Marcyl’Etoile, France), and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-51</sub> was amplified by using PCR to confirm the presence of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Luria Bertani (LB) broth and LB agar plates (both from Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) were used to culture the bacterial isolates under aerobic conditions at 37 °C. <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC25922 and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC27853 were used as reference strains for susceptibility testing; <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC17978 was used as a control strain for virulence tests.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing</title><p>Antimicrobial susceptibility testing of the isolated strains was performed according to the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute guidelines (CLSI, 2016) using the disc diffusion method. We tested the susceptibility of the isolates to piperacillin, ampicillin, ampicillin-sulbactam, piperacillin-tazobactam, ticarcillin-clavulanic acid, ceftazidime, cefepime, cefotaxime, ceftriaxone, imipenem, meropenem, gentamicin, tobramycin, amikacin, minocycline, ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin, and polymyxin B discs (Oxoid, UK). The drug susceptibility data for the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were analyzed using WHONET 5.6. Multi-drug resistance for <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates was defined as described previously.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Detection of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> Genes</title><p>The presence of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and a<italic toggle="yes">baR</italic> genes in clinical isolates was detected by conventional PCR using the primers as following, abaI-F: 5ʹ-AAAGTTACCGCTACAGGG-3ʹ, abaI-R: 5ʹ-CACGATGGGCACGAAA-3ʹ; abaR-F: 5ʹ-TCCTCGGGTCCCAATA-3ʹ, abaR-R: 5ʹ-TAAATCTACCGCATCAA-3ʹ. The PCR program was as follows: 30 cycles of denaturation at 94 °C for 1 min, annealing at 52 °C for 30 s, and extension at 72 °C for 1.5 min, with a final elongation step at 72 °C for 5 min. The PCR products were detected by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. The amplicon sizes of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and a<italic toggle="yes">baR</italic> genes were 435 bp and 310 bp, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>N-Acyl Homoserine Lactone (AHL) Production by Clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> Isolates</title><p>AHL-producing bacteria were screened by using two AHL-sensing bacterial biosensors, <italic toggle="yes">Chromobacterium violaceum</italic> CV026<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> and <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> KYC55,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> which respond to short-chain and long-chain AHLs, respectively, as described previously.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Briefly, fresh cultures of QS biosensor strains were inoculated on LB agar plates. KYC55 was grown in LB medium supplemented with 100 μg/mL tetracycline and 100 μg/mL spectinomycin at 28 °C. CV026 was grown in LB medium supplemented with 20 μg/mL kanamycin at 28 °C. For both KYC55 and CV026, the agar was supplemented with 40 mg/mL X-gal (Sangon Biotech, Shanghai, China). Freshly cultured strains to be tested were streaked on the plates parallel to the biosensor strains. The plates were incubated overnight at 28 °C. Production of AHLs was indicated by the formation of the purple pigment, violacein, or by blue coloration due to β-galactosidase activity.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Biofilm Formation Assay</title><p>The quantification of biofilm formation was performed using 96-well microtiter plates in accordance with the method of Stepanovic et al,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> but with minor modifications. Briefly, an overnight culture of an <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolate was suspended in sterile saline to achieve turbidity comparable to that of a 0.5 McFarland standard. Twenty microliters of the suspension were pipetted into each well of a 96-well microtiter plate (Corning, Corning, NY, USA) and mixed with 180 μL of LB medium. Negative control wells contained only 200 μL of sterile LB medium. The plates were incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. Then, the supernatant was carefully removed from the wells, and each well was washed three times with 200 μL of sterile saline. The plates were dried overnight at room temperature and then fixed with hot air at 65 °C for 1 h. The plates were stained with 150 μL of 1% crystal violet for 30 min. Excess dye was rinsed off with running tap water and dried at room temperature. Glacial acetic acid (150 μL, 33% (v/v)) was added to each well to resolubilize the dye bound to the adherent cells. The optical density (OD) of each well was measured at 600 nm using a spectrophotometer (Epoch, BioTek, CA, USA). Three independent experiments were performed, each in triplicate, and biofilms quantified as nonadherent, weakly adherent, moderately adherent, or strongly adherent.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The average value of three parallel test negative controls was considered as the ODC. Isolates were classified as follows: OD ≤ ODC  = nonadherent (-), ODC &lt; OD ≤ (2 × ODC)  = weakly adherent (+); (2 × ODC) &lt; OD ≤ (4 × ODC)  = moderately adherent (++), and OD &gt; (4 × ODC)  = strongly adherent (+++).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Measurement of Surface Motility</title><p>Surface motility of these clinical isolates was measured according to a previously described method,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> but with minor modifications. Overnight cultures of each strain were adjusted to a concentration of 1 × 10<sup>7</sup> colony forming units (CFUs)/mL in LB broth. One microliter of the bacterial suspension was placed in the center of a motility assay plate containing 10 g/L tryptone, 5 g/L NaCl, and 0.3% Noble agar (Becton Dickinson, Sparks, MD, USA). Plates were allowed to dry at room temperature for 1–2 h and then incubated at 37 ºC for 24 h. The radii of surface extension were measured. All assays were performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>A549 Adhesion and Invasion Assays</title><p>The A549 human alveolar epithelial cell line (ATCC CCL-185) was routinely cultured in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM, Hyclone) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS, Gibco), 50 U/mL of penicillin, and 50 μg/mL of streptomycin. Cells were grown to 90% confluence in six well plates to get a monolayer of ~10<sup>5</sup> cells per well. The monolayers were washed three times with PBS prewarmed to 37 °C before infection. Clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were grown overnight in LB medium at 37 °C, washed in PBS, and adjusted to a multiplicity of infection of 10. Approximately 5 × 10<sup>5</sup> A549 cells were infected with 5 × 10<sup>6</sup> bacteria. The infected cells were incubated with DMEM without FBS and antibiotics in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere at 37 °C for 2 h. To determine bacterial adhesion, the infected monolayers were washed three times with PBS and then lysed in 500 μL of 0.1% Triton X-100. For invasion analysis, 500 μg/mL of gentamicin was added to each well for a 30-min incubation to eliminate all extracellular bacteria. Cells were washed three times with PBS and then lysed in 500 μL Triton X-100 to release the invaded bacteria from the infected A549 cells. After lysis in both cases, dilutions of the lysates were plated on LB agar and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h to measure the CFUs of bacteria. All invasion and adhesion assays were performed in three independent experiments, each in triplicates.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008"><title><italic toggle="yes">Galleria melonella</italic> Infection and Killing Assays</title><p>The virulence of the clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was evaluated using <italic toggle="yes">Galleria melonella</italic> as an in vivo infection model. Clinical strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were cultured to the exponential (logarithmic) growth phase and washed 2–3 times with PBS. The concentration was adjusted to match the turbidity of 0.5 McFarland standard with PBS. Ten randomly selected larvae of the same size were used to test the virulence of each bacterial strain. Twenty microliters of the culture of each strain were injected into the left or right hind leg of the larvae. Thus, the actual inoculum of each strain was about 3×10<sup>6</sup> CFU/larva. Ten larvae were injected with 20 μL of PBS as control, and ten untreated larvae were used as blank controls. After the injection, the larvae were incubated in a dark environment at 37 °C for 7 days. A larva was considered to be dead if it could not respond to gentle probing.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2009"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The variance of mean values between the two groups was compared using Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t-</italic>test. Qualitative data were analyzed using chi-square and Fisher’s exact test. The resulting survival curves were plotted using the Kaplan-Meier method (Kaplan and Meier, 1958) and analyzed using a log-rank (Mantel-Cox) test. For all tests, the difference was considered to be statistically significant at P &lt; 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2010"><title>Ethical Statement</title><p>All the clinical samples included in this study were part of the routine hospital laboratory procedure. Due to the anonymous nature of the study, no written informed consent was required.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Detection of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> Genes and AHL Production</title><p>All 80 isolates were investigated for the presence of QS genes (<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes), and the results showed that 83.75% (n=67) and 78.75% (n=63) of the isolates carried the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes, respectively (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Furthermore, the ability of these isolates to produce AHL signaling molecules was determined by using two AHL-sensing biosensor strains. A total of 24 isolates were determined to be AHL-producing strains based on color changes produced by the reporter strain, <italic toggle="yes">A. tumefaciens</italic> KYC55, which mainly responds to long-chain AHLs. No strain could induce the color change produced by CV026, which indicates that no short-chain AHLs were produced by any of the isolates.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> Genes in 80 Clinical Isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive Numbers</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive Rates (n=80)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaI<sup>+</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.75%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaR<sup>+</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.75%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaI<sup>+</sup> abaR<sup>+</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.25%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaI<sup>+</sup> abaR<sup>−</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaI<sup>−</sup> abaR<sup>+</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaI<sup>−</sup> abaR<sup>−</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.75%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Antimicrobial Susceptibility</title><p>A total of 80 clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains were tested for susceptibility to various antibiotics (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). We found that the resistance rates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> to β-lactam drugs were as high as 63.75%–91.25%, among which the highest resistance rate of 91.25% was observed for ampicillin. Resistance rates for carbapenems were 67.5% (meropenem) and 65% (imipenem). <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> also developed severe resistance to aminoglycoside antibiotics: 61.25% for gentamicin, 56.25% for tobramycin, and 52.5% for amikacin. The resistance rates to quinolone antibiotics also exceeded 50%: 67.5% for ciprofloxacin and 51.25% for levofloxacin. However, the resistance rate of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> to tetracyclines was relatively low (11.25%). All strains were sensitive to the polypeptide antibiotic, polymyxin B. Among these 80 strains, 64 were identified as MDR strains according to the definition of Magiorakos.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref> shows the numbers of sensitive and resistant isolates carrying the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes. Among the strains carrying the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene, 82.09% were drug-resistant, whereas only 23.07% were drug-resistant among the strains without the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene. Among the strains carrying the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene, drug-resistant strains accounted for 81.25%, whereas those without the <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> gene only accounted for 37.50%. Correlation analysis revealed that the carrying status of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes was significantly correlated with the drug resistance of the isolates (P &lt; 0.01).<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Antibiotic Susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> Clinical Isolates</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial Agent</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistant<break/>n (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate<break/>n (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Susceptible<break/>n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (76.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (13.75)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (91.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.75)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin-sulbactam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (63.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (30)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin-tazobactam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (68.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (22.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ticarcillin-clavulanic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (26.25)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (71.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (25)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefepime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (72.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (26.25)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefotaxime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (16.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.75)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftriaxone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (71.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (18.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.75)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imipenem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (67.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (32.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meropenem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (32.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (61.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (37.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobramycin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (56.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (41.25)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (52.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (45)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minocycline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (78.75)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (67.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (32.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levofloxacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (51.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (38.75)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymyxin B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (100)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Correlation between drug resistance and carrier status of QS genes, (<bold>A</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and (<bold>B</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes in clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-13-4273-g0001.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Biofilm Formation</title><p>Based on the quantification data, the isolates were classified as strong, moderate, and weak biofilm producers or as non-biofilm producers. Among all 80 clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, 76 strains were able to form biofilms. Moreover, 45% of the isolates were strong biofilm producers, and 27.5% and 17.5% exhibited moderate and weak biofilm formation, respectively. There were 4 non-biofilm producers. We also analyzed the relationship between biofilm formation and the production of QS signaling molecules (AHLs). Strains producing AHLs showed a slightly higher ability to form biofilms; however, no significant difference was observed compared with the non-AHL-producing group.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Surface Motility</title><p>A total of 80 clinical isolates and ATCC 17978 were tested for surface motility on LB Noble agar plates (0.3%). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>, the motility exhibited by these strains was highly variable. Five clinical strains, A41, A37, A38, A79, and A76, and ATCC17978 exhibited apparent surface motility. The motility diameters are shown in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The other isolates were either noticeably less motile than the above strains or did not exhibit any motility. It is noteworthy that all five clinical strains exhibiting surface-associated motility carried the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes and produced AHLs.<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Five Clinical Isolates with Apparent Surface Motility</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug Sensitivity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHLs</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> Gene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> Gene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biofilm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motility Diameter (mm)*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 ± 2.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.51 ± 2.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.18 ± 2.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.98 ±11.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.57 ± 5.93</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: *values are mean ± S.D. (standard deviation).</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IC, international clone; MDR, multiple drug resistant; AHLs, N-acyl-homoserine lactones.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Surface-related motility of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates. ATCC17978 was used as a positive control to show surface motility. Five clinical strains A41, A37, A38, A79, and A76 showed apparent surface motility; A5 was used as a representative clinical strain without motility. DH5α was used as a negative control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-13-4273-g0002.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Adherence and Invasion into A549 Cells</title><p>A549 human type 2 alveolar epithelial cells were used to examine the adherence and invasiveness of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates. All 80 isolates exhibited different degrees of adherence and invasion into the A549 cells. Interestingly, strains carrying <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes or producing AHLs displayed significantly higher levels of invasion into A549 cells compared with strains without the QS genes or without the ability to produce signaling molecules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>).<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Correlation of invasiveness into A549 cells with carrier status of QS genes, (<bold>A</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and (<bold>B</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, and with (<bold>C</bold>) AHLs production in clinical <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates.*Means statistically significant and p &lt;0.05; **Means statistically significant and p &lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-13-4273-g0003.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>Virulence to <italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic></title><p><italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> was used as an infection model to evaluate the virulence of 80 isolates in vivo. Injection of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates resulted in larval death at 24 or 48 h post-inoculation. No larva death occurred within 7 days in the PBS and blank groups. We compared the survival of <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> infected with AHL-producing (AHL<sup>+</sup>) and non-producing isolates (AHL<sup>−</sup>) and found that the AHL<sup>+</sup> group induced significantly greater mortality of <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> than did the AHL<sup>−</sup> group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>). This suggested that the virulence of AHL-producing <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates was significantly higher than that of non-producing isolates.<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Kaplan–Meier survival curves of <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates. AHL-producing <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> induced significantly greater mortality than did non-AHL-producing <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (P&lt;0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IDR-13-4273-g0004.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>QS has been described as a general mechanism for regulating many biological processes including virulence, resistance, motility, and biofilm formation in many gram-negative pathogens.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> At present, there are few research reports on the presence of the QS system in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates and its contribution to antibiotic resistance and virulence. In this study, we determined the carrier status of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates and found that 76.25% of the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains carried both <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes, among which 24 strains were found to produce AHLs, based on responses by biosensor strains. Some studies have proved that the presence of QS systems significantly correlates with drug resistance of isolates. Dou et al,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> found that N-3-hydroxy-dodecanoyl-homoserine lactone (N-3-OH-C12-HSL) produced by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> could induce the expression of drug-resistance genes such as <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-51</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>AmpC</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">adeA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">adeB</italic>. Our study revealed that the presence of <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes significantly correlated with multidrug resistance rates, which means that isolates with a QS system were more likely to be multidrug-resistant strains. This suggests that AbaI/AbaR QS systems are involved in antibiotic resistance and may be an important target for treating multidrug‑resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections.</p><p>Biofilm formation has been considered to be important for the colonization of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> on biological and abiotic surfaces and closely related to the multidrug-resistant phenotypes of microorganisms through the obstruction of antibiotic effects on the bacteria. Our study found that most of the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> strains analyzed herein showed an impressive ability to form biofilms on abiotic surfaces. However, the data obtained in this study did not reveal a strong correlation between biofilm formation and the QS system. This result based on clinical strains was not consistent with the results of previous studies using mutant strains. Niu et al constructed an <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> mutant strain and found that biofilm formation by the mutant strain was significantly reduced.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Phenomenon of biofilm formation is not determined by any single factor or single genotype, but is a complex biological process that is regulated by several factors and these factors seem to be strain-dependent.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Similar inconsistent or contradictory results also appeared in the study of the correlation between biofilm formation and drug resistance phenotype.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Further in vitro and in vivo studies are required to clarify the contribution of QS systems to biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii.</italic></p><p>Previously, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> was thought to be a non-motile bacterium because it has no flagellum structure. But in recent years, many studies have found that some clinical and environmental <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates exhibit a robust surface motility on low-percentage agar plates.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> In this study, we analyzed the motility of 80 clinical isolates and found that five strains exhibited apparent surface-related motility, whereas others were less motile or non-motile. In addition, all five strains carried <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> genes and produced AHL signaling molecules. A previous study demonstrated that a null allele in the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> decreased motility dramatically, and the addition of exogenous N-(3-hydroxy)-dodecanoyl homoserine lactone (N-3-OH-C12-HSL) restored the motility of the <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> mutant.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> To further analyze the roles of these genes, we knocked out <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic> or both of them and found that the mutant strains were non-motile (data not shown). Currently, the surface-associated motility of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> appears to rely on the synthesis of 1.3‑diaminopropane (DAP),<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> the production of core lipopolysaccharide<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> and response to blue light.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Some genes required for motility has been shown strongly activated through quorum sensing,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> which suggests that the AbaI/AbaR QS system is important for the surface motility of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii.</italic></p><p>The adhesion and invasion of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> into epithelial cells are key factors in the colonization and nosocomial infection of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. In this study, 80 <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates displayed different abilities to adhere to epithelial cells and subsequently invade them. In particular, those strains carrying the QS system demonstrated stronger invasiveness with respect to epithelial cells. Nesse et al,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> reported that the addition of AHLs increased the invasiveness of wild <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella typhimurium</italic> strain into epithelial cells. In <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, it was found that 3O-C12-HSL could alter the integrity of the cell barrier,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> disrupt cell junction associations,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> further trigger multiple signaling pathways, and regulate various functions and behaviors of eukaryotic host cells.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p><p><italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> has been used to assess the virulence of isolates and compare the pathogenicity between strains and has proved to have good correlation with mammalian models.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> In this study, the pathogenicity of all 80 clinical isolates was assessed using <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> as an infection model; marked differences were displayed between isolates, which reflected the different levels of pathogenicity of clinical isolates to the host. Furthermore, we found that AHL-positive isolates were more virulent than AHL-negative isolates. This result suggests that the QS system may be involved in the pathogenic process of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. The virulence of QS mutants, including the lasI mutant, rhlI mutant, or lasI rhlI double mutant, decreased significantly compared to that of the parent in <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> in many different animal models. However, the exact role of the AbaI/AbaR QS system in the pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> requires further investigation.</p><p>In this study, the AbaI/AbaR QS system was found to be widely distributed among the <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> clinical isolates, which was evidently correlated with bacterial resistance, invasiveness into epithelial cells, and pathogenicity to <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic>. This study highlights the promise of a new strategy of interfering with the AbaI/AbaR signaling system, which can help to control the infections caused by MDR <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. However, elucidation of the QS network for the regulation of antimicrobial resistance and virulence of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> at the molecular and cellular levels is necessary for the application of this new strategy.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We appreciate Ayush Kumar, PhD from Department of Microbiology, University of Manitoba for <italic toggle="yes">A.baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 strain. We thank the kind donation of Mingyong Zeng (Ocean University of China, China) for biosensor strains <italic toggle="yes">C. violaceum</italic> CV026 and <italic toggle="yes">A. tumefaciens</italic>A136, and Mingsheng Dong (Nanjing Agricultural University, China) for KYC55.</p></ack><sec id="s0005" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest for this work and declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magiorakos</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: an international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clinical Microbiol Infection</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03570.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gajdacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Batori</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abrok</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lazar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burian</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterization of resistance in gram-negative urinary isolates using existing and novel indicators of clinical relevance: a 10-year data analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life10020016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7175163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32054054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gajdacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burian</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Terhes</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Resistance levels and epidemiology of non-fermenting gram-negative bacteria in urinary tract infections of inpatients and outpatients (RENFUTI): A 10-Year epidemiological snapshot</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics8030143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6784256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31505817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gajdacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spengler</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of drug repurposing in the development of novel antimicrobial drugs: non-antibiotic pharmacological agents as quorum sensing-inhibitors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics8040270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6963710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31861228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bassler</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing in bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.55.1.165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bassler</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing: cell-to-cell communication in bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.21.012704.131001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16212498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Papenfort</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bassler</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing signal-response systems in Gram-negative bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2016.89</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27510864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5056591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmer</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of an autoinducer synthase from Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3386</fpage>–<lpage>3392</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01929-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2347373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Erdonmez</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rad</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aksoz</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing molecules production by nosocomial and soil isolates Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>199</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1325</fpage>–<lpage>1334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-017-1408-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28688010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regulation of Acinetobacter baumannii biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Future Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.09.5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2724675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stacy</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Attenuation of quorum sensing in the pathogen Acinetobacter baumannii using non-native N-Acyl homoserine lactones</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ACS Chem Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1719</fpage>–<lpage>1728</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cb300351x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22853441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3477293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo-Juarez</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Jacome</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soberon-Chavez</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exploiting quorum sensing inhibition for the control of pseudomonas aeruginosa and acinetobacter baumannii biofilms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Top Med Chem</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1915</fpage>–<lpage>1927</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1568026617666170105144104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28056745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McClean</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winson</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fish</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quorum sensing and Chromobacterium violaceum: exploitation of violacein production and inhibition for the detection of N-acylhomoserine lactones</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>143</volume>(<issue>Pt 12</issue>):<fpage>3703</fpage>–<lpage>3711</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-143-12-3703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9421896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winans</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Agrobacterium bioassay strain for ultrasensitive detection of N-acylhomoserine lactone-type quorum-sensing molecules: detection of autoinducers in Mesorhizobium huakuii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Environ Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>6949</fpage>–<lpage>6953</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.11.6949-6953.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14602662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC262303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ravn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Molin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Givskov</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gram</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Methods for detecting acylated homoserine lactones produced by Gram-negative bacteria and their application in studies of AHL-production kinetics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Microbiol Methods</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-7012(01)00217-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11240047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gajdacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spengler</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Standard operating procedure (SOP) for disk diffusion-based quorum sensing inhibition assays</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Pharm Hung</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33892/aph.2019.89.117-125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Characteristics of N-Acylhomoserine lactones produced by hafnia alvei H4 isolated from spoiled instant sea cucumber</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sensors</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s17040772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5422045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28379194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vukovic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dakic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Savic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Svabic-Vlahovic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A modified microtiter-plate test for quantification of staphylococcal biofilm formation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Microbiol Methods</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-7012(00)00122-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10699673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Basson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flemming</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chenia</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of adherence, hydrophobicity, aggregation, and biofilm development of Flavobacterium johnsoniae-like isolates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Ecol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-007-9245-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17401596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carretero-Ledesma</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Quintanilla</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Pena</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pulido</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pachon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McConnell</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phenotypic changes associated with Colistin resistance due to Lipopolysaccharide loss in Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Virulence</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>930</fpage>–<lpage>942</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2018.1460187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29638177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5955468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acinetobacter baumannii quorum-sensing signalling molecule induces the expression of drug-resistance genes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Med Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>4061</fpage>–<lpage>4068</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/mmr.2017.6528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28487993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5436197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hennon</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Uncovering the mechanisms of Acinetobacter baumannii virulence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29249812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6571207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Behzadi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gajdacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between biofilm-production and antibiotic resistance in uropathogenic Escherichia coli (UPEC): an in vitro study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diseases</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diseases8020017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7348726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32517335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tracy</surname>
<given-names>EN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carruthers</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Actis</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Munson</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>. <article-title>Acinetobacter baumannii strain M2 produces type IV pili which play a role in natural transformation and twitching motility but not surface-associated motility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mBio</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00360-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3735195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23919995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skiebe</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Berardinis</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morczinek</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Surface-associated motility, a common trait of clinical isolates of Acinetobacter baumannii, depends on 1,3-diaminopropane</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Med Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>302</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmm.2012.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22560766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmer</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Genetic analysis of surface motility in Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>Pt 9</issue>):<fpage>2534</fpage>–<lpage>2544</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.049791-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3352170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McQueary</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkup</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Extracellular stress and lipopolysaccharide modulate Acinetobacter baumannii surface-associated motility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12275-012-1555-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22752907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mussi</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cabruja</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The opportunistic human pathogen Acinetobacter baumannii senses and responds to light</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bacteriol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>192</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>6336</fpage>–<lpage>6345</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00917-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3008525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Varela</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Corral</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aranda</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barbe</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Roles of efflux pumps from different superfamilies in the surface-associated motility and virulence of acinetobacter baumannii ATCC 17978</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02190-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6395914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30642939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nesse</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vestby</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Olsaker</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Djonne</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Salmonella Typhimurium invasion of HEp-2 epithelial cells in vitro is increased by N-acylhomoserine lactone quorum sensing signals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Vet Scand</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1751-0147-53-44</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21711544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3141561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vikstrom</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Konradsson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The junctional integrity of epithelial cells is modulated by Pseudomonas aeruginosa quorum sensing molecule through phosphorylation-dependent mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Cell Res</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>315</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2008.10.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19038248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vikstrom</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Konradsson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of calcium signalling and phosphorylations in disruption of the epithelial junctions by Pseudomonas aeruginosa quorum sensing molecule</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejcb.2010.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20434232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Holm</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vikstrom</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing communication between bacteria and human cells: signals, targets, and functions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Plant Sci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2014.00309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25018766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4071818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peleg</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jara</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Monga</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eliopoulos</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moellering</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mylonakis</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Galleria mellonella as a model system to study Acinetobacter baumannii pathogenesis and therapeutics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2605</fpage>–<lpage>2609</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01533-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2687231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Iglewski</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prince</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa cell-to-cell signaling is required for virulence in a model of acute pulmonary infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Immun</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>4331</fpage>–<lpage>4334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.68.7.4331-4334.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC101761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DiMango</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bryan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Contribution of specific Pseudomonas aeruginosa virulence factors to pathogenesis of pneumonia in a neonatal mouse model of infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Immun</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.64.1.37-43.1996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8557368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC173724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>