<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1524</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontpharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Pharmacol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1663-9812</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10097947</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10097947.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10097947</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10097947</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37063277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2023.1135180</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1135180</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of traditional Chinese medicine monomers interfering with quorum-sensing on virulence factors of extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>
</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Zeng et al.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2023.1135180" ext-link-type="uri">10.3389/fphar.2023.1135180</ext-link>
</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="L">Li</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2156837/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="F">Fei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/447080/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names initials="B">Baodong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/451914/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>School of Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>Chengdu Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>The Third People’s Hospital of Yibin</institution>, <addr-line>Yibin</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Department of Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>The First Affiliated Hospital of Chengdu Medical College</institution>, <institution>Chengdu Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>
<bold>Edited by:</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1891839/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Karunakaran Kalesh</ext-link>, Teesside University, United Kingdom</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>
<bold>Reviewed by:</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1136921/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Karthikeyan Sivashanmugam</ext-link>, VIT University, India</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/520539/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Prasun Kumar</ext-link>, Chungbuk National University, Republic of Korea</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Baodong Ling, <email>lingbaodong@cmc.edu.cn</email>
</corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>This article was submitted to Pharmacology of Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Pharmacology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427358</issue-id><elocation-id>1135180</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-17 13:10:13.310"><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2023 Zeng, Lin and Ling.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zeng, Lin and Ling</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fphar-14-1135180.pdf"/><abstract><p>The antimicrobial resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>) clinical isolates has emerged as a great threat to public health. Quorum sensing (QS) is one of the resistance mechanisms for drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>. Interfering with QS is a promising strategy to combat infections caused by drug-resistant bacteria. This study explored the QS inhibition ability of thirty-four traditional Chinese medicine monomers (TCMMs) and assessed the effect of QS inhibitors (QSIs) on the virulence factors of twelve extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (XDRAB) strains. Nine traditional Chinese medicine monomers, such as caffeic acid, cinnamic acid, and myricetin, were found to be able to inhibit the bacterial QS. Then, at 1/8 of the minimal inhibitory concentration, we found that these QSIs inhibited extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> adhesion and biofilm formation and downregulated the expression levels of virulence-associated genes (<italic toggle="yes">abaI, abaR, csuE, pgaA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>). In conclusion, nine traditional Chinese medicine monomers have QS inhibitory activity and may downregulate QS genes to interfere with the QS system, which could inhibit the expression of extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> virulence factors. These results suggest that traditional Chinese medicine monomers could develop as novel anti-virulence compounds to control extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> infections.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>traditional Chinese medicine monomer</kwd><kwd>extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>
</kwd><kwd>quorum sensing inhibitor</kwd><kwd>virulence factor</kwd><kwd>quorum sensing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 81373454).</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>1 Introduction</title><p>Extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> (XDRAB) is a superbug-bacteria responsible for nosocomial infections in hospitals through strong intrinsic and acquired resistance mechanisms (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2017</xref>), which has been listed as one of the highest-grade resistant pathogens of the ESKAPE family by the World Health Organization (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Mulani et al., 2019</xref>). In addition, the ability of XDRAB to form biofilms increased colonization and persistence in environments, leading to aggravating drug resistance and bacterial pathogenicity (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Yan and Bassler, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mohammed et al., 2020</xref>). Therefore, it is of great necessity to search for novel therapeutic strategies to combat XDRAB infections. Recent studies have revealed the key roles of drug resistance and biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, which are regulated by the quorum sensing (QS) system (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Shaaban et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">PauL et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>QS system is a process of communication between microbial cells. Bacteria coordinate their behaviors in a bacterial cell density-dependent manner through this process (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abisado et al., 2018</xref>). In <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, QS is regulated by the two-component system abaI/abaR, which is the luxI and luxR homologs of QS in Gram-negative bacteria (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Oh and Han, 2022</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> gene is responsible for the synthesis of N-acyl-homoserine lactone (AHL) signaling molecules (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Kalia, V.C., 2013</xref>), and then the QS system senses changes in bacterial cell density by signaling molecules. When the density reaches the threshold, the synthesized signaling molecules interact with the receptor abaR, resulting in a coordinated change in gene expression, which plays an important role in the production of virulence factors and antibiotic resistance (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>). Thus, interfering with the QS system is an attractive treatment against XDRAB infections by inhibiting bacterial virulence hence effectively reducing bacteria pathogenicity without inducing selective pressure resistance.</p><p>It has been reported that some synthetic chemical quorum sensing inhibitors (QSIs) like furanones and pyrrolidones, could successfully inhibit the virulence of pathogens (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">de Nys et al., 2006</xref>). However, the majority of these inhibitors are not only toxic to humans but also expensive. Hence, there is an urgent need to find economic, safe, and effective QSIs. Traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) has been used to treat infectious diseases since ancient times, and due to their low toxicity, many monomers isolated from TCM are now used as anti-virulence drugs or antibiotic adjuvants to improve therapeutic effects and safety (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Guzzo et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2021</xref>). Therefore, it may be a better choice to search for effective QSIs from traditional Chinese medicine monomers (TCMMs)<italic toggle="yes">.</italic>
</p><p>In this study, we sought to investigate the QS inhibition ability of thirty-four TCMMs, as well as the effect of TCMMs on virulence factors of XDRAB measured by adhesion ability, biofilm formation ability and the expression of virulence factor-related genes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>2 Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>2.1 Bacterial strains</title><p>Twelve isolates of XDRAB were derived from the bacterial specimens of patients from the critical care units, internal medicine, and emergency departments at the First Affiliated Hospital of Chengdu Medical College from 2018 to 2020 (Chengdu, China). Standard laboratory methods and ATB New (BioMérieux, France) were used to identify these isolates, which were also confirmed by PCR of the genes <italic toggle="yes">16S rRNA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">blaOXA-51</italic> (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 2015</xref>); <italic toggle="yes">Chromobacterium violaceum</italic> 026 (CV026) was purchased from Biobw (Beijing, China); <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 17978 and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> DH5a were preserved in our laboratory.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>2.2 Drugs and reagents</title><p>Berberine, ferulic acid, baicalin, baicalein, ursolic acid, naringenin, hesperidin, gallic acid, malic acid, resveratrol, myricetin, vanillin, phloretin, capsaicin, osthole, andrographolide, parthenolide, magnolol, and ellagic acid were purchased from Meilun Biological (Dalian, China). Meanwhile, ampicillin, piperacillin, ampicillin sulbactam (2:1), cefoperazone sulbactam (2:1), efotaxime, ceftazidime, tetracycline, doxycycline, amikacin, gentamicin, ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin, imipenem, meropenem, tigecycline and polymyxin B were purchased from Meilun Biological (Dalian, China); Linoleic acid, kaempferol, 4-terpineol, coumarin, linalool, naringin, matrine, and cinnamaldehyde were purchased from Macklin Biochemical (Shanghai, China); Eugenol, citral, vanillin, cinnamic acid, hordenine, and nootkatone were purchased from Yuanye Biochemical (Shanghai, China); Furanone C30 and C6-HSL were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Taufkirchen, Germany); RNA isolation kit, cDNA synthesis kit, and fluorescent dye SYBR Color qPCR Master Mix were purchased from Vazyme Biological (Nanjing, China). Cation-adjusted Muller-Hinton broth (CAMHB) (Comprised of beef extract, caseins hydrolyzates, starch and calcium chloride), Luria Bertani (LB) broth medium (Comprised of tryptone, yeast extract, sodium chloride and glucose), LB agar medium (Comprised of tryptone, yeast extract, sodium chloride and agar) and tryptone soy broth (TSB) medium (Comprised of tryptone, soya peptone, sodium chloride, glucose and dipotassium hydrogen phosphate) were purchased from Haibo Biotechnology (Qingdao, China). Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and phosphate buffer saline (PBS) were purchased from Kelong Chemical (Chengdu, China).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>2.3 Minimum inhibitory concentration test</title><p>The minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) of thirty-four TCMMs for CV026 and XDRAB were determined by using the broth microdilution method. Briefly, CV026 and XDRAB were inoculated in LB agar medium at 30°C and 37°C for 16–20 h, respectively. And then resuspended in saline (0.9% sodium chloride) to produce a 0.5 McFarland turbidity standard, followed by a 20-fold dilution. TCMMs were initially dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and diluted with PBS into a series of solutions at different concentrations. CAMHB medium, bacterial suspension and TCMMs at different concentrations were added into 96-well cell culture plates in groups. The CV026 and XDRAB were incubated at 30°C and 37°C for 16–20 h, respectively. Less than OD600 of 0.1 were regarded as no bacterial growth, and colored drugs were observed macroscopically and data were recorded (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Humphries et al., 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>2.4 Quorum sensing inhibition activity assay</title><p>CV026 is used as a biosensor strain to detect anti-QS activity. A culture-activated CV026 strain (5 mL) was added to 50 mL of LB nutrient agar medium containing kanamycin and C6-HSL (final concentration of 20 μg/mL), mixed and poured well, then punched and subinhibitory TCMM concentrations were added into the wells. After 24 h of incubation at 30°C, plates were observed for the inhibition of violacein. At the same time, the culture-activated CV026 bacterial solution was added to a 6-well cell culture plate, and then LB broth medium containing kanamycin, C6-HSL, and TCMM solutions with subinhibitory concentrations were added. 0.9% normal saline was used as the blank control, and furanone C30 was used as the positive control. After 24 h of incubation at 30°C, 1 mL of the bacterial solution from each well was centrifuged (13,000 g, 5 min) and DMSO was added to the cell pellets to dissolve violacein pigment. Supernatants (containing dissolved violacein) were transferred to a 96-well cell culture plate, and the absorbances were measured at 585 nm (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Lou et al., 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>2.5 Growth curve test</title><p>Taking the 96-well cell culture plate, 170 μL TSB medium was added into each well, and then diluted bacterial solution and TCMMs solution with the different concentrations (1 MIC, 1/2 MIC, 1/4 MIC, and 1/8 MIC) were added. The value of OD<sub>570</sub> was measured after incubation at 37°C every 6 h. The growth curves of XDRAB within 24 h were plotted, respectively. Concentrations that did not affect bacterial growth were finally selected as subsequent working concentrations (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Aranda et al., 2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>2.6 Effect on adhesion</title><p>Twelve activated XDRAB strains were diluted 1:1,000 and added into confocal dishes, then 1 mL of working concentration TCMMs were added to each well and incubated at 37°C for 4 h. After rinsing twice with PBS and sonicating for 10 min, PBS was added again to detach the bacteria adhering to the culture dish. 100 μL of detached bacteria were diluted 10-fold and spread on LB plates and cultured at 37°C for 24 h before counting. The relative value method (lg10 (N×10 × 1,000)) was used to assess the effect of TCMMs on XDRAB adhesion (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>2.7 Effect on biofilm formation</title><p>We performed biofilm formation assays using crystal violet. Briefly, using the 96-well cell culture plate, 170 μL of TSB medium and 10 μL of PBS (control group) or TCMM solution at the working concentration were added into each well, followed by the inoculation of 20 μL of bacterial suspension (OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.12). <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> DH5a was used as a negative control and six replicate wells were set for each strain. The plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 h, then the wells were voided and washed three times with PBS. After complete dryness, 0.1% crystal violet was added for staining for 20 min, then PBS was washed three times, dried in air for 30 min, dissolved in 95% ethanol for 15 min, and finally, the absorbance at 570 nm was measured (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Farshadzadeh et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>2.8 Effect on the expression of genes related to QS and virulence factors</title><p>The effect of TCMMs on XDRAB QS-regulated genes and virulence factor-related genes <italic toggle="yes">abaR, abaI, csuE, bap,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic> was investigated by quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR), the gene primer sequences are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The <italic toggle="yes">16S rRNA</italic> gene was used for the internal standard of mRNA quantification, and the expression levels of virulence factor genes were detected using the fluorescent dye SYBR Color qPCR Master Mix. According to the kit instructions, RNA was extracted and reverse transcribed into cDNA, followed by a 20 μL system used for the reaction. The cycling conditions of qRT-PCR were as follows: pre-denaturation at 95°C for 3 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 s and 60°C for 5 s. The expression level of each gene was normalized and the relative expression was calculated as 2<sup>−ΔΔCT</sup>. Fold changes in gene expression from TCMM-treated cells were compared to untreated cells that were propagated under the same conditions (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Navidifar et al., 2022</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Primer sequence.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene primers</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer (5'→3′)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">16S rRNA</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAG​CTC​GTG​TCG​TGA​GAT​GT</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGT​AAG​GGC​CAT​GAT​GAC​TT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAC​TGC​TAG​AGG​AAG​GCG​GAT​TTG</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGA​CTA​CTA​CCC​ACC​ACA​CAA​CCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAA​ATG​TCG​GTT​GGG​CTC​AGT​CAA​G</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCT​GGA​ATG​CAC​TGT​TTG​AGT​CAA​C</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCA​GAC​CGG​AGA​AAA​ACT​TAA​CG</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCC​GGA​AGC​CGT​ATG​TAG​AA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAT​GCA​CCG​GTA​CTT​GAT​CC</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAT​TGC​CTG​CAG​GGT​CAG​TT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCCGACGGTCGCGATAC</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATG​CAC​ATC​ACC​AAA​ACG​GTA​CT</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">16S rRNA</italic> were designed and synthesized by Sangon Biotech (Shanghai) Co., Ltd. Genes <italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic> were referred to the literature (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Navidifar et al., 2022</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>2.9 Statistical analysis</title><p>The mean and standard deviation of the mean were calculated using SPSS 26.0. GraphPad Prism 8.0 was used for mapping. The statistical analysis of the data was performed using the Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test to compare the treated group with the control group. Data was considered significant when <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>3 Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>3.1 Anti-bacterial activity of TCMMs</title><p>The MIC of thirty-four TCMMs against strain CV026 ranged from 16 to 1,024 μg/mL (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Cinnamic aldehyde, carvacrol, and resveratrol showed obvious antibacterial activity, and the MICs were 32 μg/mL, 32 μg/mL and 16 μg/mL, respectively. The MIC of furanone C30 was 64 μg/mL. Twelve isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> were susceptible to polymyxin B or tigecycline, but resistant to other antimicrobial agents, including aminoglycosides, carbapenems, cephalosporins, fluoroquinolones, and tetracyclines (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Such resistance profiles classified these isolates as XDRAB.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>MICs of 34 TCMMs against CV026.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCMMs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC (μg/mL)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCMMs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC (μg/mL)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCMMs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC (μg/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caffeic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naringenin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myricetin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Berberine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naringin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vanillin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferulic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hordenine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baicalin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phloretin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baicalein</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hesperidin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capsaicin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ursolic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citral</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osthole</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linoleic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamic aldehyde</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nootkatone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carvacrol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andrographolide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-Terpineol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parthenolide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coumarin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnolol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resveratrol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ellagic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eugenol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Furanone C30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>TCMMs, traditional Chinese medicine monomers; CV026, <italic toggle="yes">Chromobacterium violaceum</italic> 026; MIC, minimal inhibitory concentration; Furanone C30, drug control.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>MICs of 16 antibacterial agents against 12 clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1" align="center">Antibacterial agents</th><th colspan="14" align="center" rowspan="1">MIC (μg/mL)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">AB1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB2</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB3</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB4</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB5</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB6</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB7</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB8</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB9</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB10</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB11</th><th colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">AB12</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;1,024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,024</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;512</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefotaxime</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin/sulbactam</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefoperazone/sulbactam</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;512</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;32</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levofloxacin</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracycline</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;128</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doxycycline</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meropenem</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imipenem</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tigecycline</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymyxin B</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>3.2 Quorum sensing inhibition activity of TCMMs</title><p>Thirty-four TCMMs showed different effects on the QS activity of CV026 (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Twenty-one TCMMs, including coumarin, 4-terpineol, and hordenine, formed turbid inhibition circles on purple plates and showed different degrees of QS inhibition effects, which belonged to QS activity inhibitors. In contrast, the remaining thirteen TCMMs and blank controls did not form turbid or only transparent diaphragms, indicating no QS inhibitory activity. Thus, twenty-one of thirty-four TCMMs showed different degrees of QS inhibitory activity.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Effect of 34 TCMMs on QS activity of CV026.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCMMs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QS activity</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCMMs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QS activity</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCMMs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QS activity</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-Terpineol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hordenine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caffeic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnolol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ellagic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coumarin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carvacrol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vanillin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parthenolide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myricetin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naringenin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baicalein</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nootkatone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resveratrol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eugenol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phloretin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osthole</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Berberine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hesperidin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andrographolide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linoleic Acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferulic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baicalin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capsaicin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citral</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamic aldehyde</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naringin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ursolic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>QS, Quorum sensing; +, QS inhibitory activity; —, No QS inhibitory activity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Nine of twenty-one TCMMs could inhibit violacein production to varying degrees at sub-inhibitory concentrations and decrease in a concentration-dependent manner (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Caffeic acid, vanillin, cinnamic acid, matrine, hordenine, kaempferol, coumarin, 4-terpineol, and myricetin showed relatively obvious QS inhibitory activity, with significant differences at the concentrations of both 1/4 MIC and 1/8 MIC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and the inhibitory effects were better than furanone C30. In addition, caffeic acid, vanillin, kaempferol, myricetin, and coumarin also showed inhibitory effects at a concentration of 1/16 MIC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Thus, nine TCMMs, including caffeic acid, vanillin, and cinnamic acid, have inhibitory effects on the QS system without affecting the normal growth of the strains, which can be regarded as potential QSIs.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Effect of 9 TCMMs on the violacein production of CV026 at 1/4, 1/8 and 1/16MIC. TCMMs, traditional Chinese medicine monomers; MIC, minimal inhibitory concentration; CV026, <italic toggle="yes">Chromobacterium violaceum</italic> 026; Furanone C30, drug control; <italic toggle="yes">**</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.01<italic toggle="yes">; *</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05<italic toggle="yes">;</italic> ns, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-14-1135180-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>3.3 Effect of TCMMs on the growth of XDRAB</title><p>The MICs of nine TCMMs against twelve XDRAB strains ranged from 256 to 2048 μg/mL. We found that myricetin, cinnamic acid, caffeic acid, vanillin, hordenine, kaempferol, matrine, coumarin, 4-terpineol, and furanone C30 did not affect the growth of bacterial cells at the 1/8 MIC concentration of 32, 256, 256, 256, 128, 64, 256, 32, 64, and 4 μg/mL, respectively. The growth curve of XDRAB by TCMMs is shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Bacterial growth curves of 12 XDRAB in the presence of 9 TCMMs at sub-MIC. Control, no TCMM; Myricetin (1/8 MIC = 32 μg/mL), cinnamic acid (1/8 MIC = 256 μg/mL), caffeic acid (1/8 MIC = 256 μg/mL), vanillin (1/8 MIC = 256 μg/mL), hordenine (1/8 MIC = 128 μg/mL), kaempferol (1/8 MIC = 64 μg/mL), matrine (1/8 MIC = 256 μg/mL), coumarin (1/8 MIC = 32 μg/mL), 4-terpineol (1/8 MIC = 64 μg/mL) and furanone C30 (1/8 MIC = 4 μg/mL). TCMMs, traditional Chinese medicine monomers; XDRAB, extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii;</italic> MIC, minimal inhibitory concentration.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-14-1135180-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>3.4 Effect of TCMMs on the adhesion of XDRAB</title><p>Nine TCMMs could inhibit the adhesion of twelve XDRAB strains to confocal dishes at a concentration of 1/8 MIC and significantly reduce the number of colonies adhering to the culture dishes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). After 1/8 MIC of kaempferol and 4-terpineol, the relative numbers of bacteria adhering to the culture dishes were 3.52 ± 0.09 and 3.70 ± 0.17, respectively, compared with 6.99 ± 0.02 in the blank control group (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Effect of 9 TCMMs on the adhesion ability of XDRAB strains at 1/8 MIC (x ± s, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12). TCMMs, traditional Chinese medicine monomers; MIC, minimal inhibitory concentration; XDRAB, extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii;</italic> **, <italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-14-1135180-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>3.5 Effect of TCMMs on the biofilm formation of XDRAB</title><p>Nine TCMMs could inhibit the biofilm formation of XDRAB to different extents. At a concentration of 1/8 MIC, 4-terpineol, coumarin, hordenine, caffeic acid, matrine, kaempferol, and vanillin could significantly inhibit the biofilm formation of XDRAB (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Myricetin, cinnamic acid, and furanone C30 had relatively weak inhibitory effects (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Overall, TCMMs showed stronger anti-biofilm effects compared with furanone C30 (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 5</label><caption><p>Effect of 9 TCMMs on the biofilm formation ability of XDRAB at 1/8 MIC (x ± s, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th colspan="1" align="center" rowspan="1">TCMMs (1/8 MIC)</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">BF ability of XDRAB (n = 12)</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Inhibition rate of BF (%)</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.58 ± 0.21</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caffeic acid</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.39 ± 0.12</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">32.41</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamic acid</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.51 ± 0.11</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">13.09</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vanillin</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.42 ± 0.10</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">27.60</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.33 ± 0.11</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">42.68</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hordenine</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.36 ± 0.08</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">38.11</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myricetin</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.51 ± 0.14</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">12.40</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrine</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.38 ± 0.10</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">35.04</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-Terpineol</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.31 ± 0.10</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">47.37</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coumarin</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.38 ± 0.07</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">34.15</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Furanone C30</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">0.46 ± 0.13</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">21.69</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">&gt;0.05</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>BF, biofilm formation; XDRAB, extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii;</italic> Furanone C30 = drug control; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value = TCMMs was compared with control.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-6"><title>3.6 Effect of TCMMs on the expression of XDRAB virulence factor-related genes</title><p>The expression levels of QS-regulated genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI, abaR</italic> and virulence factor-related genes <italic toggle="yes">csuE, bap</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic> in biofilm strongly positive strains were analyzed by qRT-PCR at a concentration of 1/8 MIC (<xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Compared with the control group, the expression levels of QS genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, pilus regulatory gene <italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic>, and biofilm-related genes <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic> were significantly decreased by the eight TCMMs at the concentration of 1/8 MIC, except coumarin, which showed no effect on the biofilm-related gene <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>. Therefore, nine TCMMs downregulated the QS-related genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI, abaR</italic> and the virulence factor-associated genes <italic toggle="yes">csuE, bap</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pgaA,</italic> except coumarin, which upregulated the gene <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 6</label><caption><p>Effect of 9 TCMMs on the virulence factor-related gene expression of XDRAB at 1/8 MIC (x ± s, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative expression</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic>
</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>
</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic>
</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">bap</italic>
</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2<sup>-△△CT</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 ± 0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 ± 0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 ± 0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 ± 0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caffeic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 ± 0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 ± 0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 ± 0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 ± 0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 ± 0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vanillin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 ± 0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 ± 0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 ± 0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 ± 0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 ± 0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamic acid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 ± 0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 ± 0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 ± 0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 ± 0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ± 0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 ± 0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 ± 0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 ± 0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 ± 0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 ± 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hordenine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 ± 0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 ± 0.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 ± 0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 ± 0.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 ± 0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myricetin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 ± 0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 ± 0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 ± 0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 ± 0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 ± 0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coumarin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 ± 0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 ± 0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 ± 0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 ± 0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 ± 0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 ± 0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 ± 0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 ± 0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 ± 0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-Terpineol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 ± 0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 ± 0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 ± 0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 ± 0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 ± 0.06</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>4 Discussion</title><p>Biofilm formation in XDRAB is closely associated with bacterial virulence and resistance (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ayoub and Hammoudi, 2020</xref>). It has been found that biofilm formation is a dynamic process regulated by various factors, in which QS plays a crucial role (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Carradori et al., 2020</xref>). QSI makes bacteria more susceptible to clearance by reducing biofilm formation, thus decreasing the virulence and drug resistance of pathogens (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Warrier et al., 2021</xref>). Hence, QS is a critical target for the design of novel antimicrobial therapeutics. Some TCMMs have been shown to inhibit QS in addition to their antimicrobial activity (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2020</xref>). In this study, the QS inhibitory activity of thirty-four TCMMs was investigated by biosensor CV026. The results revealed that twenty-one TCMMs showed different degrees of QS inhibitory activity, among which nine TCMMs, such as caffeic acid, cinnamic acid, and vanillin, had relatively obvious QS inhibitory activity. Similar to our findings, coumarin and caffeic acid have been found to interfere with the violacein production of CV026 (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">D’almeida et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Pejin et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The effect of nine TCMMs on XDRAB adhesion and biofilm formation was investigated in this study. At the concentration of 1/8 MIC, all the nine TCMMs reduced the adhesion and biofilm formation of XDRAB: adhesion ability was inhibited in a range of 25.46%–53.79%; biofilm formation ability was inhibited in a range of 12.40%–47.37%. The QS system is an important way for information exchange between bacteria and involves different stages of bacterial biofilm formation (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2020</xref>). It has been reported that coumarin affects the production of violacein from CV026 at a concentration of 100 μg/mL, followed by inhibiting the formation of biofilm in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">D’almeida et al., 2017</xref>). Similarly, kaempferol, 4-terpineol and hordenine, also showed QS and biofilm inhibition activity against other common clinical pathogenic bacteria (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Rekha et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bose et al., 2020</xref>). The results depicted that the nine TCMMs represented by 4- terpineol could inhibit the adhesion and biofilm formation of XDRAB, and these drugs might have broad anti-virulence activity. Biofilm is a component of the XDRAB resistance mechanisms (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Mirghani et al., 2022</xref>). So, the susceptibility of antimicrobial agents to bacteria can be increased by reducing biofilm formation. These results suggested that the nine TCMMs could be used as antibacterial adjuvants to increase the bactericidal effect of antibacterial drugs. Alves also found linalool to be a QSI that reduced the expression of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> virulence factors (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Alves et al., 2016</xref>). Therefore, QS is closely related to bacterial virulence, which is consistent with our research results.</p><p>We also used qRT-PCR to investigate the effect of nine TCMMs on virulence factor-related gene expression of XDRAB with strong biofilm formation ability. It has been shown that QS genes are critical regulators of biofilm formation, and various virulence factors (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Elnegery et al., 2021</xref>). QSI inhibits the expression of virulence factor-related genes in pathogens by down-regulating QS key genes (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2021</xref>). The results indicated that the nine TCMMs downregulated QS-related genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI, abaR</italic> and virulence factor-related genes <italic toggle="yes">csuE, bap</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic> except coumarin, which upregulated the <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic> gene. The <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> expression was reduced by 80.97%, 83.18%, 73.30%, and 86.22% in cultures treated with 1/8 MICs of caffeic acid, cinnamic acid, vanillin, and kaempferol, respectively. In addition, treatment with myricetin and 4-terpineol revealed a significant decrease in the expression of <italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic> by 90.10%, 84.94%, and 68.77%, 39.07%, respectively. However, coumarin upregulated the expression of <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic> by 19.80%. Therefore, by down-regulating QS genes <italic toggle="yes">abaI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">abaR</italic>, the nine TCMMs affected the expression of <italic toggle="yes">csuE</italic>, which prevented bacteria from transforming from plankton to biofilm (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">de Breij et al., 2009</xref>), and inhibited the expression of <italic toggle="yes">bap</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pgaA</italic>, which reduced bacterial adhesion and destroyed biofilm formation, followed by reducing bacterial virulence (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Farshadzadeh et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, nine TCMMs like caffeic acid, cinnamic acid, and vanillin showed QS inhibitory activity. They might interfere with the QS system and inhibit the expression of XDRAB virulence factors by inhibiting QS and virulence factor-related genes, thus reversing bacterial drug resistance and reducing pathogenicity. This could develop as novel anti-virulence compounds to control XDRAB infections.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="s11" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Materials</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>This study uses strains derived from bacteria specimens (endotracheal aspirate or respiratory lavage fluid) of patients from the critical care units, internal medicine and emergency department at the First Affiliated Hospital of Chengdu Medical College in 2018 to 2020. The Biomedical Ethics Committee of Chengdu Medical College did not require the study to be reviewed or approved by an ethics committee because this was an entirely in-vitro study of bacteria ethical review is not required.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>LZ designed and performed the experiments, and drafted the manuscript; FL contributed to the study design and revising the manuscript; BL initiated and supervised the study, and revised the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s9"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher’s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2023.1135180/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2023.1135180/full#supplementary-material</ext-link>
</p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="DataSheet1.zip" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="DataSheet2.ZIP" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abisado</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benomar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klaus</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dandekar</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Bacterial quorum sensing and microbial community interactions</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>e02331</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.02331-17</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29789364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5964356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pattnaik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ampasala</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Inhibition of quorum sensing-associated virulence factors and biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 by Mycoleptodiscus indicus PUTY1</article-title>. <source>Braz J. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>51</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>487</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42770-020-00235-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32086747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7203316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domingues</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Study of the major essential oil compounds of Coriandrum sativum against Acinetobacter baumannii and the effect of linalool on adhesion, biofilms and quorum sensing</article-title>. <source>Biofouling</source>
<volume>32</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08927014.2015.1133810</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26901586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardina</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beceiro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rumbo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbé</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Acinetobacter baumannii RecA protein in repair of DNA damage, antimicrobial resistance, general stress response, and virulence</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>193</volume> (<issue>15</issue>), <fpage>3740</fpage>–<lpage>3747</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00389-11</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21642465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3147500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammoudi</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Insights into acinetobacter baumannii: A review of microbiological, virulence, and resistance traits in a threatening nosocomial pathogen</article-title>. <source>Antibiot. (Basel)</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>119</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9030119</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7148516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32178356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhingra</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chhibber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harjai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Terpinen-4-ol attenuates quorum sensing regulated virulence factors and biofilm formation in pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol.</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb-2019-0204</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32043363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carradori</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobefalo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luisi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campestre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sisto</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Biofilm and quorum sensing inhibitors: The road so far</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin. Ther. Pat.</source>
<volume>30</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>917</fpage>–<lpage>930</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13543776.2020.1830059</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32985271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Characterization of carbapenem-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii isolates in a Chinese teaching hospital</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>910</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00910</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26388854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4555021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Baicalein inhibits <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation and the quorum sensing system <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>
</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>11</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>e0153468</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153468</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27128436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4851419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slamti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>F. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pier</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maira-Litrán</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>ThepgaABCD locus of acinetobacter baumannii encodes the production of poly-β-1-6-N-acetylglucosamine, which is critical for biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>191</volume> (<issue>19</issue>), <fpage>5953</fpage>–<lpage>5963</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00647-09</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2747904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Almeida</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>R. D. I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viola</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luciardi</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardón</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Comparison of seven structurally related coumarins on the inhibition of Quorum sensing of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and Chromobacterium violaceum</article-title>. <source>Bioorg. Chem.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bioorg.2017.05.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28599132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Breij</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Meer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koning</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Broek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>CsuA/BABCDE-dependent pili are not involved in the adherence of Acinetobacter baumannii ATCC19606T to human airway epithelial cells and their inflammatory response</article-title>. <source>Res. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>160</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2009.01.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19530313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Nys</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Givskov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjelleberg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Furanones. <italic toggle="yes">Prog. Mol. Subcell. Biol</italic>
</source>. <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/3-540-30016-3_2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16805438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elnegery</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mowafy</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahra</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abou El-Khier</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Study of quorum-sensing LasR and RhlR genes and their dependent virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> isolates from infected burn wounds</article-title>. <source>Access Microbiol.</source>
<volume>3</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>000211</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/acmi.0.000211</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34151163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8209703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Imipenem with sub-inhibitory concentration enhances biofilm formation of drug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii by affecting type ⅳ pili</article-title>. <source>J. third Mil. Med. Univ.</source>
<volume>40</volume> (<issue>21</issue>), <fpage>1967</fpage>–<lpage>1972</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16016/j.1000-5404.201808141</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farshadzadeh</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoja</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pourhajibagher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haghighi</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Growth rate and biofilm formation ability of clinical and laboratory-evolved colistin-resistant strains of acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00153</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29483899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5816052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Enhanced<italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> antimicrobial activity of amphotericin B with berberine against dual‐species biofilms of candida albicans and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>130</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1154</fpage>–<lpage>1172</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.14872</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32996236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzzo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scognamiglio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buommino</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Abrosca</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Plant derived natural products against <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>: Antibiofilm activity and molecular mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<volume>25</volume> (<issue>21</issue>), <fpage>5024</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25215024</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33138250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7663672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobenchik</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hindler</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuetz</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Overview of changes to the clinical and laboratory standards institute performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing, M100, 31st edition</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>e0021321</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00213-21</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8601225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34550809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>V. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Quorum sensing inhibitors: An overview</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source>
<volume>31</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2012.10.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23142623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Biology of acinetobacter baumannii: Pathogenesis, antibiotic resistance mechanisms, and prospective treatment options</article-title>. <source>Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2017.00055</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28348979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5346588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Ginkgolic acids and Ginkgo biloba extract inhibit <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</source>
<volume>174</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.12.030</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24457153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Letsididi</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Letsididi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Inhibitive effect of Eugenol and its nanoemulsion on quorum sensing–mediated virulence factors and biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J. Food Prot.</source>
<volume>82</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-18-196</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30785306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z. X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Enhancing pili assembly and biofilm formation in Acinetobacter baumannii ATCC19606 using non-native acyl-homoserine lactones</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol.</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>62</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-015-0397-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4381447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirghani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saba</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaliq</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Biofilms: Formation, drug resistance and alternatives to conventional approaches</article-title>. <source>AIMS Microbiol.</source>
<volume>8</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/microbiol.2022019</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36317001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9576500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwer</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboshanab</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboulwafa</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Propranolol, chlorpromazine and diclofenac restore susceptibility of extensively drug-resistant (XDR) Acinetobacter baumannii to fluoroquinolones</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>e0238195</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0238195</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32845920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7449414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulani</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamble</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumkar</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tawre</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pardesi</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Emerging strategies to combat ESKAPE pathogens in the era of antimicrobial resistance: A review</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>1</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>00539</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00539</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6452778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30988669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Navidifar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Effects of sub-inhibitory concentrations of meropenem and tigecycline on the expression of genes regulating pili, efflux pumps and virulence factors involved in biofilm formation by Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source>Infect. Drug Resist</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S199993</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6512781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31190904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>AbaR is a LuxR-type regulator essential for motility and the formation of biofilm and pellicle in Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source>Genes and Genomics</source>
<volume>42</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>1339</fpage>–<lpage>1346</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13258-020-01005-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33025548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Quorum quenching activity of pentacyclic triterpenoids leads to inhibition of biofilm formation by Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source>Biofouling</source>
<volume>36</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>922</fpage>–<lpage>937</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08927014.2020.1831480</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33103466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pejin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciric</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markovic</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glamoclija</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanimirovic</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Quercetin potently reduces biofilm formation of the strain <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Curr. Pharm. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>16</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>733</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389201016666150505121951</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25941888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> activity of biofilm inhibitors in combination with antibacterial drugs against extensively drug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>18097</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-75218-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33093606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7581519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rekha</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasavi</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vipin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saptami</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arun</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>A medicinal herbCassia alata attenuates quorum sensing inChromobacterium violaceum and pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title>. <source>Lett. Appl. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>64</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/lam.12710</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28035685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaaban</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elgaml</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Biotechnological applications of quorum sensing inhibition as novel therapeutic strategies for multidrug resistant pathogens</article-title>. <source>Microb. Pathog.</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.11.043</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30503958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Inhibition of virulence factors and biofilm formation by wogonin attenuates pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 via targeting pqs quorum-sensing system</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source>
<volume>22</volume> (<issue>23</issue>), <fpage>12699</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms222312699</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34884499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8657757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warrier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satyamoorthy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murali</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Quorum-sensing regulation of virulence factors in bacterial biofilm</article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1003</fpage>–<lpage>1021</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb-2020-0301</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34414776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Quorum sensing for population-level control of bacteria and potential therapeutic applications</article-title>. <source>Cell. Mol. Life Sci.</source>
<volume>77</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1319</fpage>–<lpage>1343</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-019-03326-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31612240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11104945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Surviving as a community: Antibiotic tolerance and persistence in bacterial biofilms</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>26</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2019.06.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31295420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6629468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Sodium New houttuyfonate affects transcriptome and virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> controlled by quorum sensing</article-title>. <source>Front. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>572375</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2020.572375</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33123010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7566558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H. Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z. Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>A. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Hordenine: A novel quorum sensing inhibitor and antibiofilm agent against pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title>. <source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source>
<volume>66</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1620</fpage>–<lpage>1628</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.7b05035</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29353476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>